<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>oai:elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de:2700</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:54:540</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">All-Conjugated Diblock Copolyelectrolytes</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Gutacker, Andrea</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2018-01-22</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/chemie/diss2011/gutacker</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=2700</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20120403-101217-5</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-2847/dc1125.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;p&gt;Within this thesis, new all-conjugated, cationic diblock copolyelectrolytes, based on&#13;
polyfluorene and polythiophene blocks, have been successfully synthesized. Their&#13;
photophysical properties and aggregation behavior have been studied in solution and in the&#13;
solid state. Especially PF2/6-&lt;i&gt;b&lt;/i&gt;-P3MAHT shows a significant solvatochromatic effect in&#13;
THF/water mixtures. Bilayer-based vesicles (polymersomes) with diameters of several&#13;
microns have been observed for PF2/6-&lt;i&gt;b&lt;/i&gt;-P3PyHT and PF2/6-&lt;i&gt;b&lt;/i&gt;-P3TMAHT diblock&#13;
copolymers. Using solvents of different polarity (THF versus methanol) leads to a tunable&#13;
self-assembly for PF6NBr-&lt;i&gt;b&lt;/i&gt;-PFO with a different arrangement of the components within the&#13;
vesicle walls. Because of the resulting control on the formed nano-scaled arrangement CPEs&#13;
are also promising materials for an incorporation into optoelectronic devices. The application&#13;
of P3TMAHT and PF2/6-&lt;i&gt;b&lt;/i&gt;-P3TMAHT as thin electron extraction layers of BHJ-type organic&#13;
solar cells leads to an increase of the PCE from ca. 5.3 to ca. 6.5%. Further on, PF6NBr-&lt;i&gt;b&lt;/i&gt;-&#13;
PFO has been used as thin electron injection layer of OLEDs. Such CPEs are promising&#13;
candidates for improving the electron injection into the organic layers of OLEDs.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Furthermore, ionic surfactants, organic acids or biomolecules as DNA lead to a selective&#13;
quenching and/or a characteristic red shift of the polythiophene-based emission band of&#13;
PF2/6-&lt;i&gt;b&lt;/i&gt;-P3TMAHT in due to a conformational re-organization. In this perspective PF2/6-&lt;i&gt;b&lt;/i&gt;-&#13;
P3TMAHT seems to be a very attractive material for sensors/biosensor applications.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 540 Chemie » 540 Chemie und zugeordnete Wissenschaften</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Chemie » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>