<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>oai:elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de:2407</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:53:530</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">Properties of confined and unconfined water</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">A computer simulation study at ambient and supercooled conditions</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Guse, Christa</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2018-01-22</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/physik/diss2011/guse</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=2407</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20111125-120831-6</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-2564/dc1116.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this work is to add to the long lasting efforts to provide an unified picture of the properties of confined and unconfined water. Water is an ubiquitous substance with special importance for geological and biological as well as technical processes. There are 1.4 billion km&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; of water on earth, most of it in liquid form, 0.001% as vapor in the atmosphere and 1.8% as ice (mainly crystalline hexagonal ice I&lt;sub&gt;&lt;i&gt;h&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;) frozen at the poles and in Greenland [1]. But water can also exist in an amorphous form, which is produced by rapidly cooling liquid water and constitutes the most common structure of H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O in the universe.&lt;p&gt;&#13;
In addition to its rich and complicated phase structure, water exhibits several interesting properties which differ from those of "normal liquids". These anomalies include for instance the heat capacity minimum, the compressibility minimum, the viscosity minimum and the density maximum [2]. Although most of water's anomalies were already well established at the beginning of the 20th century, to this day there neither exists an accepted theory explaining all the different anomalies nor is the phase diagram known in the full temperature and pressure regime.&lt;p&gt;&#13;
Despite numerous proposals for a universal theory of water, progress has been slow. Mainly because the main distinctive features of the different models appear in the socalled "no man's land" of water's phase space, between the temperature of homogeneous nucleation and the crystallization temperature between 150 and 236 K at ambient pressure [3]. Bulk water crystallizes in this region making experimental investigations on liquid water impossible.&lt;p&gt;&#13;
To circumvent this problem, a number of experiments have been performed on confined water, which can be supercooled below the homogeneous nucleation temperature without crystallization. But the question remains in how far results obtained under confined conditions are transferable to bulk water [4].&lt;p&gt;&#13;
In contrast to experiments computer simulations are feasible in the "no man's land". In this case the limitations of simulation studies regarding system size and observation time are of advantage, because they prevent crystallization. Thus simulation studies can help to add pieces to the puzzle of water's anomalies by helping to interpret experimental results and to test the different proposed theoretical scenarios [5].&lt;p&gt;&#13;
In this work simulations of rigid classical water models are used to investigate the properties of bulk water and water confined in single walled carbon nanotubes.&lt;p&gt;&#13;
While today there exist a number of water models that perform exceptionally well in reproducing experimental results, the models themselves exhibit a complexity and diversity in phase behavior as well as in structure that makes it difficult, to draw conclusions for actual water from them.&lt;p&gt;&#13;
It is therefore important to test different models and to gain knowledge of their characteristics and limitations in order to assess their relevance.&lt;p&gt;&#13;
Regarding the bulk simulations our interest lay mainly in the connection between the structural features that result in the density maximum of water and their manifestation in the coherent x-ray scattering intensities as it is observed experimentally.&lt;p&gt;&#13;
We therefore computed scattering intensities for a number of different water models and compared them to experimental ones. It turns out that the best results regarding density, diffusion and intensity curves can be achieved with the TIP4P/2005 model, which shows the least change in the hydrogen bond network with temperature, while most other models seem to overestimate structural development.&lt;p&gt;&#13;
As there is a special interest in the small-angle scattering, which is clouded by some experimental controversy, we simulated large systems at small temperatures to gather additional information in this region. We find that our simulations can reproduce the experimentally observed enhancement of the intensity curves without showing any large scale density fluctuations.&lt;p&gt;&#13;
For the observation of water in confinement, carbon nanotubes possess theadvantage of a relatively week interaction with H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O molecules, which may not influence the hydrogen bonding too much. In order to gain an overview of the general behavior of water in these geometries we investigated a vast range of temperatures, pressures and tube diameters. We put our emphasis on the structural and transport properties of water as well as on its phase behavior. We compute density profiles, pair correlation functions and energy by grand-canonical Monte Carlo and determine the diffusion constant parallel and perpendicular to the tube axis by molecular dynamics simulations.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 530 Physik » 530 Physik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Physik » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>