<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>oai:elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de:11080</id><datestamp>2020-11-05</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:53</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">Analog Hadronic Calorimeter for a Future Linear Collider</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Elkhalii, Amine</dc:creator>
          <dc:contributor>Zeitnitz, Christian</dc:contributor>
          <dc:date>2020-11-05</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/physik/diss2020/elkhalii</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=11080</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20201103-123225-7</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.25926/2jx6-f298</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-10378/dc2014.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;p&gt;The work of this thesis is a part of the CALICE collaboration project, which develops calorimeters for a future e+e- linear collider. These calorimeters have a high granularity to allow Particle Flow Analysis and achieve a jet energy resolution of 3-4 %. One of these concepts is the Analog Hadronic Calorimeter (AHCAL) based on 3x3x0.3 cm3 scintillator tiles with individual Silicon Photo-multiplier (SiPM) readout. A former physics prototype of the AHCAL has proven the performance and suitability of such a concept. A second generation technological prototype of 39 layers with a 1.7 cm steel absorber has been constructed and commissioned by several institutes. A massive amount of components has been tested before the assembly, including the SPIROC ASIC developed by Omega. This chip provides the readout for 36 SiPMs, including individual bias voltages, self-triggering, timing measurements, and 12-bit signal resolution, while maintaining a low power consumption of 25 μW per channel. A test stand has been designed and developed for testing the SPIROC2E, and around 625 working chips are assembled successfully to AHCAL Front-end Electronics. The test beam of the prototype has been performed during two periods in May and June 2018 in H2 beamline at the CERN SPS. Around 8 to 10 x 107 events from muon, electron, and pion have been collected with different energy ranges. After a successful detector calibration, the electromagnetic response of the AHCAL is studied with electrons and a good electromagnetic energy resolution of (22.6 %)/(√E)  ⊕ 1%  is achieved.</dc:description>
          <dc:rights>Alle Rechte vorbehalten</dc:rights>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 530 Physik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Physik » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>