<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>10040</id><datestamp>2019-12-05</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:51</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">General Extrapolation Spaces and Perturbations of Bi-Continuous Semigroups</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Budde, Christian</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2019-12-05</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/mathematik/diss2019/budde</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=10040</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20191205-110300-4</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.25926/7ss7-bt33</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-9359/dc1937.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;p&gt;A lot of well-known partial differential equations modeling physical systems, such as the heat&#13;
equation, the Schrödinger equation or the wave equation, use temporal change of states. Evolution&#13;
equation is an umbrella term for such equations that can be interpreted as differential&#13;
laws describing the development of a system or as a mathematical treatment of motion in&#13;
time. With a solution of an evolution equation, one can predict the future of the corresponding&#13;
physical system which makes it deterministic. Evolution equations can be treated by an&#13;
operator theoretical approach. They can be rewritten as so-called abstract Cauchy problems which&#13;
are connected to strongly continuous operator semigroups on Banach spaces. However, &#13;
Stochastic differential equations, Ornstein–Uhlenbeck processes or Feller processes, give rise to&#13;
transition semigroups which are in general not strongly continuous. Here bi-continuous semigroups&#13;
come into play, which form in fact the key subject of this thesis. The research on bi-continuous&#13;
semigroups was motivated by the work of F. Kühnemund. In fact, she was the initiator for the&#13;
development of the theory of bi-continuous semigroups. The main idea is to equip the underlying&#13;
Banach space, on which the corresponding semigroup fails to be strongly continuous with respect&#13;
to the norm, with an additional locally convex topology, which is compatible with the norm topology, &#13;
such that the semigroup becomes strongly continuous with respect to this locally convex topology.&#13;
The work of F. Kühnemund was followed by research by B. Farkas. He investigated perturbation&#13;
theory for bi-continuous semigroups. In this thesis we introduce the concept of bi-continuous&#13;
semigroups and the underlying structure, study the construction of extrapolation and intermediate&#13;
spaces of non-densely defined operators, discuss different perturbation type theorems for&#13;
bi-continuous semigroups and consider flows on networks in connection with bi-continuous semigroups.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 510 Mathematik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Mathematik und Informatik » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>