<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>10370</id><datestamp>2020-03-12</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:54:540</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">Theoretical Investigations on Cluster Formation in Mass Spectrometry</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Haack, Alexander</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2020-03-12</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/chemie/diss2020/haack</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=10370</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20200312-111139-2</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.25926/x68p-cx61</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-9688/dc2001.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;p&gt;The thermochemistry and reaction dynamics of polar gas phase molecules clustering around an ion in atmospheric pressure ionization &#13;
&#13;
mass spectrometry (API-MS) dominate many observed effects. While the equilibrium conditions under elevated pressure conditions determine &#13;
&#13;
the distribution of the available charges inside different clusters, the reaction dynamics under non-equilibrium conditions downstream of &#13;
&#13;
the instrument will determine the ultimate fate of these clusters. Together, this will dictate the final degree of charging (e.g., &#13;
&#13;
protonation) of the analyte.&#13;
	&#13;
&lt;p&gt;In this work, two examples of the effect of clustering in MS are studied by using Computational Chemistry. In the first example, &#13;
&#13;
charge depletion and charge retention in nanoESI-MS for a small peptide, Substance P, is investigated. By modeling the thermochemical &#13;
&#13;
data and potential energy paths for proton transfer (PT), it is shown that protic solvent vapors like methanol (MeOH) can abstract a &#13;
&#13;
proton from the multiply charged peptide. This is due to their ability to form hydrogen bond networks. The resulting charge dilution upon &#13;
&#13;
increasing cluster sizes lowers barrier heights along the PT paths. Aprotic solvent molecules as for example acetonitrile (ACN), however, &#13;
&#13;
lack the ability to form cluster networks at the charge site. Thus, there is no trend observed regarding the barrier heights for PT. The &#13;
&#13;
charge is thus retained and not depleted. This is in accordance with experimental findings, where Substance P is observed in its 3+ &#13;
&#13;
charge state when ACN is added to the gas phase, but is found mainly in its 2+ charge state with MeOH vapor added.&#13;
	&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The second example deals with the effect of dynamic clustering in differential mobility spectrometry. This is done by modeling the &#13;
&#13;
geometry, temperature dependent collision cross section (CCS), and electrical field dependent ion temperature and mobility of many &#13;
&#13;
cluster structures in the framework of the Mason-Schamp equation applying the two-temperature theory. Thermochemical weighting yield the &#13;
&#13;
cluster size distribution and ensemble averaged mobility in dependence of the field strength. It is shown that increasing the field &#13;
&#13;
strength leads to higher ion temperatures and subsequent evaporation of the solvent molecules, which are firmly bound at low field &#13;
&#13;
strengths. This leads to an overall decrease of CCS and thus to an increase of mobility. Calculating dispersion plots from these data and &#13;
&#13;
comparison with experimental results, semi-quantitative agreement is found. Especially the good accordance with trends observed regarding &#13;
&#13;
different solvents, the background temperature and the solvent vapor concentration highlights the importance of dynamic clustering for &#13;
&#13;
differential mobility. The importance of correctly modeling the CCS as a function of temperature and using two-temperature theory to &#13;
&#13;
model the "hard-sphere" effect is also emphasized.&#13;
&#13;
&lt;p&gt;From these two case studies, it becomes apparent that the thermochemical stability of cluster systems needs to be considered. However, &#13;
&#13;
a strong obstruction in the modeling of these cases is the breakdown of the harmonic approximation (HA) usually used in the calculations. &#13;
&#13;
Due to their loosely bound nature, anharmonic effects gain significance. Two new approaches are presented in this work to account for &#13;
&#13;
these effects for a more accurate description of the thermochemistry. The first uses the well known Vibrational Perturbation Theory to &#13;
&#13;
2&lt;sup&gt;nd&lt;/sup&gt; order (VPT2) in a hybrid approach. To reduce computational time, only the harmonic contributions are calculated with high &#13;
&#13;
accuracy, while the minor anharmonic effects are calculated with faster, less accurate methods. The second approach uses a modified &#13;
&#13;
version of the quasi-harmonic approximation (QHA). Instead of using Cartesian or internal coordinates, the configurational distribution, &#13;
&#13;
obtained from molecular dynamics (MD) simulations, is represented in normal coordinates. Overall translation, overall rotation and &#13;
&#13;
internal rotations are projected out of the MD trajectories by enforcing explicitly the Eckart-Sayvetz conditions for these motions, &#13;
&#13;
leaving only true vibrational movement. Both developed methods were tested by calculating the dissociation enthalpies of different proton &#13;
&#13;
bound cluster systems. Comparison with standard methods regarding experimental results showed that both methods have similar or better &#13;
&#13;
accuracy than the HA. Similar accuracy is only achieved for challenging cases with many internal rotations or very flexible structures. &#13;
&#13;
Here, the developed methods as well as the HA exhibit significant deviations from experimental results. Thus, the two methods capture the &#13;
&#13;
anharmonic effects to some degree and perform better than the HA for systems of small to medium anharmonicity. For strongly anharmonic &#13;
&#13;
systems their performance has room for improvement.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 540 Chemie » 540 Chemie und zugeordnete Wissenschaften</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Chemie » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>