<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>10551</id><datestamp>2020-06-02</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:53:530</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">Retrieval of atmospheric quantities from remote sensing measurements of nightglow emissions in the MLT region</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Chen, Qiuyu</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2020-06-02</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/physik/diss2020/chen</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=10551</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20200602-131802-0</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.25926/w7ds-9196</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-9840/dc2004.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;p&gt;In the mesosphere and lower thermosphere (MLT) region, atomic oxygen and hydrogen&#13;
are the most abundant reactive trace species and play crucial roles in the photochemistry&#13;
and energy budget. Meanwhile, the MLT region is profoundly influenced by&#13;
atmospheric dynamics, and tides and gravity waves are the key features thereof, which&#13;
can be characterized by, e.g., temperature distributions and variations. A common way&#13;
for the detection of these atmospheric quantities in the MLT region is by means of remote&#13;
sensing of airglow emissions from ground or space.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
&#13;
The aim of this work is to offer new insight into atmospheric parameters and distributions&#13;
in the MLT region. It is focused on constituent and temperature sounding of&#13;
this region, and presents the retrieval and analysis of atomic oxygen and hydrogen as&#13;
well as temperature profiles from hydroxyl (OH) and oxygen atmospheric band (O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; &#13;
&#13;
Aband)&#13;
nightglow observations. Atomic oxygen and hydrogen abundances are obtained&#13;
from satellite limb radiance measurements of nightglow emissions in the near-infrared&#13;
region. Temperature profiles are inferred from the rotational structure of nightglow&#13;
emission lines in a broad spectral region, including observation data from a groundbased&#13;
instrument and also in-orbit validation data from a new instrument applying the&#13;
Spatial Heterodyne Interferometer (SHI) technology.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
&#13;
A new dataset of nighttime atomic oxygen density [O] and atomic hydrogen density&#13;
[H] is derived from the OH(8-4) band emission. The dataset is derived from the atmospheric&#13;
background radiation observed by the Global Ozone Monitoring by Occultation&#13;
of Stars (GOMOS) instrument aboard Envisat and with measurements of the Sounding&#13;
of the Atmosphere using Broadband Emission Radiometry (SABER) instrument aboard&#13;
the Thermosphere Ionosphere Mesosphere Energetics and Dynamics (TIMED) satellite&#13;
for the atmospheric background. Raw data are reprocessed into monthly zonal mean&#13;
values. The dataset spans from 70° S to 70° N in latitude and from 80 km to 100 km in&#13;
altitude, covering a time period from May 2002 to December 2011 at local times from&#13;
10 p.m. to 12 p.m.. The atomic oxygen density peaks at about 95 km and the maximum&#13;
concentration is in the range of 3-8 x 10&lt;sup&gt;11&lt;/sup&gt; atoms cm&lt;sup&gt;-3&lt;/sup&gt;, while the atomic &#13;
&#13;
hydrogen density&#13;
reaches the peak at around 83 km with a value of 1-4 x 10&lt;sup&gt;8&lt;/sup&gt; atoms cm&lt;sup&gt;-3&lt;/sup&gt;, &#13;
&#13;
depending&#13;
on latitude and season. The annual oscillation (AO), semiannual oscillation (SAO) and&#13;
the solar cycle impact are clearly visible in the data. This new GOMOS dataset conforms&#13;
to other published datasets and is consistent with the [O] and [H] datasets obtained&#13;
from the Scanning Imaging Absorption Spectrometer for Atmospheric CHartographY&#13;
(SCIAMACHY) OH airglow measurements within ± 20 %.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
&#13;
The nocturnal mesospheric temperature is obtained from ground-based measurements&#13;
of the OH(3-1) band emission layer centered near 87 km. The temperature dataset&#13;
is derived from observations by the GRound-based Infrared P-Branch Spectrometer&#13;
(GRIPS-F) instrument located inWuppertal. The temperature profiles fluctuate over the&#13;
course of night, and the absolute amplitude is varying with season.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
&#13;
For space-based atmospheric observations, a growing trend are miniaturized instruments,&#13;
which can fly on a nano-satellite platform, e.g., CubeSat. The SHI is a promising&#13;
technology which fits into this context. With this technology, a minimized limb sounder,&#13;
Atmospheric Spatial Heterodyne Interferometer Next Exploration (AtmoSHINE), is developed&#13;
in our research group for temperature detection in the MLT region. An in-orbit&#13;
demonstration was conducted and the first data analysis is presented herein. The global&#13;
temperature distribution for the mesopause region is retrieved from measurements of&#13;
O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; A-band nightglow emissions. The AtmoSHINE measurements are acquired from&#13;
four in-orbit tests of the commissioning phase, and the regular observation period of&#13;
four days. The derived temperature profiles cover the altitude region of around 84 to 96&#13;
km with a vertical resolution of 2 km, and its vertical distribution reaches, as expected,&#13;
its minimum value near the mesopause region. Intercomparisons of the AtmoSHINE&#13;
measurements with the coincident Optical Spectrograph and Infrared Imager System&#13;
(OSIRIS) and SABER measurements indicate a general consistency in the observed&#13;
limb radiances and derived temperature profiles.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 530 Physik » 530 Physik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Physik » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>