<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>10700</id><datestamp>2020-07-23</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:6</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="de">Untersuchung der mikrostrukturellen Stabilität in Relation mit der Wasserstoffversprödung von austenitischen FeCrNi-Legierungen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Fussik, Robert</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2020-07-23</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbd/maschinenbau/diss2020/fussik</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=10700</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20200723-103552-5</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.25926/4anw-x449</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-9997/dd2004.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;p&gt;&#13;
&#13;
Austenitic stainless CrNi-steels are generally known as non-sensitive to hydrogen embrittlement. However,&#13;
this only applies to stable systems. In contrast, unstable CrNi-steels are characterized by a low&#13;
thermal stability of the austenitic matrix and convert into bcc α'-martensite by external thermally&#13;
and/or mechanically induced strain. This is accompanied by a significant increase in strength, and&#13;
high susceptibility to an early failure of the unstable CrNi-steels under H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; atmosphere. In this context,&#13;
the present work deals essentially with the effect of deformation-induced phase transformation&#13;
on the mechanical properties at room temperature (RT), both in air and under H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; compressed gas&#13;
atmosphere. In addition to the macrostructural properties, the microstructural properties with respect&#13;
to the local phase stability are considered. In particular, the influence of the chemical constitution on&#13;
the global and local stability, starting from solidification, is investigated.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
The experimental investigations were carried out using commercial steels of type AISI 304L (EN&#13;
1.4307) and AISI 316L (EN 1.4435). Beyond that, modifications based on steels of the AISI grades&#13;
304, 305 and 316 were analyzed. Mechanical material testing was essentially carried out using uniaxial&#13;
tensile tests at RT in air and under H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; compressed gas atmosphere. The cyclic tensile tests in&#13;
air were used to analyze the α'-martensite generated as a function of strain, which was determined&#13;
using feritscope measurements. X-ray diffraction tests were used to identify all phases and quantify&#13;
their amounts before and after material failure. Moreover, X-ray diffraction was used to determine&#13;
experimentally the stacking fault energy (SFE) at RT. All microstructure analyses were performed&#13;
using light and scanning electron microscopy by using of the energy dispersive X-ray spectroscopy.&#13;
The latter were also used for the microstructural investigation of the local element distribution. To&#13;
estimate the global and local austenite stability, empirical equations as well as thermodynamic calculation&#13;
approaches using Thermo-Calc software were used.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
The matrix of unstable austenitic CrNi-steels with a dominant content of α'-martensite after material&#13;
failure, converts both directly and indirectly via the intermediate stage of the ε-martensite to&#13;
α'-martensite. If no deformation-induced ε-martensite occurs during deformation, the formed amount&#13;
of α'-martensite is significantly lower. It was therefore concluded that the existence of ε-martensite&#13;
must be responsible for the significant increase in the α'-martensite amount. In addition, the existence&#13;
of ε-martensite is linked to the SFE of the alloy under consideration. Unstable austenitic CrNi-steels&#13;
with an SFE ≤20 mJ/m&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; tend to undergo an indirect γ→ε→α' transformation under mechanical stress,&#13;
while austenitic CrNi-steels with an SFE &gt;20 mJ/m&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; tend to a undergo direct γ→α' transformation.&#13;
With increasing SFE, the propensity to α'-martensite formation decreases significantly, so that above&#13;
an SFE of about 26 mJ/m&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; the martensitic phase transformation is significantly inhibited or even completely&#13;
suppressed. Under the assumption that atomically dissolved hydrogen in the fcc crystal lattice&#13;
reduces the SFE of CrNi-steels, the increase in α'-martensite under H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; atmosphere could be explained.&#13;
Accordingly, the hydrogen penetrated into the steel must reduce the SFE to values below 20 mJ/m&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;,&#13;
which in turn allows ε-martensite to form and ultimately leads to higher α'-martensite contents due&#13;
to the γ→ε→α' conversion sequence. Commercially produced CrNi-steels show local concentration&#13;
differences of the alloying elements. These microsegregations are responsible for the inhomogeneous&#13;
distribution of the local properties. This also includes the local phase stability, which significantly&#13;
influences the global properties. In this context, it could be shown that a global consideration of the&#13;
austenite stability of low-alloyed unstable austenitic CrNi-steels is not sufficient to assess the susceptibility&#13;
to hydrogen embrittlement. Regarding a thermal reduction of the concentration gradients,&#13;
it was established that microsegregations in technically relevant process times cannot be completely&#13;
eliminated by heat treatment. However, taking solidification simulations into account, it was shown&#13;
that the degree of segregation of Cr and Ni is lower the more single-phase the primary solidification&#13;
from the melt takes place. Primary ferritic solidification favors a compensation of austenite stability&#13;
between segregated areas due to the dominantly contrary segregation of alloying elements. The most&#13;
pronounced local concentration differences were observed in alloys with balanced amounts with respect&#13;
to the ferritic or austenitic phases. The decisive factor is therefore a dominant single-phase solidifying&#13;
amount of either austenite or ferrite of more then 50 Vol.-%. The key finding of this work is that a&#13;
high and homogeneously distributed austenite stability, taking into account all alloying elements, has&#13;
a beneficial effect on the resistance of austenitic CrNi steels to hydrogen-induced embrittlement.-+</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>600 Technik, Medizin, angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Maschinenbau und Sicherheitstechnik » Maschinenbau » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>