<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>10951</id><datestamp>2020-09-21</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:57:570</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">The identification of botanical and zoological origins of different honeydew honeys</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Shaaban, Basel</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2020-09-21</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/biologie/diss2020/shaaban</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=10951</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20200921-104750-2</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.25926/mesk-c384</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-10244/dc2013.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;p&gt;Honeydew honey is produced by bees from excretions – the honeydew – of plant-sucking&#13;
insects. Honeydew can be produced by different insect-species, such as the genera Cinara and&#13;
Physokermes on conifers and the genera Eucallipterus on lime trees. Therefore, honeydew&#13;
honey can stem from different botanical as well as different zoological origins. In order to&#13;
investigate the process from phloem sap to honeydew, honeydew samples from different&#13;
Hemipteran species were collected and the sugar, amino acid, and inorganic ion profiles were&#13;
determined. Honeydew from all species contains different proportions of hexoses, sucrose,&#13;
melezitose, erlose, and trehalose, whereas the phloem exudates of the host trees contain no&#13;
trisaccharide. That was confirmed by incubating whole-body homogenates of different aphid&#13;
species with sucrose, the outcome of which was melezitose and erlose. Additionally, the&#13;
classification of honeydew samples on the basis of their sugar profiles showed that the&#13;
proportions of sugars differed significantly between different hemipteran species feeding on the&#13;
same tree species. Moreover, statistical analyses reveal that the sugar composition of honeydew&#13;
is determined more by the hemipteran species than by the host plant.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
In order to identify the botanical and zoological origin of honeydew honey, fir, spruce, and pine&#13;
honey samples were collected and analyzed. Fir and spruce samples were collected in different&#13;
locations in south Germany, pine honey samples were collected in Turkey. Pine honeys can be&#13;
separated from fir and spruce honey because of their high contents of (undef 3) sugar and&#13;
inorganic ions. In addition, fir and spruce honey can be divided in three groups:&#13;
Physokermes/spruce, Cinara/spruce, and Cinara/fir. Physokermes/spruce honey also has a&#13;
significantly higher content of phosphate and (undef 6) sugar than the other two honeys. To&#13;
reliably distinguish between fir/Cinara and spruce/Cinara honey, however, no chemical marker&#13;
was found within the analyzed compounds.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
In order to clarify the origin of linden honey, sugars, amino acids, and inorganic ions, profiles&#13;
for honeydew, nectar, and honey from Tilia sp. were determined. Melezitose and erlose were&#13;
determined in the honeydew and in the honey, but not in the nectar. In addition, the incubation&#13;
of whole-body homogenates of different aphid species with sucrose, resulting in melezitose and&#13;
erlose, confirmed our results. Finally, the ability of honeybees’ cleavage enzymes to digest&#13;
melezitose was also investigated. Honeybees’ abdomen enzymes are able to cleave melezitose&#13;
and produce glucose and fructose; this process, however, is not as efficient as the cleavage of&#13;
sucrose.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="de">&lt;p&gt;Honigtauhonig wird von Bienen aus den Ausscheidungen – dem Honigtau – von&#13;
pflanzensaugenden Insekten hergestellt. Honigtau wird von verschiedenen Insektenarten&#13;
produziert, z.B. von den Gattungen Cinara und Physokermes auf Nadelbäumen. Honigtauhonig&#13;
kann daher sowohl von verschiedenen botanischen als auch verschiedenen zoologischen&#13;
Herkünften stammen. Um die Umwandlungsprozesse von Phloemsaft zu Honigtau zu&#13;
untersuchen, wurden Honigtauproben von verschiedenen Hemipteren-Arten gesammelt und die&#13;
Zucker-, Aminosäure- und anorganischen Ionenprofile erstellt. Honigtau von allen Arten&#13;
enthielt unterschiedliche Anteile an Hexosen, Saccharose, Melezitose, Erlose und Trehalose,&#13;
während die Phloem-Exsudate der Wirtsbäume keine Trisaccharide enthielten. Dies wurde&#13;
durch die Inkubation von Ganzkörperhomogenaten verschiedener Blattlausarten mit&#13;
Saccharose und den daraus resultierenden Trisacchariden Melezitose und Erlose bestätigt.&#13;
Zusätzlich wurden Honigtauproben aufgrund ihrer Zuckerprofile klassifiziert. Die&#13;
Zuckeranteile unterschieden sich signifikant zwischen unterschiedlichen Lausarten, die sich&#13;
von der gleichen Baumart ernährten. Darüber hinaus zeigen statistische Analysen, dass die&#13;
Zuckerzusammensetzung von Honigtau eher durch die Lausarten als durch die Wirtspflanze&#13;
bestimmt wird.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
Um die botanische und zoologische Herkunft des Honigtauhonigs zu identifizieren, wurden&#13;
Tannen-, Fichten- und Kiefernhonigproben gesammelt und analysiert. Tannen- und&#13;
Fichtenhonigproben wurden an verschiedenen Orten in Süddeutschland gesammelt,&#13;
Kiefernhonigproben wurde in der Türkei gesammelt. Kiefernhonige konnten wegen ihres hohen&#13;
Gehalts an (undef 3) Zucker und anorganischen Ionen von Tannen- und Fichtenhonig&#13;
unterschieden werden. Darüber hinaus konnten Tannen- und Fichtenhonig in drei Gruppen&#13;
unterteilt werden: Physokermes/Fichte, Cinara/Fichte und Cinara/Tanne.&#13;
Physokermes/Fichtenhonig weist einen signifikant höheren Gehalt an Phosphat und (undef 6)&#13;
Zucker als die anderen beiden Honige auf. Jedoch wurde kein chemischer Marker innerhalb der&#13;
Kategorien der analysierten Verbindungen gefunden um verlässlich zwischen Tanne/Cinara&#13;
und Fichte/Cinara-Honig unterscheiden zu können.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
Zusätzlich wurde die Melizitose-Verdaufähigkeit der Spalt-Enzyme der Honigbienen&#13;
untersucht. Die Enzyme im Abdomen der Honigbiene sind in der Lage, Melezitose in Glukose&#13;
und Fruktose zu spalten, dies ist aber nicht so effizient wie die Spaltung von Saccharose.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 570 Biowissenschaften; Biologie » 570 Biowissenschaften; Biologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Biologie » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>