<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>oai:elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de:7511</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:57:570</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">Chloroplast Genome Diversity in the Phototrophic Euglenoids, with Emphasis on Genome Structure, Synteny and Intron Evolution</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Dabbagh, Nadja</dc:creator>
          <dc:contributor>Preisfeld, Angelika</dc:contributor>
          <dc:contributor>Preisfeld, Angelika</dc:contributor>
          <dc:contributor>Wägele, Heike</dc:contributor>
          <dc:contributor>Simon, Martin</dc:contributor>
          <dc:date>2018-01-22</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/biologie/diss2017/dabbagh</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=7511</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20171201-113132-6</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-7307/dc1725.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">To shed light on chloroplast genome evolution in the phototrophic euglenoids the cpGenomes of Euglena mutabilis (SAG 1224-9b), Trachelomonas grandis (SAG 204.80) and Eutreptiella pomquetensis (CCMP 1491) were isolated, sequenced and annotated. The chloroplast&#13;
genomes were investigated intensively and compared to other cpGenomes of phototrophic euglenoids, with special focus on genome size and structure, number and localization of&#13;
rRNA operons as well as introns. As a cause for genome size differences three major reasons&#13;
have been identified. First, the intergenic space between the cpGenomes of different taxa&#13;
varied greatly, even between closely related species. Second, the rRNA operon numbers&#13;
between different taxa were not uniform. Third, the different intron numbers and intron types&#13;
between different taxa led to the main reason for size differences in euglenoids cpGenomes.&#13;
Comprehensive trends of intron number and intron type have been detected in closely as well&#13;
as distantly related euglenoids. These trends can be used to explain intron density and quantity&#13;
as well as high or low similarities in the evolution of introns in all phototrophic euglenoids.&#13;
The expansion and evolution of psbC introns can partly be elucidated by assumed horizontal&#13;
intron transfers in the chloroplast of euglenoids after the split from Eutreptiales and&#13;
Euglenales.&#13;
Findings concerning the emergence and evolution of group III introns supported the&#13;
hypothesis that group III introns are degenerated group II introns. Surprisingly, the&#13;
cpGenomes of the basally branching Eutreptiales are free of group III introns, although the&#13;
results indicated that their evolution began in Eutreptiales as intermediate stages of group II&#13;
and III introns (mini group II introns).&#13;
Furthermore, a new phylogenomic analysis of phototrophic euglenoids was performed and&#13;
compared to recently published phylogenetic analyses. As a new approach genome-level&#13;
characters from all known cpGenomes of euglenoids have been used as a tool to complement&#13;
the phylogenomic analysis. Metacharacter analyses yielded gene arrangement, cluster&#13;
arrangement and rRNA operons as viable metacharacters with partly important modifications&#13;
between the taxa. Significant cluster rearrangement was identified in several clades that&#13;
matched the phylogenetic reconstruction. Using the rRNA operon as a metacharacter revealed&#13;
a trend of loss of one rRNA copy following the diversification of Euglenales. Basally&#13;
branching Eutreptiales contained two copies, which is identical to the structure in the surmised chloroplast donor Pyramimonas parkeae. Only for both Euglena gracilis species&#13;
and Strombomonas acuminata an independent acquirement of further rRNA operons was&#13;
recognizable.&#13;
The cpGenome of Eutreptiella pomquetensis showed the same quadripartite cpGenome&#13;
structure as Pyramimonas parkeae, corroborating the close relationship between these two&#13;
taxa. The present work provides a sound basis for further examinations of chloroplast genome&#13;
analyses to get a more thorough understanding of intron evolution within the phototrophic&#13;
euglenoids. Likewise it represents a precursor for future studies concerning genome-level&#13;
features in phototrophic euglenoids.</dc:description>
          <dc:source xml:lang="de">Die Dissertation enthält Material folgender Quellen:&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#13;
Journal of Eukaryotic Microbiology 2016, 0, 1–14&lt;br&gt;&#13;
doi:10.1111/jeu.12334&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#13;
Dabbagh et al. (2017), &lt;br&gt;Chloroplast genome expansion by intron multiplication in the basal psychrophilic euglenoid&#13;
Eutreptiella pomquetensis. &lt;br&gt;PeerJ 5:e3725; DOI 10.7717/peerj.3725</dc:source>
          <dc:subject>Chloroplast</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Genome</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Phototrophic Euglenoids</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Introns</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 570 Biowissenschaften; Biologie » 570 Biowissenschaften; Biologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Biologie » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>