<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>11090</id><datestamp>2022-03-14</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:54:540</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">Formation of highly oxygenated organic molecules from α-pinene photochemistry</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Kang, Sungah</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2022-03-14</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/chemie/diss2020/kang</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=11090</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20201110-122057-9</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.25926/rd20-nb07</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-14934/dc2016.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;p&gt;Understanding secondary organic aerosols (SOA) is important because of their impact on climate and human health. However, SOA formation mechanisms and SOA precursors are still&#13;
not very well known. Among the precursors of SOA, highly oxygenated organic molecules (HOM) are considered as a significant contributor to SOA formation. HOM are known to&#13;
have a high O:C ratio which allows them to have low to extremely low vapour pressures. The high O:C ratio is achieved by a process called autoxidation. Autoxidation comprises a series of&#13;
intramolecular H-shifts in peroxy radicals followed by O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; addition while preserving the peroxy functionality.&#13;
&#13;
&lt;p&gt;α-pinene is an important biogenic volatile organic compound. It contributes the largest fraction to monoterpene emissions by plants and it reacts with OH radicals which is the major&#13;
oxidant during daytime. Therefore, an understanding of α-pinene photooxidation is crucial. In this study, the formation of HOM from oxidation of α-pinene by OH was investigated. HOM&#13;
were observed by Chemical Ionisation high resolution Time of Flight Mass Spectrometry (CIToF-MS). Four factors were varied in the reaction system: OH concentration, CO addition,&#13;
addition of isoprene as a second organic component, NOx concentration. The variation of [OH] and the addition of CO served to derive mechanistic aspects of the HOM formation, while the&#13;
isoprene and NOx addition addressed effects of HOM on SOA formation. A detailed analysis of mass spectrometric data was performed at high resolution level and pathways leading to&#13;
compound families and marker compounds were elaborated.&#13;
&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The HOM concentration increased as the turnover of α-pinene increased. Herein, turnover is defined as the product of rate coefficient, [OH] and [α-pinene]. However, [HOM] and&#13;
turnover were not related in an linear manner. This is due to the importance of the secondary oxidation of oxidised products such as pinonaldehyde in HOM formation. The similarity of&#13;
the HOM mass spectra in α-pinene OH oxidation and pinonaldehyde OH oxidation supports these findings.&#13;
&#13;
&lt;p&gt;A high ratio of HO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;/RO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; was achieved by introducing CO in the system. This resulted in a preference of peroxy radicals to react with HO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; and form hydroperoxides. In addition,&#13;
we observed a substantial decrease of the concentration of HOM peroxy radicals and products which require the involvement of alkoxy radicals during their formation. Due to the lower&#13;
[RO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;], less alkoxy radicals were formed by the reaction of two RO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; and less accretion products. &#13;
&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The effect of small peroxy radicals on the a-pinene photooxidation was investigated by introducing isoprene to the reaction system. Isoprene addition led to SOA suppression via two factors. &#13;
Firstly, isoprene effectively scavenged OH because of the twofold higher reactivity of isoprene towards OH radicals compared to a-pinene. &#13;
Secondly, small peroxy radicals originating from isoprene scavenged larger HOM peroxy radicals from a-pinene leading to less volatile products.&#13;
&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Adding NOx to the reaction system changed a reaction pattern of the  α-pinene OH oxidation.&#13;
HOM organic nitrates accounted for up to 50 % of the HOM monomer signals. In addition, an increased importance of fragmentation was observed in the presence of NOx, indicated&#13;
by an increasing concentration of HOM with less than ten C-atoms. These two findings did not affect the SOA mass formation. However, a strong suppression ofHOMaccretion products&#13;
resulted in a SOA mass suppression. In addition, the coupling of intramolecular H-shifts in peroxy and alkoxy radicals, the alkoxy-peroxy pathway, explained the high concentration of&#13;
peroxy radicals even at the very high NOx concentration of up to 72 ppb.</dc:description>
          <dc:rights>Alle Rechte vorbehalten</dc:rights>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 540 Chemie » 540 Chemie und zugeordnete Wissenschaften</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Chemie » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>