<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>11511</id><datestamp>2021-03-25</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:51</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">System Theoretical Properties of linear port-Hamiltonian Systems on Infinite-dimensional Spaces</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Kaiser, Julia Theresa</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2021-03-25</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/mathematik/diss2021/kaiser</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=11511</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20210325-145302-3</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.25926/wp3p-y863</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-10822/dc2101.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">We consider a class of hyperbolic partial differential equations. This includes models of beams and waves as well as the transport equation and networks of nonhomogeneous transmission lines. We study infinite-dimensional linear port-Hamiltonian systems on a one-dimensional spatial domain with full boundary control and without internal damping and show that well-posed port-Hamiltonian systems are exactly controllable. &#13;
Furthermore, we study the Riesz basis property of port-Hamiltonian systems. It is shown that the system operator is a discrete Riesz spectral operator if and only if it generates a strongly continuous group. Moreover, in this situation the spectrum consists of eigenvalues only, located in a strip parallel to the imaginary axis and they can decomposed into finitely many sets having each a uniform gap. &#13;
In the last chapter equivalent conditions for contraction semigroup generation are derived for both infinite networks even of port-Hamiltonian systems of higher order and infinite-dimensional linear port-Hamiltonian systems of order one on the semi-axis.</dc:description>
          <dc:rights>Alle Rechte vorbehalten</dc:rights>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 510 Mathematik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Mathematik und Informatik » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>