<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>1371</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:54:540</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">Investigation of the Tropospheric Oxidation Capacity and Ozone Photochemical Formation in the City of Santiago de Chile -Field Measurements and Modelling Study-</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Elshorbany, Yasin</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2018-01-22</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/chemie/diss2009/elshorbany</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=1371</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20100064</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-1468/dc0915.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">he oxidation capacity and ozone photochemical formation of the highly polluted urban area&#13;
of Santiago de Chile has been evaluated during two field measurements campaigns during&#13;
summer and winter from March 8 – 20 and from May 25 – June 07, 2005, respectively. The&#13;
OH radical budget was evaluated in both campaigns employing a simple quasi-photo&#13;
stationary-state model (PSS) constrained with simultaneous measurements of HONO, HCHO,&#13;
O&lt;sub&gt;&lt;small&gt;3&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;, PAN, NO, NO&lt;sub&gt;&lt;small&gt;2&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;, &lt;i&gt;j&lt;/i&gt;(O&lt;sup&gt;&lt;small&gt;1&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;D), &lt;i&gt;j&lt;/i&gt;(NO&lt;sub&gt;&lt;small&gt;2&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;), 13 alkenes and meteorological parameters. In addition, a&#13;
zero dimensional photochemical box model based on the Master Chemical Mechanism&#13;
(MCMv3.1) has been used for the analysis of the radical budgets and concentrations of OH,&#13;
HO&lt;sub&gt;&lt;small&gt;2&lt;/small&gt; &lt;/sub&gt;and RO&lt;sub&gt;&lt;small&gt;2&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;. Besides the above parameters, the MCM model has been constrained by the&#13;
measured CO and other volatile organic compounds (VOCs) including alkanes and aromatics.&#13;
&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Total production and destruction rates of OH and HO&lt;sub&gt;&lt;small&gt;2&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; in winter were about two times&#13;
lower than that during summer. Simulated OH levels by both PSS and MCM models were&#13;
similar during the daytime for both, summer and winter indicating that the primary OH&#13;
sources and sinks included in the simple PSS model are predominant. On a 24 h basis, HONO&#13;
photolysis was shown to be the most important primary OH radical source comprising 52 %&#13;
and 81 % of the OH initiation rate during summer and winter, respectively followed by alkene&#13;
ozonolysis (29 % and 12.5 %), photolysis of HCHO (15 % and 6.1 %), and photolysis of O3&#13;
(4 % and &lt;1 %), respectively. &lt;p&gt;During both summer and winter, there was a balance between the secondary&#13;
production (HO&lt;sub&gt;&lt;small&gt;2&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; + NO) and destruction (OH + VOC) of OH radicals indicating that initiation&#13;
sources of RO&lt;sub&gt;&lt;small&gt;2&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; and HO&lt;sub&gt;&lt;small&gt;2&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; are no net OH initiation sources. This result was found to be fulfilled&#13;
also for other studies investigated. Seasonal impacts on the radical budgets are also discussed.&#13;
&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The photochemical formation of ozone during the summer campaign carried out from&#13;
March 8 – 20, 2005 has been investigated using an urban photochemical box model based on&#13;
the Master Chemical Mechanism (MCMv3.1). The model has been constrained with the same&#13;
set of the measured parameters used to simulate the radical budgets (see above) except O&lt;sub&gt;&lt;small&gt;3&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;,&#13;
NO&lt;sub&gt;&lt;small&gt;2&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; and PAN. The O&lt;sub&gt;&lt;small&gt;3&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;-NO&lt;sub&gt;&lt;small&gt;x&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;-VOC sensitivities have been determined by simulating ozone&#13;
formation at different VOC and NO&lt;sub&gt;&lt;small&gt;x&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; concentrations.&#13;
&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Ozone sensitivity analyses showed that photochemical ozone formation is VOC-limited&#13;
under average summertime conditions in Santiago. The results of the model&#13;
simulations have been compared with a set of potential empirical indicator relationships&#13;
including H&lt;sub&gt;&lt;small&gt;2&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;&lt;small&gt;2&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;/HNO&lt;sub&gt;&lt;small&gt;3&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;, HCHO/NO&lt;sub&gt;&lt;small&gt;y&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; and O&lt;sub&gt;&lt;small&gt;3&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;/NO&lt;sub&gt;&lt;small&gt;z&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;. The ozone forming potential of each&#13;
measured VOC has been determined using the MCM box model. The impacts of the above&#13;
study on possible summertime ozone control strategies in Santiago are discussed.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 540 Chemie » 540 Chemie und zugeordnete Wissenschaften</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Chemie » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>