<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>15090</id><datestamp>2021-08-12</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:53</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">Study of the Cosmic Ray Composition Sensitivity of AugerPrime - Probing the Prospects of the Upgrade to the Pierre Auger Observatory with a Deep Learning Approach</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Mayotte, Sonja</dc:creator>
          <dc:contributor>Kampert, Karl-Heinz</dc:contributor>
          <dc:date>2021-08-12</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/physik/diss2021/mayotte</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=15090</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20210812-123827-3</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.25926/99h7-fc44</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-14107/dc2110.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;p&gt;The composition of cosmic ray primaries at the highest energies is one of the biggest open&#13;
questions in astroparticle physics, and is directly related to understanding the sources of&#13;
ultra-high energy cosmic rays. At the Pierre Auger Observatory, cosmic rays are studied&#13;
via the extensive air showers they produce in the Earth’s atmosphere. Improving the&#13;
understanding of primary composition at the highest energies is the biggest motivation&#13;
behind the upgrade of the Observatory, AugerPrime. The Surface Detector of the Obser-&#13;
vatory is, as part this upgrade, in the process of receiving new electronics and additional&#13;
detectors. Most important is the scintillator detector, which will be placed on top of the&#13;
existing water Cherenkov detectors. It will allow for a complementary measurement of air&#13;
showers due to the differing responses of the scintillators and water Cherenkov detectors&#13;
to the different shower components. This in turn will enhance the resolution the Surface&#13;
Detector has for measuring the primary composition, perhaps even to an event-by-event&#13;
level.&#13;
In this thesis, development of the new hardware while being tested in the Engineer-&#13;
ing Array over the last few years, is analyzed for the first time. The performance of&#13;
these detector prototypes, especially in regards to the timing resolution, is studied. Using&#13;
information gained from these studies, a machine learning approach based on detector&#13;
simulations which include the AugerPrime upgrade is undertaken, with the goal of re-&#13;
constructing the depth of shower maximum, as it is an indicator of the primary mass.&#13;
Specifically, a convolutional neural network is developed to extract composition inform-&#13;
ation from the difference in the signal pulses of the two different detector types. The&#13;
improvement in composition resolution achieved by adding the trace information from the&#13;
new detector is gauged by training the same network both with and without the scintilla-&#13;
tor detector traces and comparing the results. From this, it is shown that improvements&#13;
to the overall mass resolution and event-by-event reconstruction accuracy can be expected&#13;
after the completion of the AugerPrime upgrade.</dc:description>
          <dc:rights>Alle Rechte vorbehalten</dc:rights>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 530 Physik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Physik » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>