<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>15971</id><datestamp>2022-03-24</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:53:530</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">Cirrus clouds in the extratropical tropopause and lowermost stratosphere region</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Bartolomé García, Irene</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2022-03-24</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/physik/diss2021/bartolomegarcia</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=15971</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20220324-105232-3</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.25926/xdet-zp39</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-14988/dc2139.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;p&gt;&#13;
Cirrus clouds play a fundamental role in the radiative balance of the Earth and have an important impact on the climate. &#13;
Their net effect depends on their physical characteristics, i.e., altitude, vertical extent, optical thickness and particle size. Quantifying the properties&#13;
of ice crystals from the observations is a very challenging task. Consequently, models&#13;
used for climate projections lack observational constrains when predicting the processes&#13;
related to the evolution of cirrus and their properties. The aim of this thesis was to gain a&#13;
deeper understanding of cirrus macro-physical properties (cloud top and bottom height, vertical extent, position with respect to the tropopause) and of the micro-physical properties (ice water content (IWC), particle size). For this purpose, data measured by GLORIA (Gimballed Limb Observer for Radiance Imaging of the Atmosphere) during the WISE (Wave-driven ISentropic Exchange) campaign were analyzed. GLORIA is an airborne&#13;
limb remote sensor that measures radiance in the thermal infrared region (700 cm&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; to&#13;
1400 cm&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;). Two identification methods were used to detect clouds in the measurements.&#13;
One method is based on the cloud index (CI) and the other method, on the use of the&#13;
extinction coefficient in the spectral range 832 cm&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; to 834 cm&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;. Between 13 – 27 % of&#13;
the total number of observations presented a cloud top located above the tropopause &#13;
(TP). However, no cirrus layers were found unambiguously above the TP (i.e., both cloud&#13;
top and cloud bottom above the TP). To estimate the micro-physical properties a combi-&#13;
nation of two approaches was used. The IWC was then integrated to obtain the ice water&#13;
path (IWP). The IWP was compared to the ERA5-based dataset, giving satisfactory re-&#13;
sults (qualitatively) and highlighting that the ERA5 reanalysis does not reproduce most&#13;
of the very thin clouds close to the tropopause. Quantitatively, the retrieved IWP was&#13;
smaller than the ERA5-based IWP, pointing to the need of reducing uncertainties to ob-&#13;
tain a more accurate product. Additionally, observed cloudy regions close to the TP were&#13;
selected as case studies to simulate with CLaMS-Ice (Chemical Lagrangian Model of the&#13;
Stratosphere). The model was able to successfully form clouds in the region of interest.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 530 Physik » 530 Physik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Physik » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>