<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>oai:elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de:1416</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:53:530</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="de">Charakterisierung Biogener Sekundärer Organischer Aerosole mit Statistischen Methoden</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Spindler, Christian</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2018-01-22</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/physik/diss2010/spindler</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=1416</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20100727-121025-3</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-1557/dc1009.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;p&gt;Atmospheric aerosols have important in&#13;
uence on the radiation balance of the Earth, on&#13;
visibility and human health. Secondary organic aerosol is formed from gas-to-particle conversion&#13;
of oxidized volatile organic compounds. A dominant fraction of the gases originates&#13;
from plant emissions, making biogenic secondary organic aerosol (BSOA) an especially&#13;
important constituent of the atmosphere. Knowing the chemical composition of BSOA&#13;
particles is crucial for a thorough understanding of aerosol processes in the environment.&#13;
In this work, the chemical composition of BSOA particles was measured with aerosol&#13;
mass spectrometry and analyzed with statistical methods. The experimental part of&#13;
the work comprises process studies of the formation and aging of biogenic aerosols in&#13;
simulation chambers. Using a plant chamber, real tree emissions were used to produce&#13;
particles in a way close to conditions in forest environments. In the outdoor chamber SAPHIR,&#13;
OH-radicals were produced from the photooxidation of ozone under illumination&#13;
with natural sunlight. Here, BSOA was produced from defined mixtures of mono- and&#13;
sesquiterpenes that represent boreal forest emissions. A third kind of experiments was&#13;
performed in the indoor chamber AIDA. Here, particles were produced from ozonolysis of&#13;
single monoterpenes and aged by condensing OH-oxidation products.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
Two aerosol mass spectrometers (AMS) were used to measure the chemical composition&#13;
of the particles. One of the instruments is equipped with a quadrupole mass spectrometer&#13;
providing unit mass resolution. The second instrument contains a time-of-flight mass&#13;
spectrometer and provides mass resolution sufficient to distinguish different fragments&#13;
with the same nominal mass.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
Aerosol mass spectra obtained with these instruments are strongly fragmented due to&#13;
electron impact ionization of the evaporated molecules. In addition, typical BSOA mass&#13;
spectra are very similar to each other. In order to get a more detailed knowledge about the&#13;
mass spectral characteristics of aerosol from different precursor mixtures or of different&#13;
age, statistical methods comprise a major part of the analysis performed in this work.&#13;
First, hierarchical cluster analysis is used to classify similar mass spectra. This method is&#13;
based on the distances between pairs of mass spectra and is helpful to distinguish between&#13;
groups of very similar data sets. Cluster analysis operates on static mass spectra and&#13;
does not incorporate time-dependent processes. As a result it is found that the chemical&#13;
composition of BSOA is almost independent from the detailed composition of the terpene&#13;
precursor mixture.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
Second, elemental analysis of the mass spectra is performed using the high resolving&#13;
power of the time-of-flight AMS. For each mass spectrum, the ratio of oxygen to carbon&#13;
atoms, O/C, can be calculated by knowing the chemical composition of the individual&#13;
fragments and counting the respective elements. This analysis helps interpreting the&#13;
results from the statistical methods. The temporal evolution of O/C can be directly interpreted&#13;
as an aging process. The evolution is further compared to the oxidation conditions&#13;
of the respective experiments. It is found that the temporal O/C evolution in SAPHIR experiments is strongly dependent on the abundance of OH.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
Finally, a matrix factorization method constraining the entries in the solution matrices&#13;
to positive values (PMF) is applied to determine factors in aging experiments. The results&#13;
are linked to fragment distributions in high-resolved mass spectra and to external measurements&#13;
of terpene oxidation products. A main result from PMF is that the chemical&#13;
composition of BSOA particles is a combination of many parallel processes with different&#13;
time constants.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
Additional measurements were performed on heated aerosol to infer the volatility and&#13;
changes in the chemical composition with evaporation of the most volatile compounds.&#13;
The discussion of the results from these measurements forms the final chapter of this work.&lt;/p&gt;</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 530 Physik » 530 Physik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Physik » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>