<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>16031</id><datestamp>2022-04-06</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:54:540</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="de">Entwicklung und Optimierung einer kleintechnischen Anlage zur Behandlung galvanischer Abwässer mittels Aersolbasierter Eliminierung (ABE)</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Lübke, Steffen</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2022-04-06</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/chemie/diss2022/luebke</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=16031</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20220406-131505-9</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.25926/p26k-sn21</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-15044/dc2201.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="de">&lt;p&gt;Per- and polyfluorinated surfactants (PFAAS) are hydrophobic and lipophobic substances, which are resistant against extreme conditions. PFAAS are essential for many industrial processes. Disadvantages are observed persistent, bioaccumulative and toxic properties. Some of these compounds are classified as persistent organic pollutants (POPs).&lt;br&gt;&#13;
In chromium electroplating, PFAAS are used for occupational safety by chromic mist suppression and to improve product quality. Fluorine-free alternatives are not available due to the extreme oxidizing chromic bath conditions. To reduce PFAAS emissions, an efficient wastewater treatment is required. Expensive sorption processes with ion exchange resins are used so far. The aerosol-based elimination (ABE) is a promising, alternative method.&lt;br&lt;&#13;
During the ABE process, small gas bubbles are generated by passing a gas stream through a porous filter plate into the contaminated water. The surface active PFAAS adsorb and enrich on the rising gas-water bubble interface. When bursting on the water surface an PFAAS enriched aerosol is released.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
In this work, the ABE was further studied. Goal was the development and optimization of a laboratory-sized ABE plant for PFAAS contaminated waste water treatment.&#13;
First topic was the optimization of small bubble generation inside the contaminated water. Camera experiments showed best results for fritted glass and sintered metal plates with small pore sizes, which was confirmed by ABE control experiments.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
In an upscaling procedure, an ABE plant for treatment of a larger stock of PFAAS contaminated waters was developed and optimized. Elimination rates &gt; 99 % were achieved. The PFAAS enriched aerosol was separated by a demister and collected in an aerosol fraction. To reduce unwanted PFAAS and chromium emissions, a closed loop system was installed. Further parameters affecting the elimination results, e.g. stock volume, pump circulation rate, matrix effects and water column height were studied to increase ABE performance.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
Analysis of the collected concentrate fraction showed PFAAS enrichment about a factor of 20 – 30. Inorganic matrix concentrations remained unaffected by ABE, but matrix ion strength influenced aerosol formation.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
Since the developed ABE planed showed promising results, treatment procedures for PFAAS recycling were studied. Further PFAAS enrichment in the concentrate fraction could be achieved by a second stage ABE and a foam skimming process.</dc:description>
          <dc:rights>Alle Rechte vorbehalten</dc:rights>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 540 Chemie » 540 Chemie und zugeordnete Wissenschaften</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Chemie » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>