<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>1658</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:54:540</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="de">Neuartige Gemini-Tenside aus O-acylierten Hydroxycarbonsäuren - Synthesen und Tensideigenschaften -</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Ihizane, Rachid</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2018-01-22</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/chemie/diss2010/ihizane</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=1658</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20101105-111858-3</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-1807/dc1016.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">This thesis describes the syntheses and characterization of novel surface active derivatives &#13;
based on renewable recourses like fatty acids and hydroxycarboxylic acids such as tartaric- and malic &#13;
acid. The combination of those compounds leads to &lt;i&gt;O&lt;/i&gt;-acylated - malic- and tartaric acid &#13;
anhydrides as starting materials. The aim of this work is, to provide novel so called &lt;i&gt;Gemini &#13;
surfactants&lt;/i&gt; based on those starting materials and their unambiguous characterization.&#13;
&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The first part of this work describes the syntheses of &lt;i&gt;O&lt;/i&gt;,&lt;i&gt;O&lt;/i&gt;´-diacylated tartaric acid derivatives in &#13;
an attempt for use as Gemini surfactants because of their definite structure. Their properties are &#13;
determined such as critical micellar concentration (cmc), surfactant efficiency (c&lt;sub&gt;20&lt;/sub&gt;), surface &#13;
tension (γ&lt;sub&gt;cmc&lt;/sub&gt;) and foaming ability and stability. Structure-activity-relationships are highlighted in &#13;
detail. Also different substituted &lt;i&gt;O&lt;/i&gt;,&lt;i&gt;O&lt;/i&gt;´-.diacylated tartaric acid derivatives are investigated to &#13;
enhance their surface activity.&#13;
&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;In order to increase the hydrophilic properties of those above described class of compounds the &#13;
second part illustrates the insertion (esterification) of ethyleneglycole units, such as &#13;
triethyleneglycole, into the &lt;i&gt;O&lt;/i&gt;,&lt;i&gt;O&lt;/i&gt;´-diacylated tartaric acid derivatives up to anionic groups like &#13;
sulfates or kationic systems like quaternary amines. Those attempts provide effective Gemini &#13;
surfactants with very low cmc´s, high or low foaming abilities - according to requirements.&#13;
&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;In the third part two anhydride molecules, particularly &lt;i&gt;O&lt;/i&gt;-acylated tartaric and malic acid &#13;
anhydrides, are connected by one spacer units like α,ω-alkyldiamines and triethylene glycol. The &#13;
investigation of the resulting "dimer"-molecules revealed that the desired properties of Gemini &#13;
surfactants have been limited for those compounds.&#13;
&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Several of the resulting Gemini surfactants show interesting properties such as low CMCs and &#13;
different foaming ability and stability. For practical use of the above synthesized Gemini &#13;
surfactants were tested regarding their activities against a series of bacteria, fungi and yeast. &#13;
Some of them showed promising properties.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 540 Chemie » 540 Chemie und zugeordnete Wissenschaften</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Chemie » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>