<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>2314</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:54:540</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="de">Räumlich und zeitlich aufgelöste Photoionisierung als Werkzeug zur Charakterisierung von Atmosphärendruckionenquellen in der Massenspektrometrie</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Lorenz, Matthias</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2018-01-22</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/chemie/diss2010/lorenz</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=2314</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20111014-145040-5</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-2469/dc1031.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;p&gt;Current research efforts in applied mass spectrometry for routine chemical analyses&#13;
mainly focus on the development of novel methods for liquid chromatographic hyphenation.&#13;
This hyphenation is inherently requiring the ionization stage to be held at&#13;
elevated pressure and thus the gas dynamical separation of the ion source from the&#13;
mass analyzer. It then becomes necessary to collect ions and guide them toward the&#13;
first sampling orifice of the differential pressure reduction cascade. Bulky designs and&#13;
spatial offsets in the analyte path through the ion source both contribute to a spacious&#13;
analyte distribution and thus aggravate the challenge of sampling ions. In other words,&#13;
the volume with a significant contribution to the ion acceptance is spatially rather&#13;
confined.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;    This thesis is concerned with the development and description of spatially and&#13;
temporally resolved atmospheric pressure laser ionization (APLI) as a tool supporting&#13;
the analytical application of the young technique as well as the current efforts in further&#13;
ion source development. The photo-ionization method utilizing pulsed laser radiation&#13;
allows to spatially and temporally confining the conversion of the molecular analyte&#13;
to an ionic species. The interpretation of the data describing the spatial distribution of&#13;
sensitivity within ion sources thus provides information on the ion transport in the&#13;
atmospheric pressure section. Further support can be deduced from experimental data&#13;
on ion transport times and their spatial and temporal distributions.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;    Systematic measurements regarding the spatial distribution of ion acceptance have&#13;
been performed using commercially available mass spectrometers from the manufacturers&#13;
Bruker Daltonics and Waters. Both instruments are equipped with ion sources&#13;
utilizing different approaches for pressure reduction and a rather different geometrical&#13;
outline. Experimental data provide information on the sensitivity distribution and&#13;
highlight the strong impact of various ion source parameters on the processes of ion&#13;
production and ion guidance at atmospheric pressure. In addition to pointing to favorable&#13;
conditions for routine analytical application, the results of this work direct further&#13;
ion source development by indicating a strong impact of the gas dynamics prevailing&#13;
in the source enclosure on achievable ion yield and signal-to-noise ratio. Experimental&#13;
data on transport times and the unexpectedly large ion residence time within the ion&#13;
source provide further support for the strong importance of gas dynamics in current&#13;
atmospheric pressure ion source designs.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;    In this work the relevant physical properties contributing to the sensitivity distribution&#13;
are evaluated. The gathered data provide the experimental basis for the validation&#13;
of derived set-ups and novel ion source designs. Further, the gathered data support&#13;
current computational modelling activities. The transport within atmospheric pressure&#13;
ion sources is a function of the prevailing gas dynamics and primarily determined&#13;
by the geometrical properties and the neutral gas flows. However, the ion trajectories&#13;
are shaped under the further influences of the desolvation process and the specific&#13;
forces on charged particles. The deconvolution of this complex interaction and the&#13;
numerical simulation of ion transport pose a challenge for modelling approaches.&#13;
Current research in this field is targeted at gathering a comprehensive picture of the ion&#13;
source operation in such a way as to eventually enable application-oriented planning,&#13;
design and manufacturing of atmospheric pressure ion sources.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 540 Chemie » 540 Chemie und zugeordnete Wissenschaften</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Chemie » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>