<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>2365</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:6:60:600</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">Light Matter Interaction in Nanostructured Materials</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Kremers, Christian</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2018-01-22</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbe/elektrotechnik/diss2011/kremers</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=2365</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20111108-165121-4</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-2643/de1103.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;p&gt;In this thesis two aspects of electromagnetic wave interaction with nano structured material&#13;
are studied.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;     First, two alternative semi-analytical methods to solve the scattering problem on optical&#13;
nanowire antenna are introduced. In order to reduce the general three dimensional&#13;
volume integral equation describing the scattering problem to a simple semi-analytical&#13;
one dimensional integro-differential equation, both methods utilize solutions of the problem&#13;
of plane wave scattering on infinite cylinder. A regularization and discretization&#13;
scheme is proposed in order to transform the integro-differential equations into solely&#13;
integral equation. This transformation enables to solve the original problem without the&#13;
necessity to impose additional boundary conditions at the nanowire edges. Numerical&#13;
evaluation of the proposed methods and their comparison with different numerically rigorous&#13;
methods is presented for scattering cross-section calculations. Gold nanowires are&#13;
analyzed at optical and near-infrared spectral range. The introduced one-dimensional&#13;
semi-analytical methods demonstrate good agreement and superior numerical performance&#13;
in comparison with rigorous numerical methods.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;     Second, the radiation of a uniformly moving charge (Cherenkov radiation) inside a&#13;
general three dimensional (3D) and two dimensional (2D) periodic dielectric medium is&#13;
studied. In particular analytical expressions for the emission spectrum and for the field&#13;
distribution in the far-field zone are derived. The obtained formula for the Cherenkov&#13;
power emitted per unit length (emission spectrum) of the charge trajectory involves&#13;
the calculations of Bloch modes and corresponding group velocities at limited points&#13;
of the reciprocal space only. The analysis reveals (i) that the Cherenkov effect exists&#13;
for every charge velocity (ii) that the radiation can be suppressed if the coupling of the&#13;
current density produced by a moving charge with a Bloch mode is poor and (iii) that an&#13;
enhancement of radiated energy is possible if only the component of the group velocity&#13;
orthogonal to the trajectory of the charge is small. Additional inside in the Cherenkov&#13;
radiation process is gained from the analytical expression for the field distribution in the&#13;
far-field zone. It is shown that the far-fieeld radiation can be calculated in a 3D photonic&#13;
crystal by a surface integral and in a 2D one by a contour integral over just a small&#13;
fraction of the first Brillouin zone. The spatial variation in the far-field intensity is due&#13;
to (i) interference of just a few Bloch eigenmodes and (ii) the topological properties of&#13;
the k-space surface (3D) or contour (2D). The obtained expressions both for the emission&#13;
spectrum and the field distribution are confirmed by comparison with rigorous numerical&#13;
calculations. The agreement in both cases is very good where the analytical expressions&#13;
are faster and much less demanding on computational resources.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>600 Technik, Medizin, angewandte Wissenschaften » 600 Technik » 600 Technik, Technologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Elektrotechnik, Informationstechnik und Medientechnik » Elektrotechnik » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>