<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>2524</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:3:33:330</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">Energy and Material Efficiency Innovations: The Relevance of Innovation Strategies</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Bönte, Werner</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Dienes, Christian</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2018-01-22</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=2524</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20120116-102527-8</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-2675/</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;p&gt;This study explores the relationship between energy and material efficiency innovations (EMEIs) and innovation strategies employed by manufacturing firms&#13;
to develop their process innovations. Firms may mainly develop process innovations in-house, let them mainly develop by other enterprises or institutions, or they&#13;
or they may develop them jointly with external partners. The empirical analysis is based on data of European manufacturing firms obtained from the fourth&#13;
Community Innovation Survey. Our results suggest that EMEIs are related to process innovation strategies. Firms which let mainly develop their process&#13;
innovations by other enterprises or institutions tend to be less likely to introduce EMEIs at all and these firms are also less likely to introduce EMEIs&#13;
with stronger efficiency effects. Moreover, our results do not suggest that firms following the 'cooperation strategy' are more likely to introduce EMEIs&#13;
and to reach a higher EMEI performance than firms following the 'in-house strategy'. Hence, our results do not confirm the results of previous research&#13;
pointing to a positive relationship between environmental innovations and cooperation with external partners.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="de">JEL-Classification: D22, O32, O33, Q55&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Dateigröße: 680 KB</dc:description>
          <dc:source xml:lang="de">Schumpeter Discussion Papers&#13;
SDP12001&#13;
ISSN 1867-5352&#13;
Published : January 2012</dc:source>
          <dc:subject>energy and material efficiency</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>process innovations</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>innovation strategy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>300 Sozialwissenschaften » 330 Wirtschaft » 330 Wirtschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Wirtschaftswissenschaft/Schumpeter School of Business and Economics » Schumpeter Discussion Papers (SDP)</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Texte » Book</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>