<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>2776</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:6:60:600</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">What Makes Nurses Intend To Leave Their Profession?</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">International Comparison</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Li, Jian</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2018-01-22</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbd/sicherheitstechnik/diss2012/li</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=2776</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20120416-112230-6</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-2899/dd1202.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;p&gt;Background&#13;
&lt;br&gt;The nurse shortage is an increasing problem worldwide, which has significant impact&#13;
on quality of care and patient safety. It has been reported that most industrialized&#13;
countries in America and Europe are or will be facing nursing shortages. However, the&#13;
nurse shortage happens not only in developed countries, but also in developing&#13;
countries, such as in China. In addition, the international East-West migration of&#13;
nurses makes the situation worse in the less developed and developing countries. On&#13;
the other hand, the premature departure increases the loss of nursing staff. What&#13;
makes the nurses want to leave their profession?&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Objectives&#13;
&lt;br&gt;This study was to examine the impact of two established models of psychosocial&#13;
stress at work (i.e. Job Strain model and Effort-Reward Imbalance model), together&#13;
with job alternatives in labor market (employment opportunity) and individual&#13;
resources (including age and health), on the newly developed intention to leave the&#13;
nursing profession, using a prospective design of an international comparative study,&#13;
the Nurses’ Early Exit (NEXT) Study.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Methods&#13;
&lt;br&gt;7990 registered female nurses working in hospitals from eight countries (Germany,&#13;
Italy. France, the Netherlands, Belgium, Poland, Slovakia, and China) who did not&#13;
have intention to leave the nursing profession (ITL) at baseline were followed up one&#13;
year, the logistic regression at both individual level and country level (multilevel&#13;
modeling) was applied for data analyses.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Results&#13;
&lt;br&gt;Generally, in the Netherlands and Belgium (the social-democratic European regime),&#13;
nurses had lowest work stress, highest employment opportunity, best health condition,&#13;
and lowest ITL; in Poland and Slovakia (the post-communist European regime),&#13;
nurses reported highest work stress, lowest employment opportunity, worst health&#13;
condition, and relative low ITL; while nurses from Germany, France, and Italy (the&#13;
conservative-corporatist European regime) and China had relative high work stress,&#13;
relative high employment opportunity, relative good health condition, and highest ITL.&#13;
After controlling the differences between countries, it was found that young age,&#13;
being single, poor health, effort-reward imbalance, and employment opportunity all&#13;
significantly predicted an elevated risk of ITL. In country-specific analyses, the&#13;
obvious divergence was observed. In the post-communist European regime, nurses&#13;
had to stay at their current profession due to lack of employment opportunity in the&#13;
market (so-called ‘locked-in’ situation); nurses from the social-democratic European&#13;
regime, in contrast, reported good quality of psychosocial working conditions with&#13;
easily available employment opportunity, thus weakening a link between stressful&#13;
work and ITL; while in the conservative-corporatist European regime and China, both&#13;
work stress and poor health contributed to nurses’ ITL. Notably, effort-reward&#13;
imbalance played an important role in explaining the premature departure in nurses.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Conclusions&#13;
&lt;br&gt;Findings suggest that improving the psychosocial work environment and health status&#13;
may be helpful in retaining nurses, and consequently towards tackling nursing&#13;
shortage internationally.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>Risk factors</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Work stress</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Employment opportunity</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Self-rated health</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Intention to leave</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Nursing shortage</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>International comparison</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Longitudinal study</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>600 Technik, Medizin, angewandte Wissenschaften » 600 Technik » 600 Technik, Technologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Maschinenbau und Sicherheitstechnik » Sicherheitstechnik » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>