<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>oai:elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de:873</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:53:530</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">Finite-Size Effects in Lattice QCD with Dynamical Wilson Fermions</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Orth, Boris</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2004-10-13</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/physik/diss2004/orth</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=873</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20040501</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-979/dc0411.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;p&gt;&#13;
Due to limited computing resources choosing the parameters for a full&#13;
Lattice QCD simulation always amounts to a compromise between the&#13;
competing objectives of a lattice spacing as small, quarks as light,&#13;
and a volume as large as possible. Aiming at pushing unquenched&#13;
simulations with the Wilson action towards the computationally&#13;
expensive regime of small quark masses, the GRAL project addresses the&#13;
question whether computing time can be saved by sticking to lattices&#13;
with rather modest numbers of grid sites and extrapolating the&#13;
finite-volume results to the infinite volume (prior to the usual&#13;
chiral and continuum extrapolations). In this context we investigate&#13;
in this work finite-size effects in simulated light hadron&#13;
masses. Understanding their systematic volume dependence may not only&#13;
help saving computer time in light quark simulations with the Wilson&#13;
action, but also guide future simulations with dynamical chiral&#13;
fermions which for a foreseeable time will be restricted to rather&#13;
small lattices.&#13;
&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&#13;
&#13;
We analyze data from Hybrid Monte Carlo simulations with the standard&#13;
two-flavor Wilson action at two different values of the coupling&#13;
parameter, β = 5.6 (lattice spacing a ≈ 0.08fm) and&#13;
β = 5.32144 (a ≈ 0.13fm). The larger β corresponds to the&#13;
coupling used previously by SESAM/TχL. The considered hopping&#13;
parameters κ = 0.1575, 0.158 (at the larger β) and&#13;
κ = 0.1665 (at the smaller β) correspond to quark masses of&#13;
85, 50 and 36% of the strange quark mass. At each quark mass we study&#13;
at least three different lattice extents in the range from L=10 to&#13;
L = 24 (0.85-2.04fm). Estimates of autocorrelation times in the&#13;
stochastic updating process and of the computational cost of every run&#13;
are given. For each simulated sea quark mass we calculate quark&#13;
propagators and hadronic correlation functions in order to extract the&#13;
pion, rho and nucleon masses as well as the pion decay constant and&#13;
the quark mass from the PCAC relation. We examine to what extent the&#13;
volume dependence of the masses can be parameterized by simple&#13;
functions based on M. Lüscher's analytic formula and previous&#13;
numerical findings by other groups. The applicability of results for&#13;
the pion and the nucleon from Chiral Effective Theory in the parameter&#13;
regime covered by our simulations is discussed. Cut-off effects in the&#13;
PCAC quark mass are found to be under control.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 530 Physik » 530 Physik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Physik » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>