<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>oai:elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de:5930</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:51:510</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">Ergodicity properties of affine term structure models and applications</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Trabelsi, Chiraz</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2018-01-22</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/mathematik/diss2016/trabelsi</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=5930</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20160624-084201-9</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-5691/dc1611.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;p&gt;The aim of this thesis is to study the ergodicity properties of affine term structure models as well as the practical&#13;
applications. &#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#13;
First, we consider the affine term structure model called the Cox-Ingersoll-Ross model (abbreviated  CIR). This model was introduced in 1985 by John C. Cox, Jonathan E. Ingersoll &#13;
and Stephen A. Ross  as an alternative model to overcome the disadvantage of Vasicek model, in which the interest rate &#13;
can become negative.&#13;
We show the positive Harris recurrence of the CIR process, from which we get an ergodicity results for a transformation&#13;
of the CIR process. This is applied in the calibration of the parameters of a credit migration model.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#13;
Later we focus on an extension of the CIR model that is obtained by adding jumps, namely the basic affine jump-diffusion (BAJD).&#13;
This model has been introduced by Duffie and G\^{a}rleanu as an extension of the CIR model with jumps. &#13;
We derive a closed formula for the transition densities of the BAJD. Note that this fact has already been discovered in&#13;
a special case by Filipovi´c               \cite{MR1850789}.&#13;
Further, we prove the positive Harris recurrence and the exponential ergodicity of the BAJD, and calibrate the transformation of it.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#13;
Another extension of the classical CIR model including jumps is the jump-diffusion CIR process (shorted as JCIR).&#13;
This is introduced with the help of a pure-jump Lèvy process. We find a lower bound on the transition&#13;
densities and we show the existence of a Foster-Lyapunov function from which we derive the exponential ergodicity.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#13;
Finally, we investigate some properties of non affine term structure models.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 510 Mathematik » 510 Mathematik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Mathematik und Informatik</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>