<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>3034</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:3:33:330</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="de">Bildung als Mittel sozialen Aufstiegs? Zum Zusammenhang von Bevölkerungsentwicklung und Bildungsbeteiligung von Migranten</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Schwarz, Alexandra</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Weishaupt, Horst</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2018-01-22</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=3034</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20120924-142800-9</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-3146/</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;p&gt;In this paper, we examine current changes in the ethnic and social composition of the preschool and school aged population as well as the consequences these changes may have for educational participation and thus for overall educational attainment in the near future. Based on the micro-census 2008 survey, we identify groups of migrants by region of parents’ origin where children - despite low levels of parents’ education and comparatively few socioeconomic resources - have greater chances of upward educational mobility than non-migrant children. By contrast, children from less educated, non-migrant families show a much lower tendency to be upwardly mobile, and educational choices are more closely tied to the economic and social background. Thus, our analysis provides evidence that educational background and socio-economic resources in the students’ families are of greater importance for the overall development of educational attainment in Germany than characteristics of migration and ethnicity.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="de">JEL Classification: H75, I24, J10, J15&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Dateigröße: 710 KB</dc:description>
          <dc:source xml:lang="de">Schumpeter Discussion Papers&#13;
SDP12009&#13;
ISSN 1867-5352&#13;
Published : September 2012</dc:source>
          <dc:subject>demografische Entwicklung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Migration</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Bildung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Bildungsmobilität</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>soziale Mobilität</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>300 Sozialwissenschaften » 330 Wirtschaft » 330 Wirtschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Wirtschaftswissenschaft/Schumpeter School of Business and Economics » Schumpeter Discussion Papers (SDP)</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Texte » Book</dc:type>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>