<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>314</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:53:530</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="de">Supraleitende YBa&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;Cu&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;7-&amp;#948;&lt;/sub&gt;-Schichten auf metallischen Bändern</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Kreiskott, Sascha</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2002-04-02</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fb08/diss2001/kreiskott</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=314</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20020165</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-408/d080112.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">For the use of high-temperature superconducting&#13;
materials in energy technology flexible wires or tapes are needed. Up to now&#13;
two different routes for their fabrication do exist. Primary there is the&#13;
powder in tube process, which uses polycrystalline BSCCO powder in a silver&#13;
tube. Secondary there are the coated conductor concepts, which use a metallic&#13;
tape as a substrate for the deposition of buffer and superconducting layers. In&#13;
order to achieve high critical current densities biaxially textured layers of&#13;
the superconductor YBCO are necessary. As a consequence either the substrates&#13;
(RABiTS: rolling assisted biaxially textured substrates approach) or the&#13;
deposited buffers (IBAD: ion beam assisted deposition approach) have to be&#13;
textured. In this thesis the RABiTS approach was used to produce short samples&#13;
of superconducting tapes.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;One of the most important aspects of the RABiTS technique is the&#13;
deposition of buffer layers, which serve as a chemical barrier between the&#13;
ferromagnetic Nickel substrate and match the structural properties of the&#13;
substrate tape and the YBCO layer. In order to deposit high quality YBCO films&#13;
on textured Nickel substrates highly (100) textured and crack free buffer&#13;
layers are needed. Only few materials such as CeO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; and Yttria-stabilised&#13;
Zirconia (YSZ) are suited for the use as a buffer layer. In this thesis several&#13;
deposition techniques such as rf sputtering, thermal reactive evaporation and&#13;
electron beam evaporation were developed and tested for the deposition of CeO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;&#13;
and YSZ. The buffer layers were characterised by XRD, SEM and optical&#13;
microscopy. The growth behaviour of CeO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; on Nickel was studied in&#13;
detail to ensure (100) oriented growth on the cube textured Nickel substrate.&#13;
Growth conditions for the reproducible deposition of (100) oriented buffer&#13;
layers could be found.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;YBCO films were deposited by dc-sputtering on the buffer layers and the&#13;
resulting superconducting properties were measured by inductive&#13;
characterisation and transport current measurements. The cracking of the buffer&#13;
layers during the highly oxidising conditions of the YBCO deposition process&#13;
turned out to be the main obstacle to achieving good superconducting&#13;
properties. After optimisation critical current densities up to 0.6 MA/cm&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&#13;
(77 K, 0 T) and critical temperatures of 91 K with transition&#13;
widths of 3 K could be obtained in 400 nm thick YBCO films on&#13;
exclusively evaporated CeO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;/YSZ/CeO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; buffer&#13;
architectures. These layers still showed cracks after the YBCO deposition,&#13;
which seemed to be the cause for the low critical current densities. Buffer&#13;
architectures with evaporated CeO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; followed by sputtering of YSZ and&#13;
CeO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; remained crack free after the YBCO deposition. Critical current&#13;
densities between 1.5 and 2.6 MA/cm&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; (77 K, 0 T) in&#13;
400 nm thick films could be achieved reproducibly. The transition&#13;
temperatures were measured to be between 91 and 92 K with transition&#13;
widths of 1.5 K.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 530 Physik » 530 Physik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Physik » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>