<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>322</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:53:530</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="de">Advanced Algorithms for the Simulation of Gauge Theories with Dynamical Fermionic Degrees of Freedom</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Schroers, Wolfram</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2002-02-12</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fb08/diss2001/schroers</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=322</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20020097</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-416/d080110.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;p align=justify&gt;&#13;
  The topic of this thesis is the numerical simulation of quantum&#13;
  chromodynamics including dynamical fermions. Two major problems of&#13;
  most simulation algorithms that deal with dynamical fermions are (i)&#13;
  their restriction to only two mass-degenerate quarks, and (ii) their&#13;
  limitation to relatively heavy masses. Realistic simulations of&#13;
  quantum chromodynamics, however, require the inclusion of three&#13;
  light dynamical fermion flavors. It is therefore highly important to&#13;
  develop algorithms which are efficient in this situation.&#13;
  &lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&#13;
  &lt;p align=justify&gt;&#13;
  This thesis is focused on the implementation and the application of&#13;
  a novel kind of algorithm which is expected to overcome the&#13;
  limitations of older schemes. This new algorithm is named Multiboson&#13;
  Method. It allows to simulate an arbitrary number of dynamical&#13;
  fermion flavors, which can in principle have different masses. It&#13;
  will be shown that it exhibits better scaling properties for light&#13;
  fermions than other methods. Therefore, it has the potential to&#13;
  become the method of choice.&#13;
  &lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&#13;
  &lt;p align=justify&gt;&#13;
  An explorative investigation of the parameter space of quantum&#13;
  chromodynamics with three flavors finishes this work. The results&#13;
  may serve as a starting point for future realistic simulations.&#13;
  &lt;/p&gt;</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 530 Physik » 530 Physik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Physik » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>