<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>3352</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:53:530</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="de">The Finite State Machine for the ATLAS Pixel Detector and Beam Background Studies with the ATLAS Beam Conditions Monitor</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Lantzsch, Kerstin</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2018-01-22</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/physik/diss2011/lantzsch</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=3352</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20130206-154031-3</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-3470/dc1132.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="de">&lt;p&gt;Der Large Hadron Collider am CERN bei Genf hat Ende 2009 mit den ersten Proton-Proton Kollisionen seinen&#13;
Betrieb aufgenommen. Der ATLAS-Detektor ist einer der Universaldetektoren, und wurde entwickelt und gebaut&#13;
um neue physikalische Phänomene zu studieren und das Wissen und Verständnis der zugrundeliegenden Theorie&#13;
zu verbessern. Der Pixeldetektor ist der innerste Subdetektor von ATLAS und wird mit seinen 80 Millionen&#13;
Auslesekanälen eine wichtige Rolle spielen bei der Identifikation und Vermessung der interessanten physikalischen&#13;
Phänomene. Komplexe Kontrollsysteme sind erforderlich, um ein System wie den Pixeldetektor sicher betreiben&#13;
zu können. Letztendlich wird ein einziger Operator für die Kontrolle und Überwachung des gesamten ATLASDetektors&#13;
zuständig sein.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Diese Arbeit besteht aus drei Teilen. Der erste Teil gibt einen Überblick über das Experiment. Kapitel 1 gibt&#13;
mit einer kurzen Zusammenfassung des Standardmodells der Teilchenphysik eine Motivation zum Bau großer&#13;
Beschleuniger und Detektoren. In Kapitel 2 wird der Beschleuniger beschrieben, und der ATLAS-Detektor mit&#13;
seinen Subsystemen wird vorgestellt. Da der Pixeldetektor und der Beam Conditions Monitor von spezieller&#13;
Bedeutung für diese Arbeit sind, werden sie in größerem Detail in Kapitel 3 und 4 beschrieben.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Der Schwerpunkt dieser Arbeit liegt im zweiten Teil, der das Kontrollsystem des ATLAS Pixeldetektors behandelt.&#13;
In Kapitel 5 werden die Hardware- und Software-Komponenten beschrieben. Kapitel 6 und 7 stellen den&#13;
Hauptteil der zugrundeliegenden Arbeit dar. Der Betrieb der ATLAS Subdetektoren wird hauptsächlich durch die&#13;
Zustandsmaschine (FSM) gewährleistet. Kapitel 6 beginnt mit einer Einführung der zugrundeliegenden Software-&#13;
Komponenten. Die Anforderungen für die Pixel-FSM werden dargelegt, und die Pixel-spezifische Implementierung&#13;
diskutiert. In Kapitel 7 werden Skripte vorgestellt, die ergänzend zur FSM entwickelt wurden, um sicherheitsrelevante&#13;
Aspekte abzusichern, sowie die Automatisierung von Prozeduren zur Interaktion mit externen Systemen&#13;
handhaben.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Der letzte Teil beschäftigt sich mit Untergrundereignissen aufgrund von strahlbezogenen Belangen. Kapitel 8&#13;
beschreibt potentielle Szenarios zu Strahlverlust, sowie Untergrund während des regulären Betriebs. Während der&#13;
frühen Betriebs-Phase mit wenigen Protonen-Paketen und einer Strahlenergie von bis zu 3500 GeV wurden Daten&#13;
vom Inneren Detektor und des Beam Condition Monitors korreliert.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Eine Zusammenfassung und Bewertung dieser Arbeit im Hinblick auf den Betrieb des ATLAS Pixeldetektors wird&#13;
im Abschluß dieser Arbeit gegeben.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;p&gt;The Large Hadron Collider at CERN near Geneva has started operation with the first proton-proton collisions in&#13;
the end of 2009. The ATLAS detector is one of the general purpose experiments designed to take full advantage of&#13;
the possibilities to study new physics phenomena and improve the knowledge and understanding of the currently&#13;
known state of theory. The Pixel Detector is the innermost sub-detector of ATLAS and with its 80 million readout&#13;
channels will play an important role in the identification and measurement of the interesting physics phenomena.&#13;
To operate a complex detector like the Pixel Detector in a safe and coherent way, sophisticated control systems are&#13;
necessary. In the end, the control and supervision of the Pixel Detector has to be handled by a single shift operator&#13;
integrated into the ATLAS control system and in coordination with the data acquisition and the accelerator.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;This thesis is divided into three parts. In the first part an overview of the experiment is given.&#13;
In chapter 1 the motivation for building large accelerators and detectors is given with a short summary of the&#13;
Standard Model of particle physics and the phenomena to be studied at the LHC. In chapter 2 the accelerator is&#13;
described, and the ATLAS detector and its subsystems are introduced. As the Pixel Detector and the Beam Conditions&#13;
Monitor are of special relevance to this thesis, they are described in more detail in chapters 3 and 4.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The focus of this thesis lies in the second part, covering the Control System of the ATLAS Pixel Detector.&#13;
In chapter 5 the hardware and software components are described. Chapter 6 and 7 constitute the main part of the&#13;
performed work. The Finite State Machine (FSM) is the main tool for the operation of the ATLAS sub-detectors.&#13;
Chapter 6 starts with an introduction to the underlying (common) software components and prior work. The&#13;
requirements for the Pixel FSM originating from various directions are stated, and the pixel specific FSM implementation&#13;
is discussed. Complementary to the FSM, background scripts have been developed to address safety&#13;
and automatization aspects. The first part of chapter 7 presents the implemented safety actions to protect the Pixel&#13;
Detector from danger, while the second part deals with automatization of complex interactions with external systems.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Finally, the third part treats beam background related issues.&#13;
Chapter 8 describes background related to potential beam loss accidents and accident scenarios, as well as background&#13;
during regular operation. During the early running with few bunches and beam energies of up to 3500 GeV&#13;
data from the inner detector and the beam conditions monitor has been correlated for different energies and beam&#13;
optics.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Concluding this thesis is a summary and evaluation of this work in the larger context of the operation of the ATLAS&#13;
Pixel Detector. Achieved results are presented and an outlook for possible future developments and work is given.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 530 Physik » 530 Physik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Physik » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>