<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>3382</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:7:79:796</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">Performance Diagnostics Quantitative Methods to Provide Training Consequences</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">Empirical Study to Development and Evaluation Field Team Sports</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Hassan, Ibrahim</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2018-01-22</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbg/sportwissenschaft/diss2013/hassan</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=3382</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20130227-164847-6</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-3500/dg1301.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;p&gt;Football codes sports have been many studies, which investigated the physical&#13;
fitness profiles of these sports, but especially in the case of soccer. However,&#13;
some physical fitness components of these sports are poorly understood.&#13;
Furthermore, there are individuals who have competed at elite level in soccer&#13;
and rugby union. There are a few studies have been compared the physical&#13;
fitness characteristics of elite level players in each of the football codes.&#13;
Therefore, the current study describe a physical fitness profile for soccer and&#13;
rugby players, and determine if there are any differences in theses fitness&#13;
characteristics between both field team sports.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Twenty-eight players participated in this study. Both field team sports play at&#13;
high-level competitions. Fourteen of them are soccer players from a Bundesliga&#13;
Club (age 24.57 ± 4.33 years; height 1.85 ± 0.07 m; weight 83.86 ± 8.5 kg; BMI&#13;
24.50 ± 1.45 kg.m&lt;sup&gt;-2&lt;/sup&gt;), and the other fourteen are international rugby players from&#13;
DRV federation (age 24 ± 3.94 years; height 1.81 ± 0.05 m; weight 91.05 ±&#13;
12.16 kg; BMI 27.77 ± 2.33 kg.m&lt;sup&gt;-2&lt;/sup&gt;). All players completed performance&#13;
diagnostic tests in speed, strength and endurance aerobic capacity in the&#13;
season break phase.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The results showed significant difference in BMI and physical fitness&#13;
characteristics (speed, strength and endurance) between soccer and rugby&#13;
players, although no significant difference observed in anthropometric (age,&#13;
height, and weight), speed (non-linear sprint 8 m, 22 m and 2.Ch), strength&#13;
(1RMbp and 1RMbs) and endurance aerobic capacity (VO&lt;sub&gt;2max&lt;/sub&gt; test). In&#13;
conclusion, the results together with collected results from the literatures&#13;
revealed significant differences between soccer and rugby union sports, and&#13;
indicate that the demands of both field team sports are different. This difference&#13;
should be considered by those designing the conditioning fundamentals of&#13;
training programmes for these sports.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>700 Künste und Unterhaltung » 790 Sport, Spiele, Unterhaltung » 796 Athletische Sportarten u. Spiele, Freiluftsportarten u. -spiele</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Human- und Sozialwissenschaften » Sportwissenschaft » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>