<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>3433</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:54:540</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">Cascade Reactions Initiated by ᴨ - Activation. A Flexible Way to Heterocycles &amp; Studies toward the Total Synthesis of Melohenine B</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Palisse, Adeline</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2018-01-22</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/chemie/diss2013/palisse</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=3433</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20130409-124009-4</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-3552/dc1305.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">Over the last years, a large number of synthetic routes to obtain heterocyclic compounds have applied transition-&#13;
&#13;
metal-catalyzed cascade reactions. Due to their ability to activate π-systems, especially alkynes, strategies using &#13;
&#13;
soft metal cations, such as Au&lt;sup&gt;I&lt;/sup&gt;, Au&lt;sup&gt;III&lt;/sup&gt;, Ag&lt;sup&gt;I&lt;/sup&gt; or Pt&lt;sup&gt;II&lt;/sup&gt; have been found to &#13;
&#13;
be excellent for constructing complex scaffolds. With the intention of extending the scope of cascade reactions &#13;
&#13;
initiated by π-activation, two sequences were developed to produce tri- and tetra-substituted furans.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#13;
On one hand, by exploring the cascade process of heterocyclization/1,2-migration to provide 2,3-dihydrofurans, an &#13;
&#13;
unexpected furan was isolated. Nevertheless, as poly-substituted furans are interesting target structures the &#13;
&#13;
catalyzed route from the cyclo-hexanones was investigated. A new and convenient way to access tri-substituted &#13;
&#13;
furans with an aldehyde-containing side chain was developed. The sequence is catalyzed by PtCl&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; and &#13;
&#13;
probably proceeds via a heterocyclization followed by 1,2-shift ring-contraction and a Grob-type fragmentation. &#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#13;
On the other hand, in the realm of the study on catalyzed propargyl-Claisen rearran-gements launched in the &#13;
&#13;
&lt;i&gt;Kirsch&lt;/i&gt; group, a sequence of propargyl-Claisen rearran-gement/condensation on propargylic vinyl ethers has &#13;
&#13;
generated tri- and tetra-substituted furans. The domino reaction was effectively catalyzed by AgBF&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;.  &#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#13;
In a second part of the dissertation, the studies toward the total synthesis of melohenine B are described. The &#13;
&#13;
investigations have focused on the production of the aminolactone building block.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 540 Chemie » 540 Chemie und zugeordnete Wissenschaften</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Chemie » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>