<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>oai:elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de:3837</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:54:540</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">Development and Application of a new Long Path Absorption Photometer (LOPAP) Instrument for the Sensitive Detection of NO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Villena Tapia, Guillermo Harold</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2018-01-22</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/chemie/diss2012/villenatapia</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=3837</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20140120-101638-4</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-3946/dc1234.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;p&gt;A compact and simple instrument for the sensitive detection of NO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; in the atmosphere has&#13;
been developed. NO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; is sampled in a stripping coil by a selective chemical reaction, converted&#13;
into a highly absorbing dye, which is detected by long path absorption in a liquid core&#13;
waveguide. Several interferences were quantified in the laboratory, which so far can all be&#13;
neglected. The significant interferences against HONO and O&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;  were suppressed by using an&#13;
upstream HONO/O&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; -scrubber. The instrument has a detection limit of 2 pptv, an accuracy of&#13;
10 % and a precision of 0.5 % for 3 min time resolution. Thus, the new NO2-LOPAP&#13;
technique is more sensitive than known commercial NO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; instruments. The new analyzer is&#13;
much simpler to apply than other highly sensitive and selective NO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; methods, e.g. LIF,&#13;
DOAS, pulsed CRDS or REMPI methods. The new instrument allows an absolute calibration&#13;
that can be easily performed with liquid nitrite standards, which is a significant advantage&#13;
over other NO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; measurement techniques, for which NO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; calibration gas mixtures are typically&#13;
necessary. The new instrument has been validated against the chemiluminescence technique&#13;
during an urban field campaign and against the FTIR technique in a smog chamber under&#13;
complex photosmog conditions. The data sets exhibit high correlation and excellent&#13;
agreement.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#13;
The instrument was used at an urban field site and direct NO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; emissions, from engine&#13;
combustion, were determined. A NO2/NO&lt;sub&gt;x&lt;/sub&gt;  ratio of (12 ± 1) % was determined, a ratio much&#13;
higher than 10 years ago. This is explained by high NO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; emissions from modern diesel&#13;
vehicles and an increasing diesel vehicle fraction. The ratio is lower than that determined by&#13;
using a chemiluminescence instrument, which is explained by interferences.&#13;
The new NO2-LOPAP was also used in laboratory studies on the photolysis of nitroaromatic&#13;
species. In contrast to a recent study on this topic, in which a luminol NO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; instrument was&#13;
used, a significant formation of NO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; was observed besides formation of nitrous acid (HONO).&#13;
Both applications demonstrate that the use of selective NO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; instruments is of paramount&#13;
importance for the quantification and interpretation of NO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; sources in the atmosphere.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 540 Chemie » 540 Chemie und zugeordnete Wissenschaften</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Chemie » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>