<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>3748</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:54:540</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="de">SPR-Analytik von Tetracyclinen in Matrices tierischer Herkunft</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Krause, Simone Janine</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2018-01-22</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/chemie/diss2013/krause</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=3748</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20131023-092150-6</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-3850/dc1311.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="de">&lt;p&gt;Tetracyclines are the most commonly used class of antibiotics in veterinary medicine due to their broad spectrum activity. The use of four &#13;
&#13;
tetracyclines (chlortetracycline, tetracycline, oxytetracycline and doxycycline) is allowed in the European Union for all food-producing species. &#13;
&#13;
Maximum residue limits (MRL) in different tissues are mandatorily defined to maintain consumer health protection. A check for compliance &#13;
&#13;
with these limits requires precise quantification methods. However, to reduce the number of analyzed samples, distinguishing between positive &#13;
&#13;
and negative samples also needs quick and easy to use, but nevertheless reliable screening assays.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#13;
Möller et al. described a tetracycline-specific assay using a surface plasmon resonance (SPR) biosensor based on a bacterial resistance &#13;
&#13;
mechanism against tetracycline in gram negative bacteria. The resistance mechanism relies on the expression of an efflux protein. As long as &#13;
&#13;
no tetracycline is present, the repressor protein TetR binds to a short DNA sequence called &lt;i&gt;tet&lt;/i&gt;O and suppresses the biosynthesis of &#13;
&#13;
the efflux-protein. When tetracycline enters the bacterial cell, it binds to the repressor protein TetR and initiates a conformational change &#13;
&#13;
causing its release from the DNA with subsequent generation of the efflux-protein. &#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#13;
The focus of this thesis is the application of this assay on complex matrices like kidney. A sample preparation method was developed, which &#13;
&#13;
is both quick and easy to perform. Each of the four tetracyclines could reliably be detected in kidney of pig, cow, calf and lamb at the half &#13;
&#13;
MRL. This assay was successfully applied not only to manually doped samples, but also to samples with incurred residues. The assay &#13;
&#13;
imitates a biological system and therefore requires specific physiological conditions. Thus, the sample preparation method could not employ &#13;
&#13;
organic solvents for extraction of tetracyclines from the matrix.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#13;
Robustness tests included a study on chlortetracycline storage. Storing chlortetracycline solutions at temperatures higher than -20°C led to &#13;
&#13;
degradation and can therefore not be recommended. The assay is sensitive to the running buffer used. With two commercially available &#13;
&#13;
running buffers assay stability was achieved. The assay was successfully applied on samples from the official surveillance system.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 540 Chemie » 540 Chemie und zugeordnete Wissenschaften</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Chemie » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>