<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>377</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:54:540</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="de">Infrarotspektroskopische Untersuchungen an SCF&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt;, SeCF&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt;, D&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt;Se und HDSe</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Jerzembeck, Wolfgang</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>1999-10-21</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fb09/diss1999/jerzembeck</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=377</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-19990251</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-471/d099911.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="de">&lt;P&gt;Die vorgelegte Dissertation behandelt Synthese, hochaufgelöste Gasphasen-FTIR-Spektren und deren Rotationssanalyse von einer Reihe 3 - 6 -atomiger Moleküle.&lt;/P&gt;&#13;
&lt;P&gt;Hochaufgelöste FTIR-Spektren von SCF&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; (Auflösung Δσ&gt;  = 2.5 - 3.3 x 10&lt;sup&gt;-3&lt;/sup&gt; cm&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;) wurden im Bereich der sechs Grundschwingungen aufgenommen und analysiert. Rotationsparameter der offensichtlich  ungestörten Banden &lt;IMG SRC="/images/jerzembeck/Image88.gif" height=28 width=19&gt; = 789.535 cm&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;,  &lt;IMG SRC="/images/jerzembeck/Image89.gif" height=29 width=19&gt; = 526.697 cm&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;,  &lt;IMG SRC="/images/jerzembeck/Image90.gif" height=29 width=19&gt; = 419.546 cm&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; und  &lt;IMG SRC="/images/jerzembeck/Image91.gif" height=29 width=19&gt; = 623.187 cm&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; wurden mit hoher Genauigkeit  (&lt;σ (Fit) ≅ 3.5 x 10&lt;sup&gt;-4&lt;/sup&gt; cm&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;) bestimmt.  Grundzustandsparameter des Hauptisotopomers &lt;sup&gt;32&lt;/sup&gt;S&lt;sup&gt;12&lt;/sup&gt;C&lt;sup&gt;19&lt;/sup&gt;F&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;  wurden aus Grundzustandskombinationsdifferenzen (GSCD) der ν&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;-Bande  gegenüber den aus Rotationsdaten ermittelten maßgeblich verbessert.  Die beiden Banden oberhalb 1000 cm&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;, ν&lt;sub&gt;4, eff&lt;/sub&gt; = 1190.084 cm&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; und  ν&lt;sub&gt;1, eff&lt;/sub&gt; = 1366.712 cm&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;,  stehen mit den Kombinationstönen ν&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; + ν&lt;sub&gt;5&lt;/sub&gt; bzw.  ν&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; + ν&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; und  ν&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; + 2ν&lt;sub&gt;5&lt;/sub&gt;  in starker anharmonischer Resonanz. Es gelang, effektive und entstörte Schwingungsrotationsparameter  dieser fünf Banden zu ermitteln. Mit den verbesserten Grundzustandsparametern sowie den  Schwingungskorrekturen konnten erstmals die Gleichgewichtskonstanten Ae, Be und Ce von &lt;sup&gt;32&lt;/sup&gt;S&lt;sup&gt;12&lt;/sup&gt;C&lt;sup&gt;19&lt;/sup&gt;F&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;  experimentell bestimmt werden.&lt;/P&gt;&#13;
&lt;P&gt;Eine Synthese für monoisotopes &lt;sup&gt;80&lt;/sup&gt;SeCF&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; wurde entwickelt und hochaufgelöste FTIR-Spektren (Δσ = 2.5 - 3.3 x 10&lt;sup&gt;-3&lt;/sup&gt; cm&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;) der ν&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;-Bande (ν&lt;sub&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt; = 431.053 cm&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;)  und ν&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;-Bande (ν&lt;sub&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt; =  1208.790 cm&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;)  aufgenommen. Die unbekannten Rotationskonstanten konnten erstmals durch GSCD für &lt;sup&gt;80&lt;/sup&gt;SeCF&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; bestimmt werden.  Sie ermöglichten die erfolgreiche Suche reiner Rotationsübergänge im MW-Bereich zwischen 5 und  26.5 GHz für &lt;sup&gt;M&lt;/sup&gt;SeCF&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; (M = 76, 77, 78, 80, 82) und im MMW-Bereich zwischen 152 und  240 GHz für &lt;sup&gt;M&lt;/sup&gt;SeCF&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; (M = 78, 80). Die Grundzustandsparameter einschließlich  der quartischen Zentrifugaldehnungskoeffizienten konnten für alle fünf Se-Isotopomere bestimmt werden.  Die Konstanten der angeregten Zustände v&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; = 1 und v&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; = 1 von &lt;sup&gt;80&lt;/sup&gt;SeCF&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;  wurden mit hoher Signifikanz bestimmt. Die Standardabweichungen der Fits, σ≅ 4.5 x 10&lt;sup&gt;-4&lt;/sup&gt; cm&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;, belegen, daß beide Schwingungszu-stände ungestört sind.  Unter Verwendung von &lt;I&gt;ab initio&lt;/I&gt; Berechnungen und Ergebnissen eines Elektronenbeugungsexperiments konnten  die effektiven (r&lt;sub&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt;), die mittleren (r&lt;sub&gt;z&lt;/sub&gt;) und die Gleichgewichtsstrukturparameter (r&lt;sub&gt;e&lt;/sub&gt;)  von SeCF&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; bestimmt werden.  &lt;/P&gt;&#13;
&lt;P&gt;Hochaufgelöste FTIR-Spektren von natürlichem und &lt;sup&gt;80&lt;/sup&gt;Se monoisotopem HDSe und D&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;Se wurden zwischen 600 und 4000 cm&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; mit einer Auflösung von ca. 3 x 10&lt;sup&gt;-3&lt;/sup&gt; cm&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; registriert. Die Grundzustandsparameter von HD&lt;sup&gt;M&lt;/sup&gt;Se und D&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;M&lt;/sup&gt;Se (M = 76, 77, 78, 80, 82) bis zu oktischen Zentrifugaldehnungskoeffizienten konnten durch GSCD aus den drei Grundschwingungen ν&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;, ν&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;, ν&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; bestimmt werden. Mit &lt;sup&gt;80&lt;/sup&gt;Se-monoisotopem Material ermittelte, genauere Grundzustandsparameter von HD&lt;sup&gt;80&lt;/sup&gt;Se und D&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;80&lt;/sup&gt;Se wurden z. T. auf die weniger häufigen Se-Isotopomere übertragen. Mit Hilfe dieses Grundzustandes wurden die Rotationsparameter des angeregten (v&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; =  1)-Zustandes von HD&lt;sup&gt;M&lt;/sup&gt;Se(ν&lt;sub&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt; = 900.43820 cm&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;) und D&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;M&lt;/sup&gt;Se(ν&lt;sub&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt; =  741.67503 cm&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;) bestimmt, σ (Fit) ≅ 1.5 x 10-4 cm&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;. Nicht bestimmbare Zentrifugaldehnungskoeffizienten der seltenen Se-Isotopomere wurden auf den Werten der beiden Hauptisotopomere festgehalten.&lt;/P&gt;&#13;
&lt;P&gt;Ausgehend von monoisotopem &lt;sup&gt;120&lt;/sup&gt;Sn konnte &lt;sup&gt;120&lt;/sup&gt;SnD&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; in zwei Schritten dargestellt und seine Spektren im Bereich der (Sn-D)-Streckschwingung sowie des ersten und zweiten Obertons aufgenommen werden. Die Analyse dieser Spektren zeigte, daß sich SnD&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; wie SnH&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; durch das Local-Mode-Modell beschreiben läßt. &lt;/P&gt;&#13;
&lt;P&gt;In kleinen Anteilen (3 - 5%) enthaltenes &lt;sup&gt;120&lt;/sup&gt;SnD&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;H wurde im Bereich der ν&lt;sub&gt;5&lt;/sub&gt;-Bande (ν&lt;sub&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt; = 646.897 cm&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;) untersucht. Bei der Analyse dieser Bande kam das Lobodenko-Modell äquivalenter Reduktionen des Hamiltonians zur Anwendung.&lt;/P&gt;&#13;
&lt;P&gt;Von SbD&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; und AsD&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;, aus SbCl&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; und AsCl&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; mit LiAlD&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; gewonnen, wurden die reinen Rotationsspektren im FIR sowie Spektren im Bereich der vier Grundschwingungen mit einer Auflösung von 2.3 - 3.0 x 10&lt;sup&gt;-3&lt;/sup&gt; cm&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; aufgenommen. Die Auswertung der reinen FIR-Spektren von beiden Molekülen ist abgeschlossen. Weitere Rotationsschwingungsanalysen der aufgenommenen Spektren sind weit fortgeschritten.&lt;/P&gt;&#13;
&lt;P&gt;Durch MW- bzw. MMW-Untersuchungen an H&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;SiCN und dessen Isotopomeren (&lt;sup&gt;29&lt;/sup&gt;Si, &lt;sup&gt;30&lt;/sup&gt;Si, &lt;sup&gt;13&lt;/sup&gt;C, &lt;sup&gt;15&lt;/sup&gt;N, d&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;, d&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;, d&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;), die ausgehend von Phenyltrichlorsilan in einer Mehrstufen-synthese dargestellt wurden, konnte mit Hilfe von &lt;I&gt;ab initio&lt;/I&gt; Berechnungen eine genaue Struktur ermittelt werden. Durch Stark-Messungen im MW-Bereich wurde das Dipolmoment von H&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;SiCN bestimmt. Die ermittelten Grundzustandsparameter des Hauptisotopomers H&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;28&lt;/sup&gt;Si&lt;sup&gt;12&lt;/sup&gt;C&lt;sup&gt;14&lt;/sup&gt;N sowie die beobachteten reinen Rotationsübergänge des (v&lt;sub&gt;8&lt;/sub&gt; = 1)-Zustandes unterstützen die bereits vorangeschrittene Analyse dieser Bande. &lt;/P&gt;&#13;
&lt;P&gt;Von trans-HCOOD und trans-DCOOD wurden im Bereich zwischen 400 und 2100 cm&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; hochaufgelöste FTIR-Spektren mit einer Auflösung von 2.5 - 3.0 x 10&lt;sup&gt;-3&lt;/sup&gt; cm&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; aufgenommen. Die in starker Coriolis-Resonanz stehenden Schwingungen ν&lt;sub&gt;7&lt;/sub&gt; und ν&lt;sub&gt;9&lt;/sub&gt; konnten unter Federführung von Prof. Baskakov analysiert werden. &lt;/P&gt;</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;P&gt;This thesis reports on the syntheses, high resolution FTIR spectra and the rovibrational analyses of several molecules containing 3 to 6 atoms.&lt;/P&gt;&#13;
&lt;P&gt;High resolution FTIR spectra of SCF2 in the region of the six fundamentals (resolution Δσ = 2.5 - 3.3 x 10&lt;sup&gt;-3&lt;/sup&gt; cm&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;) have been recorded and analysed. Rovibrational constants of the unperturbed bands &lt;IMG SRC="/images/jerzembeck/Image88.gif" height=28 width=19&gt; = 789.535 cm&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;, &lt;IMG SRC="/images/jerzembeck/Image89.gif" height=29 width=19&gt; = 526.697 cm&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;, &lt;IMG SRC="/images/jerzembeck/Image90.gif" height=29 width=19&gt; = 419.546 cm&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; and &lt;IMG SRC="/images/jerzembeck/Image91.gif" height=29 width=19&gt; = 623.187 cm&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; were determined with high accuracy (σ (fit) ≅ 3.5 x 10-4 cm&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;). Ground state constants of the isotopic species 32S12C19F2 were improved by means of ground state combination differences (GSCD) obtained from the ν&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; band. The two fundamentals above 1000 cm&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;, ν&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;,eff = 1366.712 cm&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; and ν&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;,eff =  1190.084 cm&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;, are involved in strong anharmonic (Fermi) resonances with the combination bands ν&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; +ν&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; and ν&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; +2ν&lt;sub&gt;5&lt;/sub&gt;, ν&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; +ν&lt;sub&gt;5&lt;/sub&gt;, respectively. Effective and deperturbed rovibrational parameters of all five bands were determined with high significance. Equilibrium rotational constants Ae, Be, Ce of 32S12C19F2 were derived from improved ground state parameters and vibrational corrections.&lt;/P&gt;&#13;
&lt;P&gt;Monoisotopic &lt;sup&gt;80&lt;/sup&gt;SeCF&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; has been prepared, and high resolution FTIR spectra (Δσ = 2.5 - 3.3 x 10&lt;sup&gt;-3&lt;/sup&gt; cm&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;) of the ν&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; band (ν&lt;sub&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt; = 431.053 cm&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;) and the ν&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; band (ν&lt;sub&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt; =  1208.790 cm&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;) have been recorded. The formerly unknown rotational parameters were determined by GSCD for &lt;sup&gt;80&lt;/sup&gt;SeCF&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;. These guided a search for pure rotational transitions of &lt;sup&gt;M&lt;/sup&gt;SeCF&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; in the MW region (5 - 26 GHz; M = 76, 77, 78, 80, 82) and MMW region (152 - 240 GHz; M = 78, 80). Ground state constants up to quartic terms of the five isotopic species were determined. Parameters of the v&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; = 1 and v&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; = 1 excited states of &lt;sup&gt;80&lt;/sup&gt;SeCF&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; were also determined. Standard deviations of the fits, σ ≅ 4.5 x 10-4 cm&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;, proved that both states are unperturbed. Using &lt;I&gt;ab initio&lt;/I&gt; calculations and results of an electron diffraction study effective (r&lt;sub&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt;), average (r&lt;sub&gt;z&lt;/sub&gt;) and equilibrium structural parameters were determined. &lt;/P&gt;&#13;
&lt;P&gt;   High resolution spectra of natural and &lt;sup&gt;80&lt;/sup&gt;Se monoisotopic HDSe und D&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;Se have been recorded between 600 and 4000 cm&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; with Δσ ca. 3 x 10&lt;sup&gt;-3&lt;/sup&gt; cm&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;. Ground state constants of HD&lt;sup&gt;M&lt;/sup&gt;Se and D&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;M&lt;/sup&gt;Se (M = 76, 77, 78, 80, 82) up to octic terms were determined by GSCD obtained from the rotational analyses of the fundamentals ν&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;, ν&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;, ν&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;. Ground state constants of HD&lt;sup&gt;80&lt;/sup&gt;Se and D&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;80&lt;/sup&gt;Se obtained from the analyses of the &lt;sup&gt;80&lt;/sup&gt;Se monoisotopic spectra and determined with high accuracy were transferred to the less abundant Se species. Using these ground state constants, excited state parameters for v&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; = 1 of HD&lt;sup&gt;M&lt;/sup&gt;Se (ν&lt;sub&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt; = 900.43820 cm&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;) and D&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;M&lt;/sup&gt;Se (ν&lt;sub&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt; =  741.67503 cm&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;) were determined, σ (fit) ≅ 1.5 x 10&lt;sup&gt;-4&lt;/sup&gt; cm&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;. Some centrifugal distortion terms of the less abundant Se species were constrained to those of the &lt;sup&gt;80&lt;/sup&gt;Se species.&lt;/P&gt;&#13;
&lt;P&gt;Spectra of &lt;sup&gt;120&lt;/sup&gt;SnD&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; prepared in two steps from monoisotopic &lt;sup&gt;120&lt;/sup&gt;Sn have been recorded in the stretching fundamentals as well as the first and second overtone regions. Rovibrational analyses of the spectra indicated local mode behaviour of SnD&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;, as was found in SnH&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;.&lt;/P&gt;&#13;
&lt;P&gt;The sample contained in a small amount (3 - 5%) &lt;sup&gt;120&lt;/sup&gt;SnD&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;H. The high resolution spectrum of the latter was investigated in the region of the ν&lt;sub&gt;5&lt;/sub&gt; band (ν&lt;sub&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt; = 646.897 cm&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;). The analyses were performed using the Lobodenko model of unitary equivalent reductions of the Hamiltonian.&lt;/P&gt;&#13;
&lt;P&gt;The rotation spectrum in the vibrational ground state and spectra in the region of the four fundamentals of SbD&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; and AsD&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; (prepared from SbCl&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; or AsCl&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; and LiAlD&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;) were recorded with Δσ 2.3 - 3.0 x 10&lt;sup&gt;-3&lt;/sup&gt; cm&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;. The analyses of the pure rotational spectra were completed and further analyses are in progress.&lt;/P&gt;&#13;
&lt;P&gt;An accurate structure of H&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;SiCN prepared in four steps from C&lt;sub&gt;6&lt;/sub&gt;H&lt;sub&gt;5&lt;/sub&gt;SiCl&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; was determined from FTMW and MMW data of H&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;SiCN and its isotopic species (&lt;sup&gt;29&lt;/sup&gt;Si, &lt;sup&gt;30&lt;/sup&gt;Si, &lt;sup&gt;13&lt;/sup&gt;C, &lt;sup&gt;15&lt;/sup&gt;N, d&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;, d&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;, d&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;) employing results of &lt;I&gt;ab initio&lt;/I&gt; calculations. The dipole moment of H&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;SiCN was determined, too. Ground state parameters as well as the observed pure rotational transitions in the v&lt;sub&gt;8&lt;/sub&gt; = 1 state were used for the ongoing analysis of this band.&lt;/P&gt;&#13;
&lt;P&gt;High resolution FTIR spectra of trans-HCOOD and trans-DCOOD have been recorded in the region between 400 and 2100 cm&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; (Δσ = 2.5 - 3.0 x 10&lt;sup&gt;-3&lt;/sup&gt; cm&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;). A rovibrational analysis of the Coriolis-coupled ν&lt;sub&gt;7&lt;/sub&gt; and ν&lt;sub&gt;9&lt;/sub&gt; bands was performed by Prof. Baskakov.&lt;/P&gt;</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 540 Chemie » 540 Chemie und zugeordnete Wissenschaften</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Chemie » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>