<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>3785</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:8:80:800</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">Defining Narrative Journalism Through the Concept of Plot</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Vanoost, Marie</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2018-01-22</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=3785</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20131120-175150-0</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-3898/dej13020205.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;p&gt;Narrative journalism, as has been frequently stressed, offers stories closer to fic-tional narratives than to conventional press stories, at least in their writing tech-niques and in the kind of truth they intend to convey. But what has been less&#13;
extensively examined are the implications of this hybridization for the character-istics of such narratives. This article will highlight how these narratives differ from Lits’s notion of récit médiatique and from the “narratives” Revaz, Pahud and Baroni identify in the daily press. Then, using the distinction between the two functions of narratives that Baroni introduced – which he calls fonction intrigante and fonction configurante –, the article will propose a new way of conceiving how narrative journalism is both fundamentally inscribed in the realm of journalism and closely connected to fiction, through the concept of plot. Finally, the article will suggest distinguishing between different approaches – connected with different ethical stances – within narrative journalism, depending on the kind of plot the narrative offers.</dc:description>
          <dc:source xml:lang="de">&lt;b&gt;DIEGESIS.&lt;/b&gt; &#13;
&lt;br&gt;Interdisziplinäres E Journal für Erzählforschung / &#13;
&lt;br&gt;Interdisciplinary E-Journal for Narrative Research &#13;
&lt;br&gt;ISSN 2195-2116&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#13;
&lt;a target=new_window href="https://www.diegesis.uni-wuppertal.de"&gt;https://www.diegesis.uni-wuppertal.de&lt;/a&gt;&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#13;
Heft 02 (2013) Seite 77-97&#13;
&lt;br&gt;2. Jahrgang</dc:source>
          <dc:subject>800 Literatur » 800 Literatur, Rhetorik, Literaturwissenschaft » 800 Literatur und Rhetorik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Geistes- und Kulturwissenschaften » DIEGESIS » Jg. 2 (2013) H. 2</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Texte » PeriodicalPart</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>