<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>3804</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:53:530</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">Investigation of clusters and precipitates in reactor pressure vessel steels by X-ray absorption spectroscopy</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Cammelli, Sebastiano</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2018-01-22</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/physik/diss2009/cammelli</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=3804</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20131211-101625-6</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-3909/dc0925.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;p&gt;The goal of the study is the investigation of the build-up of copper clusters in reactors&#13;
pressure vessel (RPV) steels. The study comprises tests on RPV surveillance samples&#13;
provided by a nuclear power plant, and on RPV reference samples. The reference steels,&#13;
named Japanese Reference Quality (JRQ), were provided by the International Atomic&#13;
Energy Agency (IAEA). Moreover the study was completed with the investigation of&#13;
some unirradiated binary alloys.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
To better understand the mechanism of cluster build-up in a simplified system, tests were&#13;
performed on the binary alloy Fe-Cu containing 1.3 at % Cu. The samples were annealed&#13;
at 775 K for different times. They were analysed using x-ray absorption fine structure&#13;
(XAFS) spectroscopy at the Cu K-edge, x-ray diffraction (XRD) and transmission&#13;
electron microscopy (TEM). The results show that Cu cluster formation occurs even with&#13;
short annealing times. These clusters with a diameter of a few nm have been observed to&#13;
switch easily from bcc Fe-like to fcc Cu-like structure. While a short annealing time of&#13;
2.5 h at 775 K does practically not change the good dilution of Cu in the bcc Fe matrix,&#13;
an annealing treatment for 312 h leads to large fcc Cu precipitates. A linear combination&#13;
analysis suggests that in the sample annealed for 8 h, Cu clusters are formed mostly in the&#13;
same structure as the bcc matrix. A coexistence of bcc and fcc clusters is obtained for 115&#13;
h of annealing. TEM indicates the presence of precipitates with a diameter up to 60 nm&#13;
for an annealing time of 312 h, and XRD provides complementary data about the clusters&#13;
size distributions in differently annealed samples.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
The reactor pressure vessel (RPV) reference steel from IAEA submitted to neutron&#13;
irradiation in a research reactor and subsequently thermally annealed and re-irradiated&#13;
was investigated by XAFS spectroscopy. It could be expected that Cu and Ni atoms form&#13;
nano-clusters. In the unirradiated sample and in the irradiated sample no significant&#13;
clustering is detected. In all irradiated and subsequently annealed samples an increase of&#13;
Cu and Ni atom densities are recorded around the x-ray absorbing atoms. Furthermore,&#13;
the density of Cu and Ni atoms determined in the first and second shell around the&#13;
absorber is found to be affected by irradiation and the annealing treatment. The&#13;
comparison of the XAFS data at the Cu and Ni K-edges shows that these elements are in&#13;
a bcc structure like the Fe host lattice. However, the local irradiation damage reduces the&#13;
number of next neighbour atoms around copper; while the annealing reduces the number&#13;
of vacancies. The number of Cu and Ni atoms around (Cu or Ni) absorbers then&#13;
increases. The IAEA samples are very well characterised due to earlier analysis by atom&#13;
probe tomography (APT) at the Oak-Ridge National Lab (ORNL) and mechanical tests,&#13;
at the Paul Scherrer Institut. The possibility to compare XAFS and APT provided an&#13;
invaluable opportunity to understand the differences and similarities among the two&#13;
techniques. XAFS and APT are both very sensitive to nanostructures and both are&#13;
element selective techniques. XAFS is highly sensible to the average environment of the&#13;
absorber element, within &lt; 0.5 nm, so it delivers information about the short range order.&#13;
The results show a general agreement and the differences were considered within the&#13;
experimental error.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
Finally, surveillance samples from a Swiss nuclear power plant (KKG Kernkraftwerk&#13;
Gösgen) were analysed by XAFS. The number of Cu and Ni atoms determined in the first&#13;
and second shell around the absorbers is affected by irradiation and temperature. The&#13;
comparison of the EXAFS data at the Cu and Ni K-edges shows that these elements are&#13;
in a crystallographic structure similar to bcc Fe. There are indications that the formation&#13;
of Cu and Ni clusters differs significantly; irradiation damage reduces the next neighbour&#13;
number for both elements. Clusters were detected only around copper atoms: the number&#13;
of Cu atoms in the first two shells was found to increase with the irradiation time.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
With EXAFS it could be verified that neutron irradiation in a power reactor leads to small&#13;
changes of the local atomic environment around the investigated Cu and Ni atoms.&#13;
Moreover, most of the local structural changes are obtained for the sample with the&#13;
longest irradiation time. This lets assume that the reduction of the number of next&#13;
neighbours in the bcc structure around Cu and Ni in the steel matrix is steadily increasing&#13;
with the years of irradiation in the reactor. However it can be expected that the elevated&#13;
temperature helps refilling the irradiation induced vacancies by a permanent annealing&#13;
process. The detailed EXAFS analysis has demonstrated that the number of Cu atoms in&#13;
the local vicinity of copper is enriched during irradiation in the power plant, while the&#13;
local atomic environment around nickel seems to be less affected.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
Cu and Ni atoms behave similarly in the IAEA samples, but they show differences in the&#13;
power reactor samples. The reasons for the different behaviour reside in the different&#13;
irradiation processes: IAEA samples were strongly irradiated and then annealed at high&#13;
temperature, while the KKG samples were irradiated at a higher temperature than the&#13;
IAEA samples without any post irradiation annealing. Obviously neutron irradiation&#13;
forms many vacancies and vacancies clusters, which are easily filled by solute atoms. In&#13;
case of irradiation in the power reactor, there are fewer vacancies and the temperatures&#13;
involved are lower than the annealing temperature of the IAEA reference samples; the&#13;
atom cluster formation of Cu is slowed down and Ni is even less affected.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 530 Physik » 530 Physik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Physik » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>