<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>3833</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:54:540</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">Aerosol processes in the Planetary Boundary Layer: High resolution Aerosol Mass Spectrometry on a Zeppelin NT Airship</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Rubach, Florian</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2018-01-22</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/chemie/diss2013/rubach</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=3833</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20140116-100341-2</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-3942/dc1321.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;P&gt;Atmospheric aerosol plays an ambivalent role for mankind. On the one hand,&#13;
aerosol is known to have adverse health effects and even increase mortality. On&#13;
the other hand, a raised aerosol concentration in the atmosphere is the only&#13;
anthropogenic contribution to the Earth’s climate known to have a net cooling&#13;
effect by scattering light and acting as cloud condensation nuclei (CCN). Among&#13;
other things, the magnitude of these effects depend on the chemical composition&#13;
of the aerosol.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
&lt;br&gt;In this work, an Aerosol Mass Spectrometer (AMS) was adapted for airborne&#13;
aerosol chemical composition measurements on a Zeppelin NT airship. The Zeppelin&#13;
platform allows for measurements with high spatial resolution throughout&#13;
the entire planetary boundary layer (PBL). The new instrument was successfully&#13;
operated aboard the Zeppelin NT on nine out of ten flight days of a seven week&#13;
campaign in two countries in the context of the European project PEGASOS. The&#13;
mass concentrations of the measured aerosol chemical species are presented for&#13;
these days.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
&lt;br&gt;The campaign observations revealed a higher relative concentration of nitrate&#13;
aerosol in the Netherlands compared to the Po Valley in northern Italy. For sulfate&#13;
aerosol, the situation was opposite. Furthermore, the organic aerosol was more&#13;
aged in the Po Valley than in the Netherlands.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
&lt;br&gt;The influence of the aerosol chemical composition on the cloud droplet activation&#13;
was studied by computation of the critical activation diameter and comparing to&#13;
aerosol number size distribution measurements. In some situations, the chemical&#13;
composition was the driving force behind changes in CCN concentration, in other&#13;
situations its effect was overshadowed by changes in the size distribution.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
&lt;br&gt;Differences between the individual layers of the PBL were identified in the mass&#13;
concentrations of the aerosol chemical species and the organic aerosol age.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
&lt;br&gt;A backward trajectory analysis was used in conjunction with the obtained data to&#13;
estimate the aerosol production rate of the Po Valley to 0.60 (μg/m&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;)/h for organic&#13;
aerosol, 0.88 (μg/m&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;)/h for nitrate aerosol, and 0.15 (μg/m&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;)/h for sulfate aerosol.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
&lt;br&gt;The aerosol ion balance was used to gain insights into organic aerosol functionalization&#13;
patterns.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 540 Chemie » 540 Chemie und zugeordnete Wissenschaften</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Chemie » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>