<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>407</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:54:540</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">Advances in the stereoselective synthesis of antifungal agents and aromatase inhibitors</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Summa, Vincenzo</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2000-07-21</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fb09/diss1999/summa</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=407</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20000188</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-501/d099922.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;P&gt;Numerous drugs are chiral, generally only one enantiomer is therapeutically active while the other antipode is completely inactive or shows often undesired and/or toxic side effects. For this reason, all new chiral drugs are now formulated in enantiopure form. Non-steroidal anticancer and antifungal drugs contain the same chemical structure e.g. Bifonazole &lt;B&gt;6a&lt;/B&gt; and non-steroidal aromatase inhibitors such as the Menarini anticancer drug &lt;B&gt;18.&lt;/B&gt; They are characterized by the presence of single chiral centre in benzhydrilic position. The present work was aimed at new procedures for the synthesis of both Bifonazole &lt;B&gt;6a &lt;/B&gt;and the Menarini aromatase inhibitors &lt;B&gt;18 &lt;/B&gt;in enantiomeric pure form.&lt;/P&gt;&#13;
&lt;P&gt;In order to prepare enantiopure synthons and final products several synthetic methods were developed.&lt;/P&gt;&#13;
&lt;P&gt;A chiral lithium aluminiumhydride complex with (&lt;I&gt;R&lt;/I&gt;)-(-)-2-isoindolinyl-butan-1-ol &lt;B&gt;(&lt;I&gt;R&lt;/I&gt;)-(-)-24&lt;/B&gt; as auxiliary was used for the asymmetric reduction of ketones &lt;B&gt;25a-d &lt;/B&gt;and &lt;B&gt;26a,c&lt;/B&gt; in order to obtain the corresponding enantiopure alcohols. &lt;/P&gt;&#13;
&lt;P&gt;Racemic and enantiopure alcohols &lt;B&gt;27a-c,g,m&lt;/B&gt; and &lt;B&gt;31a-1&lt;/B&gt; were used as starting materials in multi-step syntheses for the corresponding &lt;I&gt;N&lt;/I&gt;-imidazole derivatives in racemic and enantiopure forms. Involved are three reaction steps: (a) Mitsunobu reaction with 4,5-dicyano imidazole to obtain the &lt;I&gt;N&lt;/I&gt;-4,5-dicyanoimidazole derivatives &lt;B&gt;33a-m&lt;/B&gt;; (b) hydrolyses of the &lt;I&gt;N&lt;/I&gt;-imidazole-4,5-dicarbonitrile derivatives &lt;B&gt;33a-m&lt;/B&gt; to the corresponding diacids &lt;B&gt;34a-m&lt;/B&gt;, (c) thermic decarboxylation of the diacids  &lt;B&gt;34a-m&lt;/B&gt; to the final &lt;I&gt;N&lt;/I&gt;-imidazole derivatives &lt;B&gt;35a-d.&lt;/P&gt;&lt;/B&gt;&lt;P&gt;This synthetic procedure was exceptionally well suited for the production of enantiopure &lt;I&gt;N&lt;/I&gt;-alkyl imidazole derivatives &lt;B&gt;34a,b&lt;/B&gt;, instead gave high chemical yield but complete racemic products with benzylic alcohols &lt;B&gt;31d &lt;/B&gt;and benzhydroles &lt;B&gt;27a-c.&lt;/P&gt;&lt;/B&gt;&lt;P&gt;  Using a modified Marckwald procedure starting from chiral amines &lt;B&gt;(&lt;I&gt;S&lt;/I&gt;)-(+)-44 &lt;/B&gt;and &lt;B&gt;(&lt;I&gt;S&lt;/I&gt;)-(+)-51&lt;/B&gt; it was possible to synthesize the imidazole ring and to obtain the corresponding enantiopure (&lt;I&gt;S&lt;/I&gt;)-(+)-1-(2-octyl) imidazole &lt;B&gt;(&lt;I&gt;S&lt;/I&gt;)-(+)-35a &lt;/B&gt;and (&lt;I&gt;S&lt;/I&gt;)-(+)&lt;B&gt;-&lt;/B&gt;1-phenyl-1-ethyl imidazole &lt;B&gt;(&lt;I&gt;S&lt;/I&gt;)-(+)-54. (&lt;I&gt;S&lt;/I&gt;)-(+)-35a &lt;/B&gt;presented an identical specific rotation as the corresponding compound obtained from the three step synthesis discussed above and proved the inversion of the configuration during the Mitsunobu reaction. &lt;/P&gt;&#13;
&lt;P&gt;In order to obtain the enantiopure aryl-2-benzo[b]furan methanols&lt;B&gt; 27 &lt;/B&gt;a new synthetic method was considered instead of the asymmetric reduction&lt;B&gt; &lt;/B&gt;of the corresponding ketones that lead to poor results. The use of the lipase SAMII allowed the synthesis of enantiopure 1-aryl-2-propyn-1-ols &lt;B&gt;(&lt;I&gt;R&lt;/I&gt;)-(-)-58a-c,e,h-l&lt;/B&gt; in high enantiomeric excesses and good chemical yields &lt;I&gt;via &lt;/I&gt;hydrolysis of corresponding racemic acetates &lt;B&gt;60a-c&lt;/B&gt; and chloroacetates &lt;B&gt;61a-l &lt;/B&gt;(Scheme 7.4). &lt;/P&gt;&#13;
&lt;P&gt;The racemic and enantiopure 1-aryl-2-propyn-1-ols &lt;B&gt;58 a-l&lt;/B&gt; were cyclized with 2-iodophenol to the corresponding aryl-2-benzo[b]furan carbinols &lt;B&gt;27g-h&lt;/B&gt; and &lt;B&gt;63a-d&lt;/B&gt; and with 2-&lt;I&gt;N&lt;/I&gt;-Mesyl iodoaniline to aryl-2-(&lt;I&gt;N&lt;/I&gt;-mesyl)indol carbinols &lt;B&gt;64a-g&lt;/B&gt; using Pd(0) as catalyst. Both products were obtained in high e.e. and chemical yield. These constitute the first applications of Pd catalyses with enantiopure arylpropynols.&lt;/P&gt;&#13;
&lt;P&gt;The reaction conditions were optimized in order to maximize chemical yields and enantiomeric excesses. Finally an hypothesis for the mechanism of cyclization was formulated. The first step is the Pd &lt;sup&gt;&lt;small&gt;0&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; catalyzed addition of the acetylenic compound to the 2-iodophenol leading to &lt;B&gt;62&lt;/B&gt;; the second step is the CuI catalyzed cyclization to benzo[b]furane derivatives &lt;B&gt;27 &lt;/B&gt;or to &lt;I&gt;N&lt;/I&gt;-Ms-indol derivatives &lt;B&gt;64&lt;/B&gt;.&lt;/P&gt;&#13;
&lt;P&gt;In conclusion the present work led to advances in the stereoselective synthesis of antifungal agents such as bifonazole &lt;B&gt;6a&lt;/B&gt; and the aromatase inhibitors &lt;B&gt;18&lt;/B&gt;; in fact the application of the described methodology to an enantiopure amine may probably lead to the target molecule in enantiopure form.&lt;/P&gt;</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 540 Chemie » 540 Chemie und zugeordnete Wissenschaften</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Chemie » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>