<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>413</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:54:540</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="de">Darstellung von neuen verzweigten und unverzweigten Cyclitolen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Braun, Martin</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2000-04-25</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fb09/diss2000/braun</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=413</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20000121</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-507/d090003.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">Starting from methyl-α-d-glucopyranoside the synthesis of protected 5-&lt;I&gt;epi&lt;/I&gt;-valiolone could be carried out via a &lt;I&gt;chiral-pool&lt;/I&gt;-synthesis using the Ferrier reaction as key-step. Valiolones are of biological and biochemical interest because of their possible function as an intermediate in the biosynthesis of acarbose, which is one of the most potent α-glucosidase-inhibitors and is commercially used for the treatment of diabetes mellitus.&#13;
Also by this route the synthesis of an inositol substitued with a C&lt;SUB&gt;1&lt;/SUB&gt;-branch was realized. This substance has pharmacological potential as a new, so far untested glycosidase-inhibitor.&#13;
&lt;P&gt;&#13;
In an alternative &lt;I&gt;de-novo&lt;/I&gt;-synthesis, starting from &lt;I&gt;p&lt;/I&gt;-benzoquinone, some biologically, biochemically and pharmacoligically interesting substances could be synthesized:&#13;
Valiol and 1-&lt;I&gt;epi&lt;/I&gt;-valiol are also possible intermediates of the acarbose-biosynthesis. These compounds could be synthesized for the first time and can now be used for testing in enzyme-reactions.&#13;
Many amino-substituted cyclitols are known to be highly effective glycosidase-inhibitors. The most prominent example is valienamine, but there are many other examples of branched and unbranched cyclitols with a amino-group in different positions. The synthesis of 7-amino valiol gave access to a new class of amino-substituted, branched cyclitols, which also may have potential as a glycosidase-inhibitor.&#13;
&lt;P&gt;&#13;
In the &lt;I&gt;de-novo&lt;/I&gt;-synthesis starting from &lt;I&gt;p&lt;/I&gt;-benzoquinone an independant synthesis of the cyclohexenone system, that results from the Ferrier reaction, could be carried out.&#13;
The advantage of this method is that all the products synthesized via pathways starting from &lt;I&gt;p&lt;/I&gt;-benzoquinone, can be obtained in both enantiomers, using a powerful enzymatic resolution with &lt;I&gt;Pig Pancreas Lipase&lt;/I&gt;.&#13;
&lt;/P&gt;</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 540 Chemie » 540 Chemie und zugeordnete Wissenschaften</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Chemie » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>