<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>4130</id><datestamp>2014-08-13</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:3:33:330</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">Price Competition in the enlarged EU 27 Export Market and the Role of Foreign Direct Investment</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Perret, Jens K.</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2014-08-13</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=4130</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20140813-092831-1</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">     From a microeconomic perspective competition between firms has been duely discussed. Extending microeconomic concepts to a macroeconomic level and considering competition between countries becomes more complex. The complexity issues is tackled in this study by extending a methodology developed in Borbely (2006) to account for specialization in specific sectors as well as price groups that under certain assumptions can be seen as a quality indicator. This study observes 27 EU countries - excluding Croatia - and Turkey. This allows for a view on the competition structure in the context of the EU common market.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;     In a second step of the analysis it is analyzed whether FDI inflows impact the price - quality - level of a sector or the probability to switch to a higher or a lower price level in said sector. Where in other publications including \cite{borbely06} for selected EU countries a positive impact of FDI inflows is found, this study finds for the EU as a whole or the EU 15 or EU 10+1 (including Turkey) sub-groups no significant impact of FDI inflows on the price level or the probability to switch to another price level.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="de">&lt;p&gt;JEL-Classification : F14, F15, L16&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Dateigröße : 815 KB</dc:description>
          <dc:source xml:lang="de">Schumpeter Discussion Papers&#13;
SDP14011&#13;
ISSN 1867-5352&#13;
Published : August 2014</dc:source>
          <dc:subject>Structural Change</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>European Union</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Price Competition</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Exports</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Revealed Comparative Advantages</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Export Unit Values</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>300 Sozialwissenschaften » 330 Wirtschaft » 330 Wirtschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Wirtschaftswissenschaft/Schumpeter School of Business and Economics » Schumpeter Discussion Papers (SDP)</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Texte » Book</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>