<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>416</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:54:540</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">Identification of  the midecamycin biosynthetic gene cluster in &lt;I&gt;Streptomyces mycarofaciens&lt;/I&gt; UC189B (ATCC 21454) and analysis of the enzymes for dTDP-D-mycaminose biosynthesis</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Cong, Lina</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2000-03-29</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fb09/diss2000/cong</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=416</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20000101</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-510/d090002.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="de">In dieser Arbeit wurden die folgenden Aspekte der Genetik und Biosynthese des Makrolids Midecamycin ausgearbeitet, um die Mechanismen der Makrolidzuckersynthese zu klären und Handwerkszeuge für die Herstellung hybrider Makrolide zu liefern.&#13;
&lt;OL&gt;&#13;
&lt;LI&gt;Durch sequentielles Screening einer genomischen DNA-Bank im Cosmidvektor pKU206 durch zwei homologe PCR-amplifizierte Genproben wurden zwei Regionen von insgesamt ca. 75 kb DNA isoliert, die die gewünschten Anteile des Midecamycin (&lt;I&gt;mid&lt;/I&gt;)&#13;
        Genclusters enthielten.&#13;
&#13;
&lt;LI&gt;Ca. 10 kb DNA aus Cosmid Smyc-LC1 und ca. 7 kb DNA aus Smyc-LC3 wurden komplett sequenziert. Die übrigen Regionen wurden durch partielle Sequenzierung charakterisiert, um weitere Informationen über Struktur und Genverteilung zu erhalten. Unter den Genen wurden 10 komplette und 14 unvollständige Leserahmen identifiziert, die für die Midecamycin-Biosynthese notwendig sind. Die Region der Mycarose-Biosynthesegene wurde auf Smyc-LC1 gefunden. Das komplette Set der Gene für Biosynthese und Transfer der Mycaminose wurde kloniert. Die Organisation des &lt;I&gt;mid&lt;/I&gt;&#13;
        Genclusters ist ähnlich wie in andern Makroliden zu beiden Seiten der&#13;
        zentralen PKS Gene mit zwei gemischten Gruppen von Zucker-,&#13;
        Acylierungs-, Resistenz- und Regulatorgenen strukturiert.&#13;
&#13;
&lt;LI&gt;Die Genen, &lt;I&gt;midC&lt;/I&gt;, &lt;I&gt;midH&lt;/I&gt;, &lt;I&gt;midK&lt;/I&gt; und &lt;I&gt;midI&lt;/I&gt;, wurden durch heterologe Expression  charakterisiert. MidC und MidH wurden als lösliche Proteine in &lt;I&gt;E. coli&lt;/I&gt; überproduziert, jeweils in nativer und&#13;
        His-tag fusionierter Primärstruktur. Die ebenfalls löslichen His-tag&#13;
        Proteine MidK und MidI wurden nur in geringer Menge gebildet und über&#13;
        Westernblot nachgewiesen.&#13;
&#13;
&lt;LI&gt;Um die postulierten Funktionen der MidH (3,4-Isomerase) und MidC (3-Aminotransferase) nachzuweisen, wurden die Produkte eines gekoppelten Enzymtests zur Umsetzung von dTDP-D-Glucose mit RmlB (4,6-Dehydratase), MidH und MidC mittles HPLC und LC-MS Techniken ausgewertet. Es wurde bestätigt, daß das MidC Protein verantwortlich ist für die Transaminierungsreaktion bei der Bildung des dTDP-Amino-6-Deoxy-D-Glucose.&lt;/LI&gt;&#13;
&lt;/OL&gt;</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">In this study the following aspects have been worked out by studying the genetics of midecamycin biosynthesis as a model system to elucidate the biosynthesis of sugar components in 16-membered macrolides and to acquire tools for the production of new hybrid macrolide antibiotics.&#13;
&lt;OL&gt;&#13;
&lt;LI&gt;By sequentially screening a genomic library in the cosmid vector pKU206 via two homologous gene probes which were detected by PCR, the midecamycin biosynthetic (&lt;I&gt;mid&lt;/I&gt;) gene cluster has been identified in the isolated ca. 74 kb DNA in the genome of &lt;I&gt;S&lt;/I&gt;. &lt;I&gt;mycarofaciens&lt;/I&gt;, falling into two regions.&#13;
&#13;
&lt;LI&gt;About 10 kb DNA from the cosmid Smyc-LC1 and ca. 7 kb DNA from the cosmid Smyc-LC3 were sequenced contiguously. The remaining regions of these two cosmids were partially sequenced to get further information on extension and informational contents of the cluster. Among them, 10 genes with complete reading frames and 14 genes incomplete were identified, all of which are necessary for midecamycin biosynthesis. The region of genes responsible for mycarose biosynthesis was found in Smyc-LC1. A complete set of genes for the biosynthesis and transfer of mycaminose was identified. The organisation of the overall &lt;I&gt;mid&lt;/I&gt; gene cluster revealed that, similar to&#13;
        other macrolide gene clusters, the PKS genes are flanked by two regions&#13;
        containing genes encoding enzymes for sugar biosynthesis, with others&#13;
        for resistance, regulatory, and sugar or lactone modification.&#13;
&#13;
&lt;LI&gt;The genes, &lt;I&gt;midC&lt;/I&gt;, &lt;I&gt;midH&lt;/I&gt;, &lt;I&gt;midK&lt;/I&gt; and &lt;I&gt;midI&lt;/I&gt;, were characterised by heterologous expression of these enzymes. MidC and MidH were over-produced as soluble proteins in &lt;I&gt;E.&lt;/I&gt; &lt;I&gt;coli&lt;/I&gt; both in native form and as His-tag fusion.&#13;
        Soluble proteins His-tag-MidK and His-tag-MidI were detected only by&#13;
        Western blotting in low quantities.&#13;
&#13;
&lt;LI&gt;To characterise the postulated function of MidH (3,4-isomerase) and MidC (3-aminotransferase), the products of a coupling enzymatic reaction to convert dTDP-D-glucose by RmlB (4,6-dehydratase), MidH and MidC were analysed by HPLC and LC-MS. It has been confirmed that the MidC protein is responsible for transamination to form dTDP-amino-6-deoxy-D-glucose.&lt;/LI&gt;&#13;
&lt;/OL&gt;</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 540 Chemie » 540 Chemie und zugeordnete Wissenschaften</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Chemie » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>