<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>421</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:54:540</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="de">Difluorcarben-Reaktionen des Bis(trifluormethyl)cadmiums: Synthese von partiell fluorierten organischen Verbindungen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Haiges, Ralf</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2000-12-15</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fb09/diss2000/haiges</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=421</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20000518</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-515/d090020.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="de">&lt;P ALIGN="justify"&gt;In nicht-koordinierenden Lösungsmitteln ist (CF&lt;SUB&gt;3&lt;/SUB&gt;)&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt;Cd extrem reaktiv und eliminiert bereits bei Temperaturen deutlich unter 0°C quantitativ CF&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt;. In Gegenwart von elektronenreichen Alkenen und Alkinen erfolgt CF&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt;-Addition unter Bildung von Cyclopropanen und -propenen, während im Falle von elektronenarmen Doppelbindungssystemen bevorzugt Dimerisierung von CF&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt; erfolgt. Bei En-Molekülen mit asymmetrischer sterischer Hinderung, wie den Carenen, verläuft die kinetisch kontrollierte CF&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt;-Addition stereospezifisch. Durch Addition an, von chiralen Tartraten abgeleiteten, chiralen α,β-ungesättigten Acetalen werden hohe Diastereoselektivitäten erreicht. Für diese Reaktion konnte eine alternative Methode entwickelt werden, welche das (CF&lt;SUB&gt;3&lt;/SUB&gt;)&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt;Cd durch Diethylcadmium und CF&lt;SUB&gt;3&lt;/SUB&gt;I ersetzt. Tieftemperatur-NMR-Untersuchungen deuten darauf hin, dass hierbei CF&lt;SUB&gt;3&lt;/SUB&gt;CdEt die aktive Difluorcarbenquelle darstellt.&lt;/P&gt;&#13;
&lt;P ALIGN="justify"&gt;Oxirane werden durch (CF&lt;SUB&gt;3&lt;/SUB&gt;)&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt;Cd in hohen Ausbeuten in Difluorcyclopropane überführt.&lt;/P&gt;&#13;
&lt;P ALIGN="justify"&gt;Die kontrollierte thermische Zersetzung von (CF&lt;SUB&gt;3&lt;/SUB&gt;)&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt;Cd in Gegenwart von Alkoholen und Carbonsäuren führt zu Difluormethylethern und –estern. Die Ausbeuten hängen hierbei von der Acidität der OH-Funktion ab.&lt;/P&gt;&#13;
&lt;P ALIGN="justify"&gt;Während aromatische Aldehyde durch (CF&lt;SUB&gt;3&lt;/SUB&gt;)&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt;Cd in Difluormethylbenzol-Derivate überführt werden, stellen &lt;I&gt;gem&lt;/I&gt;-(Difluormethoxy)fluoralkane die Hauptprodukte von aliphatischen Aldehyden dar. Analoge Reaktionen werden im Falle von Ketonen beobachtet. Der Mechanismus dieser Umsetzungen wird diskutiert. Die Reaktion mit sterisch beladenen cycloaliphatischen Thioketonen führt zur Bildung von Difluorthiiranen und 2,2-Difluor-1,3-dithiacyclopentanen. Aromatische Thioketone werden in 1,1,2,2-Tetrafluorcyclopropane überführt.&lt;/P&gt;&#13;
&lt;P ALIGN="justify"&gt;Die stereospezifische Öffnung des Dreirings in 2-Alkoxymethyl-1,1-difluor-3-phenylcyclopropanen ist durch starke Säuren, wie Bromwasserstoff- oder Perchlorsäure, möglich. In ähnlicher Weise können 4-Chlor-3,3-difluor-4-phenyl-1-butene durch Reaktion dieser Cyclopropane mit SOCl&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt;, SnCl&lt;SUB&gt;4&lt;/SUB&gt; oder SbCl&lt;SUB&gt;5&lt;/SUB&gt; erhalten werden. Die entsprechenden Iod-Derivate sind mit Me&lt;SUB&gt;3&lt;/SUB&gt;SiI zugänglich.&lt;/P&gt;</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;P ALIGN="justify"&gt;The aim of this thesis was (a) to explore the synthetic potential of the recently available, donor-free bis(&lt;A NAME="temp"&gt;&lt;/A&gt;trifluoromethyl)cadmium, (CF&lt;SUB&gt;3&lt;/SUB&gt;)&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt;Cd, as a low-temperature source for the generation of difluorocarbene, CF&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt;, (b) to synthesize a variety of difluorocyclopropanes, (c) to examine possibilities for the controlled stereospecific addition of CF&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt; to multiple bond systems or its insertion into acidic X-H bonds, and (d) to investigate the reactivity of selected difluorocyclopropanes. &lt;/P&gt;&#13;
&lt;P ALIGN="justify"&gt;While the reactivity is reduced by donor molecules, (CF&lt;SUB&gt;3&lt;/SUB&gt;)&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt;Cd is extremely reactive in non-coordinating solvents and evolves CF&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt; well below 0 °C. In the presence of electron-rich alkenes or alkynes, cyclopropanes or cyclopropenes, respectively, are formed in high yields, while dimerization of CF&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt; is preferred with electron–poor systems such as allyl bromide. The kinetically controlled addition of CF&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt; to sterically hindered double bonds such as carenes proceeds stereospecifically. High diastereospecificity is achieved upon addition of CF&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt; to chiral α,β-unsaturated acetals which are derived from aldehydes and chiral tartrates. For this reaction, an alternative "one-pot" synthesis was developed replacing the dangerous (CF&lt;SUB&gt;3&lt;/SUB&gt;)&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt;Cd by diethylcadmium and CF&lt;SUB&gt;3&lt;/SUB&gt;I. Low-temperature NMR investigations indicated that CF&lt;SUB&gt;3&lt;/SUB&gt;CdEt is the active CF&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt; source in this case.&lt;/P&gt;&#13;
&lt;P ALIGN="justify"&gt;Oxiranes are converted by (CF&lt;SUB&gt;3&lt;/SUB&gt;)&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt;Cd to the corresponding difluorocyclopropanes by desoxygenation followed by re-addition of CF&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt;. &lt;/P&gt;&#13;
&lt;P ALIGN="justify"&gt;The controlled thermal decomposition of (CF&lt;SUB&gt;3&lt;/SUB&gt;)&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt;Cd in the presence of alcohols or carboxylic acids allows the preparation of difluoromethyl ethers or esters, respectively - the yields depending on the acidity of the respective OH function. &lt;/P&gt;&#13;
&lt;P ALIGN="justify"&gt;While 1,1-difluoromethylbenzene derivatives are obtained from (CF&lt;SUB&gt;3&lt;/SUB&gt;)&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt;Cd with aromatic aldehydes, &lt;I&gt;gem&lt;/I&gt;-(difluoromethyl)fluoroalkanes are the major products of the reaction with aliphatic aldehydes. Corresponding conversions are found with ketones. The mechanism of the reactions is discussed. In case of aliphatic ketones, elimination of HF followed by addition of CF&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt; also provides 1,1,2-trifluoro- and 1,1-difluoro-2-(difluoromethoxy)cyclopropanes in moderate amounts. &lt;/P&gt;&#13;
&lt;P ALIGN="justify"&gt;With sterically crowded cycloaliphatic thioketones, both formation of difluorothiiranes and of 2,2-difluoro-1,3-dithiacyclopentanes are observed, the latter being formed by addition of CF&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt; to the CS double bond followed by addition of a second thioketone molecule and cyclization. Aromatic thioketones are converted to 1,1,2,2-tetrafluorocyclopropanes by desulfurization and addition of a second CF&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt; moiety.&lt;/P&gt;&#13;
&lt;P ALIGN="justify"&gt;The stereospecific opening of the three membered ring of 2-alkoxymethyl-1,1-difluoro-3-phenylcyclopropanes is possible with strong acids such as hydrobromic or perchloric acid. Similarly, 4-chloro-3,3-difluoro-4-phenyl-1-butenes are obtained by reaction of these cyclopropanes with SOCl&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt;, SnCl&lt;SUB&gt;4&lt;/SUB&gt;, or SbCl&lt;SUB&gt;5&lt;/SUB&gt; while the corresponding iodo derivatives are accessible by reaction with Me&lt;SUB&gt;3&lt;/SUB&gt;SiI. &lt;/P&gt;</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 540 Chemie » 540 Chemie und zugeordnete Wissenschaften</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Chemie » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>