<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>432</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:54:540</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="de">Synthese und Eigenschaften hydrophiler Arylphosphate</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Hingst, Martin</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2000-12-14</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fb09/diss2000/hingst</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=432</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20000505</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-526/d090019.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">This work presents a new and efficient approach to hydrophilic aromatic phosphines, the palladium-catalyzed P-C coupling reaction. By coupling of primary and secondary phosphines with a great variety of different functionalized aromatic halocarbons a number of novel phosphines (&lt;B&gt;12&lt;/B&gt;, &lt;B&gt;14&lt;/B&gt;-&lt;B&gt;32&lt;/B&gt;,&lt;B&gt; 34&lt;/B&gt;) bearing electron rich (-NH&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt;, -OH, -CH&lt;SUB&gt;3&lt;/SUB&gt;) as well as electron poor substituents (-COOR,  -COOH, -SO&lt;SUB&gt;3&lt;/SUB&gt;H) are accessible. Even multifunctional phosphines with a combination of equal (e. g. &lt;B&gt;24&lt;/B&gt;,&lt;B&gt; 30&lt;/B&gt;) or different substituents (e. g. &lt;B&gt;25&lt;/B&gt;, &lt;B&gt;27&lt;/B&gt;)  at the aromatic groups can be obtained in good to high yields. The required catalyst concentrations are low (0.05-0.2 mol%), and no formation of side products is observed.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;The coupling reactions of Ph&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt;PH with aromatic halocarbons can simply be initiated by addition of Pd(OAc)&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt; as a precatalyst, whereas the corresponding reactions of PhPH&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt; need Pd(0) complexes that contain chelating phosphine ligands as a catalyst. It has been shown that a solution of Pd(dba)dppp, which is easily prepared in situ of Pd(dba)&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt; and dppp, is satisfying for that purpose.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;In contrast to alternative methods the Pd-catalysed coupling of primary phosphines like PhPH&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt; with one equivalent of an aromatic halocarbon (e. g. 3-iodo-4-methylbenzoic acid) offers a direct route to secondary phosphines like &lt;B&gt;34&lt;/B&gt; without the need of protecting groups at the phosphorus atom or excess of the educt phosphine. Further reaction of &lt;B&gt;34 &lt;/B&gt;with 3-iodobenzoic acid yields the p-chiral phosphine &lt;B&gt;35&lt;/B&gt;.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;Reaction of 5-diphenylphosphinosalicylic acid &lt;B&gt;16&lt;/B&gt; with phenylboronic acid affords&lt;B&gt; 36&lt;/B&gt;, an interesting ligand with a Lewis acceptor function at the boron atom. In the presence of NEt&lt;SUB&gt;4&lt;/SUB&gt;OH &lt;B&gt;16&lt;/B&gt; is converted by B(OH)&lt;SUB&gt;3&lt;/SUB&gt; into the chiral bidentate phosphine &lt;B&gt;37 &lt;/B&gt;which forms with [(nor)RhCl]&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt; the chiral binuclear Rhodium complex &lt;B&gt;44&lt;/B&gt;.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;Reactions of the sulfonated phosphine ligands &lt;B&gt;38&lt;/B&gt; and &lt;B&gt;39&lt;/B&gt; with the Rhodium precursors [Rh(CO)&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt;Cl)]&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt; and [Rh(C&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt;H&lt;SUB&gt;4&lt;/SUB&gt;)&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt;Cl)]&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt; in the biphasic medium toluene/H&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt;O lead to the hydrophilic Rhodium complexes &lt;B&gt;40&lt;/B&gt;-&lt;B&gt;43&lt;/B&gt;, the latter being a water soluble derivative of the Wilkinson catalyst.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;The catalytic properties of a selection of the obtained phosphine ligands (&lt;B&gt;12&lt;/B&gt;, &lt;B&gt;13&lt;/B&gt;, &lt;B&gt;17&lt;/B&gt;, &lt;B&gt;18&lt;/B&gt;, &lt;B&gt;30&lt;/B&gt;) under the conditions of the Shell Higher Olefin Process have been investigated, showing 5-diphenylphosphinoanthranilic acid &lt;B&gt;18&lt;/B&gt;&#13;
      being able to form an active catalyst.&#13;
      &lt;P&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The synthesized compounds were characterized by &lt;SUP&gt;1&lt;/SUP&gt;H-, &lt;SUP&gt;13&lt;/SUP&gt;C- and &lt;SUP&gt;31&lt;/SUP&gt;P-NMR spectroscopy, elemental analyses , IR- and mass spectra. The structures of &lt;b&gt;16 &lt;/b&gt;and &lt;b&gt;33 &lt;/b&gt;have been determined by X-ray crystallography.&lt;/p&gt;</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 540 Chemie » 540 Chemie und zugeordnete Wissenschaften</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Chemie » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>