<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>449</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:54:540</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="de">Synthese von Aminosäurephosphanen und Darstellung von Derivaten des Triphenylphosphans durch palladiumkatalysierte P-C- Kupplung</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Tepper, Michael</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2000-12-12</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fb09/diss2000/tepper</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=449</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20000493</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-544/d090018.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">The first section of this work was dedicated to the development of nucleophilic phosphination reactions&#13;
on aromatic fluoro compounds. Phosphino- derivatives of the α-amino&#13;
acids phenylglycine and phenylalanine have been obtained by reaction of the potassium- salts of 2, or&#13;
4-fluorophenylglycine- or alanine respectively with KPPh&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt; using DME as solvent. The x-ray&#13;
structural analysis of &lt;B&gt;1&lt;/B&gt; reveals the bulky nature of the PPh&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt;- substituent in &lt;I&gt;ortho&lt;/I&gt;&#13;
position to the amino acid substituent and the betaine type structure in the&#13;
α-amino acid moiety of &lt;B&gt;1&lt;/B&gt;. Derivatives of&#13;
2-diphenylphosphino-phenylglycine &lt;B&gt;1,&lt;/B&gt; bearing N-, O-, P- protecting groups have been synthesed and&#13;
investigated. N-acetyl protected amino acid &lt;B&gt;9&lt;/B&gt; was accessible by reaction of &lt;B&gt;1&lt;/B&gt; with&#13;
Ac&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt;O in good yields. The methylester &lt;B&gt;10&lt;/B&gt; was obtained by using equimolar amounts&#13;
of HC(OMe)&lt;SUB&gt;3&lt;/SUB&gt;/ CF&lt;SUB&gt;3&lt;/SUB&gt;COOH/ MeOH. Due to the low solubility of &lt;B&gt;1&lt;/B&gt; in solvents&#13;
like toluene its reaction with sulphur failed, the phosphine oxide &lt;B&gt;11&lt;/B&gt; was easily accessible by&#13;
oxidation of &lt;B&gt;1&lt;/B&gt; with H&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt;O&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt;.&#13;
      &lt;P&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&#13;
&lt;P&gt;A new synthetic approach to the aldehyde &lt;B&gt;15&lt;/B&gt; has been developed using acetal protected&#13;
2-fluorobenzaldehyde and KPPh&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt;. &lt;B&gt;15&lt;/B&gt; was obtained in 85 % overall yield. Base catalysed&#13;
reaction of the aldehyde &lt;B&gt;15&lt;/B&gt; with HP(O)(OMe)&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt; and HP(O)Me&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt; afforded the&#13;
α-hydroxyphosphonic acid compound &lt;B&gt;16&lt;/B&gt; and&#13;
the phosphine oxide &lt;B&gt;17&lt;/B&gt;. The analogous α-aminophosphonic&#13;
acid and phosphanoxide have been obtained by reaction of the aldimine &lt;B&gt;18&lt;/B&gt; with HP(O)(OEt)&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt;&#13;
and HP(O)Me&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt;. Wittig reaction of &lt;B&gt;15&lt;/B&gt; with Ph&lt;SUB&gt;3&lt;/SUB&gt;P=CHCO&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt;Me yielded the&#13;
cinnamic ester &lt;B&gt;22&lt;/B&gt;. The alkali metal salts of the cinnamic acid &lt;B&gt;23&lt;/B&gt; show an unusual high solubility&#13;
in water (&gt; 500 g &lt;B&gt;23&lt;/B&gt; in 1000 g H&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt;O at ambient temperature). &lt;/P&gt;&#13;
&lt;P&gt;Using KO&lt;SUP&gt;t&lt;/SUP&gt;Bu/DME as deprotonation agent twofold arylation of 2-pyridylphosphine with&#13;
F-C&lt;SUB&gt;6&lt;/SUB&gt;H&lt;SUB&gt;4&lt;/SUB&gt;-SO&lt;SUB&gt;3&lt;/SUB&gt;K was possible and afforded ligand &lt;B&gt;24&lt;/B&gt; with a surprisingly&#13;
low solubility in water. The molecular structure of &lt;B&gt;24&lt;/B&gt; has been determinated by x-ray structural analysis.&lt;/P&gt;&#13;
&lt;P&gt;The second part of this work was concerned with the development of new synthetic methologies for derivatives of&#13;
triphenylphosphine bearing +M/ +I substituents like OH, NH&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt;, alkyl which were not accessible by&#13;
nucleophilic phosphination of fluoro aromatic compounds. Prompted by literature reports a novel type of&#13;
catalytic P-C cross coupling reaction was discovered. Reaction of secondary phosphines (PhPHR, R= Ph,&#13;
CH&lt;SUB&gt;3&lt;/SUB&gt;) with functionalized iodo aromatic compounds in presence of catalytic amounts of&#13;
Pd(OAc)&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt; afforded tertiary phosphines bearing a wide range of different substituents. The&#13;
reaction was found to be independent of the electronic nature of the substituents. A multitude of&#13;
triphenylphosphine derivatives ((&lt;I&gt;o&lt;/I&gt;, &lt;I&gt;m&lt;/I&gt;,&#13;
&lt;I&gt;p&lt;/I&gt;)-Ph&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt;PC&lt;SUB&gt;6&lt;/SUB&gt;H&lt;SUB&gt;(4-n)&lt;/SUB&gt;-R&lt;SUB&gt;n&lt;/SUB&gt; R=  CH&lt;SUB&gt;3&lt;/SUB&gt;,&#13;
NH&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt;, OH, CO&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt;Me, CH&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt;OH, NHC(NH&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt;)&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt;&lt;SUP&gt;+&lt;/SUP&gt;)&#13;
and heteroaromatic substituted phosphines have been synthesised in excellent yields. By arylation of&#13;
primary phosphines (RPH&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt;, R= aryl, alkyl) with one equivalent of the iodo compound secondary&#13;
phosphines could be obtained selectively. Arylation reactions with secondary phosphines were catalysed&#13;
by using  0.01 to 0.1 mol% Pd(OAc)&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt;. For the corresponding reactions with PhPH&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt;&#13;
and other primary phosphines a palladium(0)complex formed by Pd&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt;(dba)&lt;SUB&gt;3&lt;/SUB&gt; with equimolar&#13;
amounts of a chelating ligand like dppp has been employed. Using this method triphenylphosphine ligands&#13;
bearing hydrophilic guanidinium moieties have been obtained by reaction of iodophenylguanidines with PhRPH&#13;
(R= H, Ph) in excellent yields. The structure of the guanidinium phosphines has been revealed by structural&#13;
analysis and multinuclear NMR- spectroscopy including &lt;SUP&gt;15&lt;/SUP&gt;N-NMR- spectroscopy.&lt;/P&gt;</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 540 Chemie » 540 Chemie und zugeordnete Wissenschaften</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Chemie » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>