<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>4581</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:54:547</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">Chemical Characterization of Native Chili Peppers (&lt;i&gt;Capsicum&lt;/i&gt; spp.)</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Meckelmann, Sven Werner</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2018-01-22</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/chemie/diss2014/meckelmann</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=4581</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20150204-110700-6</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-4528/dc1433.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">The genus Capsicum belongs to the botanical family of Nightshades (Solanaceae) and is closely related to other important crops from the “New World” like tomato, eggplant, potato or tobacco. For over 6,000 years, their fruits were used for many purposes and not only as spice or food in the human diet. Peru and Bolivia are the supposed center of origin of the genus Capsicum. Germplasm banks in both countries hold more than thousand different chili pepper accessions, which have never been characterized. This study had the aim of analyzing the phytochemical composition and major quality traits with evaluating the environmental impact on these traits by multi-location and year-to-year comparison. Partner institutions in Peru and Bolivia provided the dried and crushed chili pepper sample materials.&#13;
Improved analytical methods and a streamlined analytical strategy were applied to analyze 362 different chili pepper accessions. The analytical procedures included the determination of pungency by major capsaicinoids and pattern of capsaicin, dihydrocapsaicin and nordihydrocapsaicin. In addition, health promoting phytonutrients and parameters such as flavonoid aglycons (quercetin, luteolin, kaempferol and apigenin), total polyphenols according to the Folin-Ciocalteu method, the antioxidant capacity (TEAC assay), vitamin E by analyzing the content of a-, ß- and ?-tocopherol and vitamin C (ascorbic acid) were determined. The set of analytical parameters was extended by the analysis of fat content, surface and extractable color (ASTA 20.1).&lt;br&gt;&#13;
The sample set included the five domesticated species C. annuum, C. baccatum, C. chinense, C. frutescens, and C. pubescens and some wild species belonging to C. baccatum var.&#13;
baccatum and C. eximium. Within the sample set, Capsicum accessions were identified showing pungency from non-pungent to extremely pungent and with outstanding content in valuable health-related phytochemicals.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
Multivariate data evaluation by principal component analysis (PCA) and partial least square regression (PLS) did not show any underlying structures when replanting experiments were evaluated. However, significant influences of the environment on the concentration and levels were observed by analysis of variance (ANOVA) indicating the high influence of the environment on the traits.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
The obtained data allowed identifying high value accessions. All analytical data were submitted to the project partners in Peru and Bolivia to select high value accessions and to start market specialization or as starting point for further breeding programs focusing on nutrition quality. Thus, the study results add value to the Capsicum diversity of Peru and Bolivia to generate higher income for small-scale chili farmers. In addition, this helps conserving local native chili peppers through their use as high value crop.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 540 Chemie » 547 Organische Chemie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Chemie » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>