<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>466</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:54:540</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="de">Zum Carry over von Toxaphen in Legehennen und Eiern - Beitrag zur Etablierung eines Höchstwertes für Toxaphenrückstände in Futtermitteln für Legehennen auf Basis einer indikatorspezifischen Analytik</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Kaltenecker, Martin</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2001-07-25</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fb09/diss2001/kaltenecker</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=466</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20010417</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-561/d090105.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="de">&lt;p&gt;A feeding study with 87 laying hens subdivided&#13;
into 5 test groups was carried out. The addition of technical toxaphene to the&#13;
hens’ diet was 0, 0.1, 0.5, 1.0, or 5.0 mg/kg, respectively. The feeding was&#13;
continued for 38 weeks. The accumulation and depletion behaviour was&#13;
investigated in eggs, muscle tissue, liver, kidney, blood, and faeces. &lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&#13;
Similar as in fish, some typical&#13;
toxaphene congeners could be identified in laying hens and were present in&#13;
higher concentration levels, when the feed was contaminated with toxaphene.&#13;
Because of this fact, toxaphene residues can be quantified on the basis of&#13;
these main congeners. &lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&#13;
This study demonstrated that&#13;
toxaphene congeners accumulate only in adipose tissues. The congeners Parlar&#13;
No. 26, 41, 42, 44, 50, 62 and 63 had the highest accumulation potential of all&#13;
22 tested toxaphene congeners. In adipose tissue, the carry over factors of&#13;
these congeners were calculated to give values between 8 and 14. The carry over&#13;
factors in yolk ranged between 1.4 and 2.6 and in liver between 0.9 and 2.0. No&#13;
accumulation could be found in the hens’ muscle tissue, kidney, blood, or&#13;
faeces, with carry over factors all being below 1. &lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&#13;
The obtained data allowed to set up&#13;
dose/tissue concentration diagrams which could be used to calculate the&#13;
toxaphene concentration in the tissue when the amount of the toxaphene&#13;
contamination of the diet is known.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&#13;
For the most abundant congeners the biological half life periods&#13;
were determined. These were between 25 and 49 days in matrices with high fat content&#13;
(depot fat, yolk, kidney). In tissues with lower fat content (muscle tissues,&#13;
blood, faeces) toxaphene was depleted much quicker. For those congeners with&#13;
the highest accumulation potential, the half life period in muscle meat gave&#13;
values between 15 and 22 days.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&#13;
Balancing the fate of ingested toxaphene it can be stated that 5-10 %&#13;
were trapped in the animals’ bodies. Only 2-4 % were identified as&#13;
unmetabolised congeners in the faeces. The main route of excretion was the egg.&#13;
22 % or 37 % of unmetabolised toxaphene was depleted via egg or egg yolk,&#13;
respectively&lt;/p&gt;</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 540 Chemie » 540 Chemie und zugeordnete Wissenschaften</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Chemie » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>