<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>4690</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:54:540</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="de">Synthese von Aminokonduritolen und Inositolphosphat-Analoga</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Gün, Ümit</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2018-01-22</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/chemie/diss2014/guen</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=4690</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20150318-124858-9</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-4630/dc1435.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;p&gt;After the discovery that the Inositolphosphate (1,4,5)IP&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; is a Ca-mobilizing ”second messenger”&#13;
and involved in diverse cell processes the research in that field has been focussed&#13;
on the synthesis of this and other inositol phosphates aswell as their modified analogues&#13;
to clarify their role in cell processes and their potential use for pharmaceutical purposes.&#13;
Up to now a number of analogues have been described. In this thesis the synthesis of new&#13;
analogues is described, which in contrary to known systems exhibit a better binding to&#13;
Protein-Domäne.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;In the first part of the thesis an unsymmetrical concept is described which enables the&#13;
synthesis of some phosphorylamino substituted inositol derivatives via building blocks,&#13;
which could be also used for the preparation of so called mixed phosphorylamino inositols.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The second part deals with the synthesis especially of bisphosphorylamino inositol derivatives&#13;
by a symmetrical concept. In this approach new &lt;i&gt;anti&lt;/i&gt;-benzenebisimines could be&#13;
prepared, which are isosters of &lt;i&gt;anti&lt;/i&gt;-benzenedioxide.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The synthesized phosphorylamino inositol derivatives could be successfully transformed&#13;
to potential prodrug systems.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;In a third part more inositolphosphate analogues could be prepared, which are not accessible&#13;
or only with great difficulties via the desribed routes, using a direct route starting&#13;
from myo-inositol via its 1,2-mono- or 1,2-diacetal protected derivatives.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;In a fourth chapter the synthesis of amino- and diamino conduritols either in racemic or&#13;
in enantiomerically pure form is described using building blocks which have been made&#13;
accessible by the above mentioned methods. With regard to ”Green Chemistry” only&#13;
reactions were used, which use water as solvent. In this context a cascade click reaction&#13;
could be developped which allows the simple transformation of bromohydrins into 1,2-&#13;
aminoalcohols and thereby the easy preparation of aminofunctionalized conduritols and&#13;
inositols.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 540 Chemie » 540 Chemie und zugeordnete Wissenschaften</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Chemie » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>