<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>4771</id><datestamp>2015-05-06</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:3:33:330</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">Energy and Material Efficiency Improvements, Compliance Strategies, and Investments in Resource Efficiency: A Cross-Country Study</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Dienes, Christian</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2015-05-06</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=4771</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20150506-111215-1</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;p&gt;This paper empirically studies the relationship between different compliance strategies concerning environmental legislation and intentions of entrepreneurs to increase their firms’ material and energy efficiency&#13;
in the next two years. Moreover, I examine the relationship between such intentions and the extent to which entrepreneurs are satisfied with past investments in resource efficiency improvements. Using data covering&#13;
small and medium-sized enterprises from 36 countries from 2013, this study also explores the institutional framework regarding the stringency and enforcement of national environmental regulations. The results based&#13;
on the total sample indicate that entrepreneurs who are more satisfied with past resource efficiency investments and who follow a strategy which goes beyond compliance are more likely to intend material and energy efficiency&#13;
improvements in the future. The results further suggest that entrepreneurs translate their pro-environmental attitudes into intentions to reduce their demand for energy but not their demand for materials.&#13;
Furthermore, the results based on subgroup analyses also point to decreasing marginal productivities of resource efficiency investments.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="de">Dateigröße: 707 KB</dc:description>
          <dc:source xml:lang="de">Schumpeter Discussion Papers SDP15004 ISSN 1867-5352 Published : May 2015</dc:source>
          <dc:subject>energy and material efficiency improvements</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>return on investment</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>compliance strategy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>environmental regulation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>300 Sozialwissenschaften » 330 Wirtschaft » 330 Wirtschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Wirtschaftswissenschaft/Schumpeter School of Business and Economics » Schumpeter Discussion Papers (SDP)</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Texte » Book</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>