<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>oai:elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de:3351</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:54:540</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="de">Untersuchungen von Niere und anderen Matrices auf β-Lactam-Antibiotika mittels rezeptorgestützten Chemilumineszenz-Tests</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Wehe, Lena</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2018-01-22</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/chemie/diss2012/wehe</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=3351</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20130206-145313-0</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-3468/dc1228.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;p&gt;Penicillins and cephalosporines, which belong to the group of ß-lactam antibiotics, are, together&#13;
with tetracyclines and macrolides, the most commonly used antibiotics for the therapy and&#13;
prophylaxis of bacterical infections in food delivering animals. Therefore, maximum residue&#13;
limits (MRL) exist in the EU relating to the antimicrobial properties of the ß-lactams. In order to&#13;
control the application and possible illegal use of ß-lactams, screening methods are useful to get&#13;
first results cheap and rapidly.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;In this work, the application of chemiluminescence (CL) as an analytical tool for the detection of&#13;
residues of ß-lactam antibiotics in porcine kidney juice and other matrices was investigated.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The developed method is based on an indirect competitive microtiter plate assay that uses the&#13;
penicillin-binding protein PBP 2x* as receptor for ß-lactam antibiotics. The PBP 2x* were coated&#13;
on a microtiter plate, and a digoxigenin labeled ampicillin (Dig-Ampi) was used to compete with&#13;
free beta-lactams in the sample. In a next step, we added anti-digoxigenin F&lt;sub&gt;ab&lt;/sub&gt; fragments (F&lt;sub&gt;ab&lt;/sub&gt;)&#13;
that were conjugated with horseradish peroxidase (HRP). These conjugated antibodies can bind&#13;
to the digoxigenin-moiety of Dig-Ampi. In the last step, a CL based technique was used as detection&#13;
system. Therefore the luminol oxidation catalyzed by HRP was used. The obtained signal&#13;
was reversely related to the ß-lactam concentration in the sample.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The assay format utilizing PBP 2x* based on a previous work developed in our research group,&#13;
but was modified with regard to a CL based technique. In the previously developed colorimetric&#13;
assay format, an HRP catalyzed oxidation with tetramethylbenzidine as chromogen was used.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Experimental parameters of the CL assay, for example amount of PBP 2x*, Dig-Ampi, F&lt;sub&gt;ab&lt;/sub&gt;, luminol&#13;
reagent volume, and measurement time were characterized and optimized for low consumption&#13;
of the expensive assay compounds and for high sensitivity.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;A variety of food matrices, mainly kidney, but also milk and muscle tissue, were investigated by&#13;
the CL assay and the results were compared to the colorimetric assay format.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Matrix interferences from kidney juice could be minimized by a centrifugation and dilution step.&#13;
A full factorial design was used to examine significant matrix interferences. For both assay formats,&#13;
the parameter “texture” (comparison: kidney-muscle) showed a significant matrix effect to&#13;
the measurement performance. Thus, a calibration in blank matrix is necessary. In contrast to&#13;
the colorimetric assay, no significant matrix effect was detected for the parameter animal species&#13;
(comparison: pork-beef), when using the CL assay.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The performance criteria limit of detection (LOD), limit of quantification (LOQ), precision, repeatability,&#13;
and working range were investigated for the determination in spiked kidney juice&#13;
and milk. 20 porcine kidney samples were analyzed for precision of the assay formats.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Benzylpenicillin, ampicillin, cefquinom and ceftiofur (measured as desfuroylcefitofur, the active&#13;
metabolite) were detected at concentrations below their respective MRL. LOD and LOQ were&#13;
twofold lower for the CL assay than for the colorimetric assay. However, the increased sensitivity&#13;
of the CL assay leads to a loss of precision and higher interference of matrix compounds. Nevertheless,&#13;
the CL assay represents a good alternative to the colorimetric test system and is applicable&#13;
for the screening of ß-lactam residues in a variety of food matrices.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Based on the developed CL assay, a test system for single sample measurements was designed&#13;
by using magnetic beads as surface to immobilize PBP 2*. For this purpose, a commercial&#13;
Charm II receptor test equipment was used. The experiments have shown that the CL assay format&#13;
could not be transferred to this type of equipment. Significant interference of nonspecific&#13;
interactions and difficulties in the separation technique were observed.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;In conclusion, the experiments on kidney juice have shown that both microtiter plate assay formats&#13;
(CL and colorimetric) are suitable for the semi-quantitative screening of ß-lactams. An advantage&#13;
of the CL assay over the colorimetric assay is the higher sensitivity.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 540 Chemie » 540 Chemie und zugeordnete Wissenschaften</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Chemie » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>