<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>5300</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:53</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="de">Systematische Untersuchung und Reduktion der Elektronenfeldemission von metallischen Oberflächen in Teilchenbeschleunigern</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Lagotzky, Stefan</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2018-01-22</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/physik/diss2015/lagotzky</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=5300</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20151109-105045-5</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-5116/dc1520.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="de">&lt;p&gt;Systematic field emission (FE) measurements on flat Nb, Cu and Mo surfaces relevant for typical &#13;
accelerating structures or photocathode substrates of linear accelerators are reported. The emitter &#13;
activation and the resulting emitter number density of such surfaces as function of the&#13;
applied electric activation field &lt;i&gt;E&lt;sub&gt;act&lt;/sub&gt; &lt;/i&gt;were measured with a field emission scanning microscope.&#13;
Furthermore, a statistical model for the activation of typical emitters on metallic surfaces is&#13;
developed and shows good agreement with the obtained results. Finally the FE of the emission&#13;
sites were characterized by local &lt;i&gt;I(E)&lt;/i&gt; measurements. Correlated surface analysis techniques (e.g.&#13;
scanning electron microscopy, energy dispersive X-ray spectroscopy, optical profilometry,&#13;
atomic force microscopy) were used to identify the origin of the FE.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
&#13;
Measurements on dry-ice-cleaned (DIC) single crystal Nb after electropolishing (EP) and&#13;
buffered chemical polishing (BCP) showed first FE at &lt;i&gt; E&lt;sub&gt;act&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/i&gt; ≥ 120 MV m&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; with onset fields of&#13;
&lt;i&gt;E&lt;sub&gt;on&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/i&gt; ≥ 50 MV m&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;. Conditioning of typical emitters up to 1 µA did not weaken the FE&#13;
significantly. An alternative polishing with a combination of centrifugal barrel polishing and&#13;
light BCP resulted in first FE at &lt;i&gt;E&lt;sub&gt;act&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/i&gt; = 175 MV m&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; with &lt;i&gt;E&lt;sub&gt;on&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/i&gt; ≥ 80 MV m&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;. Heat treatments (HT)&#13;
of single crystal and large grain Nb after high-pressure rinsing showed strong FE activation at&#13;
&lt;i&gt;T&lt;sub&gt;HB&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/i&gt; ≤ 400°C with &lt;i&gt;E&lt;sub&gt;on&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/i&gt; ≥ 40 MV m&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; due to the dissolution of the native Nb&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;5&lt;/sub&gt;-layer.&#13;
Accordingly, thermal oxidation of single crystal Nb in air after DIC led to a reduction of FE and&#13;
finally to an activation at &lt;i&gt;E&lt;sub&gt;act&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/i&gt; ≥ 150 MV m&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;. The implications of these results for the&#13;
superconducting accelerating structures of a future International Linear Collider are discussed.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
&#13;
FE measurements on diamond-turned and partially etched Cu surfaces relevant for the future&#13;
Compact Linear Collider accelerating structures showed FE at &lt;i&gt;E&lt;sub&gt;act&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/i&gt; ≥ 30 MV m&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; with&#13;
&lt;i&gt;E&lt;sub&gt;on&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/i&gt; ≥ 20 MV m&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; caused by particulates. Cleaning with ionized N&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; (DIC)  reduced the FE with&#13;
activation at &lt;i&gt;E&lt;sub&gt;act&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/i&gt; ≥ 130 MV m&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; (&lt;i&gt;E&lt;sub&gt;act&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/i&gt; ≥ 140 MV m&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;) and &lt;i&gt;E&lt;sub&gt;on&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &gt; 30 MV m&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; caused by surface&#13;
defects. Furthermore, a strong activation effect was observed. A possible breakdown mechanism&#13;
based on this effect is discussed.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
&#13;
Comprehensive investigations of the FE of annealed single crystal and polycrystalline Mo&#13;
plugs used as substrates for actual photocathodes revealed no FE up to &lt;i&gt;E&lt;sub&gt;act&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/i&gt; = 50 MV m&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;, but HT&#13;
at &lt;i&gt;T&lt;sub&gt;HB&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/i&gt; ≥ 400°C activated FE with &lt;i&gt;E&lt;sub&gt;on&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/i&gt; ≥ 20 MV m&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;. O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; loading into the Mo surface, however,&#13;
partially weakened these emitters. X-ray photoelectron spectroscopy of comparable Mo samples&#13;
showed the dissolution of the native oxide layer during such HT. These results reveal the&#13;
suppression of FE by native Mo oxides.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 530 Physik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Physik » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>