<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>592</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:6:60:600</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">Novel HTS microstrip resonator configurations for microwave bandpass filters</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Reppel, Michael</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2000-10-10</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fb13/diss2000/reppel</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=592</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20000418</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-688/d130002.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="de">In der vorgelegten Dissertation werden Konfigurationen aus neuartigen&#13;
Mikrostreifenleitungsresonatoren eingeführt und experimentelle&#13;
Ergebnisse von supraleitenden Bandpaß Filtern basierend auf diesem&#13;
Resonator vorgestellt. Mit Hilfe von supraleitenden Bandpaß Filtern&#13;
können Empfangssysteme (z.B. in Mobilfunkbasisstationen) wesentlich&#13;
robuster gegen Interferenzen ausgelegt werden, als mit konventioneller&#13;
Technik (Koaxialleitungsfilter).&#13;
&lt;br&gt;Der vorgestellte Resonatortyp ist durch sein zweifach symmetrisches&#13;
Layout besonders für Anwendungen geeignet, bei denen eine schwache&#13;
Kopplung zwischen räumlich benachbarten planaren Resonatoren erforderlich ist.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;Dies ist z.B. bei schmalbandigen Filtern mit hoher Selektivität (steile&#13;
Filterflanken) der Fall. Weiterhin können Filter mit einer sogenannten&#13;
quasi-elliptischen Filterantwort sehr einfach realisiert werden, da die&#13;
natürliche Phase der Transmission zweier verkoppelter Resonatoren&#13;
veränderbar ist. Bei der Verwendung von supraleitenden Materialien&#13;
können deutlich höhere Leerlaufgüten als mit konventionellen&#13;
Resonatortypen erzielt werden.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;In der Arbeit wird zunächst das Design des neuen planaren Resonatortyps&#13;
eingeführt, um dann die Verkopplung von zwei dieser Resonatoren&#13;
ausführlich zu besprechen. Im nächsten Teil wird diskutiert, inwieweit&#13;
das neue Design vorteilhaft ist, wenn supraleitende Materialien zur&#13;
Realisierung von planaren Resonatoren benutzt werden. Es wird gezeigt,&#13;
daß die erzielbare Leerlaufgüte Q_0 eines planaren Resonators von der&#13;
Geometrie abhängt und daher optimierbar ist.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;Nach einer kurzen Erläuterung der benutzten Meßmethoden werden im&#13;
folgenden Kapitel experimentelle Ergebnisse vorgestellt. Zunächst&#13;
werden die zuvor besprochenen Eigenschaften des neuen Resonatortyps&#13;
(Leerlaufgüte und Kopplungseigenschaften) experimentell verifiziert.&#13;
Danach werden Meßergebnisse verschiedener hochselektiver Bandpassfilter&#13;
vorgestellt und diskutiert.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;Der letzte Teil der Arbeit beschäftigt sich mit der Abstimmung von&#13;
Filtern. Es wird zunächst gezeigt, wie aus einer realisierten&#13;
Filterstruktur verschiedene Parameter (z.B. Kopplungskoeffizienten)&#13;
meßtechnisch ermittelt werden können, so daß Abweichungen vom&#13;
Filterdesign einfacher identifiziert werden. Abschließend wird eine&#13;
Möglichkeit vorgestellt, mit Hilfe der Gruppenlaufzeit ein Filter&#13;
systematisch abzustimmen.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">This work introduces novel microstrip resonator configurations and presents&#13;
experimental results of superconducting filters developed based on this&#13;
configurations.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;The suggested resonator type, which forms the building block for filters, is&#13;
especially qualified for applications where a weak coupling is required, e.g. for&#13;
narrow–band filters with a high selectivity because of its doubly–symmetric design.&#13;
Furthermore, the natural phase of the coupling of two resonators can be altered&#13;
so that filters which depend on cross–couplings with specific phases can easily be&#13;
built. This is the case e.g. for quasi–elliptic or self–equalising filters. Using high&#13;
temperature superconductors high unloaded quality factors which exceed those of&#13;
conventional resonators can be achieved.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;The first chapter of this work gives a short introduction into the topic. In&#13;
chapter two the novel resonator design and the coupling method is explained after&#13;
a brief introduction into planar microstrip resonators. It is also shown that the new&#13;
design implies a unique tuning capability for the coupling coefficients of a filter.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;The next chapter discusses the issue of microstrip resonators fabricated from&#13;
high temperature superconducters. It is shown that due to the extremely low&#13;
conductor losses of HTS materials other loss contributions as e.g. packaging losses&#13;
can dominate the overall unloaded quality factor and that the novel microstrip&#13;
resonator is relatively immune to such losses compared to conventional resonators.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;After the measurement methods and set–ups are briefly explained in chapter&#13;
four, experimental results for the HTS resonators and filters are presented in&#13;
the next chapter. Firstly, the fabrication of the devices is illustrated, and&#13;
then measured results of the unloaded quality factor of different microstrip&#13;
resonators are presented. A validation for the unique coupling method of the&#13;
doubly–symmetric resonator is given with two–pole test filters. It is experimentally&#13;
shown that the natural phase as well as the coupling strength can easily be chosen.&#13;
Based on the novel resonator, the designs and experimental results for filters with a&#13;
high selectivity are described. Firstly, a four–pole filter design with a quasi–elliptic&#13;
response at ~ 2 GHz and a bandwidth of only 5 MHz, that is 0.25 % fractional&#13;
bandwidth, is presented. Then, designs and results of two quasi–elliptic nine–pole&#13;
filters at ~ 1715 MHz (~1775 MHz) with 10.5 MHz (15 MHz) bandwidth are shown.&#13;
Finally, measurement results of an alternative filter based on meander–line&#13;
resonators are presented. All the developed and measured filters had steep filter&#13;
skirts and low insertion loss. Results of intermodulation measurements obtained&#13;
with the latter filter are presented at the end of this chapter.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;The last chapter deals with filter tuning issues. It describes how filter&#13;
parameters (centre frequencies of the resonators, coupling coefficients and external&#13;
quality factor) can be experimentally determined. It further suggests a step by&#13;
step tuning method if the measured filter response differs significantly from the&#13;
theoretical design.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>600 Technik, Medizin, angewandte Wissenschaften » 600 Technik » 600 Technik, Technologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Elektrotechnik, Informationstechnik und Medientechnik » Elektrotechnik » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>