<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>6040</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:53</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">Properties of convective gravity waves derived by combining global modeling and satellite observations</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Trinh, Quang Thai</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2018-01-22</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/physik/diss2016/trinh</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=6040</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20160726-104957-2</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-5824/dc1615.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Gravity waves play the key role in the dynamics of the middle atmosphere.&#13;
Among different gravity wave sources, convection has been long accepted as one&#13;
of the most prominent ones. However, due to the broad spectrum of convective&#13;
gravity waves and limitations of current observation techniques, the contribution&#13;
of these waves to atmospheric dynamics is still an open issue. Moreover, due&#13;
to the same reasons, the horizontal and temporal scales of gravity waves forced&#13;
by convection are not well known. These scales are usually treated in current&#13;
convective gravity wave parameterizations as free parameters and they are defined&#13;
by assuming typical scales of convective systems. In this study, we addressed&#13;
these issues using a unique approach of combining modeling and measurements.&#13;
In order to determine the scales of convective gravity waves, instead of assuming&#13;
typical scales of convective systems, a systematic survey varying the spatial and&#13;
temporal scales as free parameters of the Yonsei convective gravity wave source&#13;
(CGWS) scheme is performed. Gravity waves are generated using this CGWS&#13;
scheme and propagated upward using the Gravity wave Regional Or Global RAy&#13;
Tracer (GROGRAT). Gravity wave momentum flux spectra in terms of horizontal&#13;
and vertical wave numbers are calculated from simulations and compared with&#13;
the respective spectrum observed by the High Resolution Dynamics Limb Sounder&#13;
(HIRDLS). Based on this comparison, combinations of scale sets which reproduce&#13;
the observed gravity wave spectrum are selected.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;HIRDLS can only see a limited portion of the gravity wave spectrum due to&#13;
visibility effects and observation geometry. To allow for a meaningful comparison&#13;
of simulated gravity waves to observations a comprehensive filter that mimics the&#13;
instrument limitations is applied to the simulated waves. This comprehensive&#13;
observational filter takes into account both instrument visibility due to radiative&#13;
transfer and retrieval as well as the complex observation geometry.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;In order to analyze the contribution of convective gravity waves to the atmospheric&#13;
dynamics, the zonal momentum balance is considered in vertical cross&#13;
sections of gravity wave momentum flux (GWMF) and gravity wave drag (GWD),&#13;
and consistency between model results and HIRDLS observations is found. Global&#13;
maps of the horizontal distribution of GWMF are considered and good agreement&#13;
in the structure as well as the magnitude between simulated results and HIRDLS&#13;
observations is found. In particular, main convection hot spots are well reproduced.&#13;
In addition, the latitude dependence of the zonal phase speed spectrum&#13;
of GWMF and its change with altitude is shown. The latitude dependences for&#13;
different climate conditions and different altitudes show a main peak in the tropics&#13;
and summer subtropics associated with eastward phase speeds between several&#13;
m/s and about 30 m/s.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;The current study is unique in two aspects: the complexity and comprehensiveness&#13;
of the observational filter and the fact that the model spectral distribution&#13;
is determined merely from observed spectral distributions. In advance to previous&#13;
studies, the spatial distribution is used only afterwards for validation. Due to the&#13;
limitation of HIRDLS instrument, only long horizontal wavelength waves are addressed&#13;
in the current approach. However, the momentum flux of these waves are&#13;
found to be significant and relevant for the driving of the Quasi-Biennial Oscillation&#13;
(QBO). Findings of the current study therefore provide the key information&#13;
for estimating relative contributions of different convective gravity wave scales to&#13;
the whole convective gravity wave spectrum.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 530 Physik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Physik » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>