<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>6060</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:6</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">The Reaction of People on Low Frequency Noise and the Correlation with Measurement</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>He, Mu</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2018-01-22</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbe/elektrotechnik/diss2016/he</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=6060</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20160728-084415-2</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-5845/de1607.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;p&gt;This thesis deals with the perception and reaction of people on low frequency noise (LFN) and&#13;
the correlation with the objective and subjective measurements. LFN is a common noise type in the &#13;
normal life, it has been studied a lot and researchers found physiological and psychological &#13;
effects on people. There are many national standards and methods to measure and evaluate LFN, but &#13;
the LFN complainants and problems are still increasing and many aspects about LFN are still not &#13;
clear.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#13;
Firstly, the indirect method is introduced and proves the feasibility of using additional &#13;
components to reduce the annoyance caused by LFN. A pilot  EEG test indicates that EEG is a useful &#13;
tool to observe the brain reaction to LFN. After that several subjective listening tests are made &#13;
for LFN sufferers and subjects with different personality traits, such as noise sensitivity, mental &#13;
performance, and stress situation and so on, to find out whether they have different perceptions &#13;
and reactions on LFN related signals. And EEG is recorded during these listening tests to observe &#13;
the corresponding brain  reactions . The  analysis results  show that pink noise (PN) is a suitable &#13;
component to combine with LFN to reduce the annoyance for subjects with high general noise &#13;
sensitivity. Adding extra PN is found as a loudness decreasing effect for LFN sufferers and &#13;
subjects with relative high stress levels.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#13;
The calculation of the listening test results and EEG data reveal the relations between subjective &#13;
annoyance value (SAV) and the power change of EEG bands in different brain function areas. When &#13;
there is only LFN related auditory stimulus, SAV shows a positive correlation with the relative &#13;
power spectral density (RPSD) of Theta band at the brain function area of dealing with auditory &#13;
stimuli, and a negative relation with RPSD of Beta band at the area for emotional content and &#13;
auditory imagery. There are signals comprised of both visual information and auditory stimuli in &#13;
the wind turbines test, besides the above relationships, a positive correlation between SAV and &#13;
RPSD of Thetal band at the position related to the function of processing emotional stimuli is also &#13;
found.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#13;
The other part of this thesis is to use psychoacoustic parameters as the variables to simulate and &#13;
predict the subjective feelings caused by LFN related signals. The linear regression and curve &#13;
estimation calculation in SPSS shows that the evaluated loudness caused by LFN related signals can &#13;
be predicted well with the psychoacoustic Loudness in linear or quadratic form. And the predicting &#13;
results for SAV are various and depend on the type of the LFN signals. Psychoacoustic annoyance and &#13;
the maximum value of the Fluctuation Strength are found more suitable to predict the annoyance &#13;
reaction. Different personality traits show certain degrees of effects on the form and variable of &#13;
the prediction. There is no significant result found for LFN sufferers in my tests, however, &#13;
experiment with larger amount of this special subject group should be investigated in the future.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>600 Technik, Medizin, angewandte Wissenschaften</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Elektrotechnik, Informationstechnik und Medientechnik » Elektrotechnik » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>