<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>6220</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:6:62:624</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">A study on buoyancy-driven flows: Using particle image velocimetry for validating the Fire Dynamics Simulator</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Meunders, Andreas</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2018-01-22</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbd/bauingenieurwesen/diss2016/meunders</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=6220</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20161005-143323-8</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-6007/dd1603.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;p&gt;The aim of this thesis is to design and carry out bench-scale laboratory experiments&#13;
specifically designed for the validation of fire models, and to use&#13;
the experimental data for a validation study of the Fire Dynamics Simulator&#13;
(FDS). The focus of the experiments is on one of the key components of&#13;
fire models, the modeling of buoyancy-driven flows. The experimental setup&#13;
is simplified by neglecting pyrolysis and combustion and its objective is to&#13;
achieve high precision and reproducibility. Therefore, an electrically heated&#13;
block of copper is used as a heat source and particle image velocimetry (PIV)&#13;
is applied for measuring the flow velocities. Two different setups are investigated:&#13;
an undisturbed open buoyant plume above the heat source, and a&#13;
buoyant spill plume emerging from a compartment opening.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;     Depending on the setup, different characteristic values of the flow are&#13;
evaluated. For the undisturbed buoyant plume setup, maximum velocities&#13;
in the plume, plume widths and flow integrals are determined. Furthermore,&#13;
a centerline analysis is carried out in order to localize the transition from&#13;
laminar to turbulent flow as a function of the Grashof number. The obtained&#13;
values lie in the range 4 x 10&lt;sup&gt;8&lt;/sup&gt; &lt; &lt;i&gt;Gr&lt;/i&gt; &lt; 2 x 10&lt;sup&gt;9&lt;/sup&gt; and therefore agree well with&#13;
previous studies. For the buoyant spill plume compartment setup, position&#13;
and maximum velocity of the outflow as well as volume flows in front of the&#13;
opening are compared. The heat flows out of the opening cannot be measured&#13;
directly and are therefore estimated based on the available data.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;     The validation study with FDS leads to mixed results. For the open plume&#13;
setup, generally a good agreement is achieved. Provided that a sufficiently&#13;
fine resolution is used, the important flow characteristics are reproduced in&#13;
the simulations. With the spill plume setup, significant differences between&#13;
experiments and simulations are observed. In order to analyze them in detail,&#13;
modifications of the experiments are required. Therefore, in conclusion of&#13;
the study, areas of potential improvements for future experiments and the&#13;
suitability of PIV for this kind of experiment are discussed.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="de">&lt;p&gt;Das Ziel der Arbeit besteht in der Planung und Durchführung von Experimenten&#13;
im Labormaßstab zur Validierung von Brandsimulationsprogrammen.&#13;
Die erhobenen Daten werden anschließend für die Validierung des Fire&#13;
Dynamics Simulator (FDS) genutzt. Der Fokus der Experimente liegt auf&#13;
auftriebsgetriebenen Strömungen, einem zentralen Element für Brandsimulationen.&#13;
Durch den Ausschluss von Pyrolyse und Verbrennung werden&#13;
die Experimente vereinfacht und eine höhere Genauigkeit und Wiederholbarkeit&#13;
erreicht. Zu diesem Zweck wird ein elektrisch beheizter Kupferblock&#13;
als Wärmequelle eingesetzt und die Strömungsgeschwindigkeiten mittels particle&#13;
image velocimetry (PIV) gemessen. Zwei unterschiedliche Aufbauten&#13;
werden untersucht, einerseits der freie Auftriebsstrahl über der Wärmequelle,&#13;
andererseits die auftriebsgetriebene Ausströmung aus einer Raumöffnung.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;In Abhängigkeit des experimentellen Aufbaus werden unterschiedliche&#13;
Charakteristika der Strömung ausgewertet. Im freien Auftriebsstrahl werden&#13;
maximale Strömungsgeschwindigkeiten, Plumebreiten und Strömungsintegrale&#13;
ermittelt. Außerdem werden die Zentrallinien analysiert, um&#13;
den Umschlag von laminarer zu turbulenter Strömung in Abhängigkeit&#13;
der Grashof Zahl zu bestimmen. Die Ergebnisse liegen im Bereich&#13;
von 4 x 10&lt;sup&gt;8&lt;/sup&gt; &lt; &lt;i&gt;Gr&lt;/i&gt; &lt; 2 x 10&lt;sup&gt;9&lt;/sup&gt; und damit in guter Übereinstimmung mit&#13;
früheren Studien. Im zweiten Aufbau werden die Position und maximale&#13;
Geschwindigkeiten der Ausströmung sowie die Volumenströme vor der&#13;
Raumöffnung verglichen. Da die konvektiven Wärmeströme aus der Öffnung&#13;
nicht direkt gemessen werden können, werden sie auf Grundlage der vorhandenen&#13;
Daten abgeschätzt.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Der Vergleich mit FDS Simulationen zeigt nur teilweise gute Übereinstimmung.&#13;
Während Simulationen mit ausreichend feiner Auflösung die&#13;
wesentlichen Charakteristika des freien Auftriebsstrahls gut wiedergeben,&#13;
zeigen sich im zweiten Aufbau deutliche Unterschiede. Um diese eingehender&#13;
zu untersuchen, sind Veränderungen an den Experimenten erforderlich. Zum&#13;
Abschluss der Arbeit werden daher mögliche Verbesserungen diskutiert sowie&#13;
ein Fazit zur Eignung von PIV für Experimente dieser Art gezogen.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>600 Technik, Medizin, angewandte Wissenschaften » 620 Ingenieurwissenschaften » 624 Bauingenieurwesen, Ingenieurbauten</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Architektur und Bauingenieurwesen » Bauingenieurwesen » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>