<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>6351</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:8:80:800</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="de">Der Erzählsalon als Verfahren strategischen Erzählens - Konzeptionelle Voraussetzungen und empirische Gestalt am Beispiel des Projektes Lausitz an einen Tisch</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Richter, Ralph</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Rohnstock, Nepomuk</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2018-01-22</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=6351</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20161122-084807-8</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-6145/dej16050205.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;p&gt;The &lt;i&gt;Story Telling Salon&lt;/i&gt; is a method that regularly brings together groups of people who, under the leadership of a moderator – the salonnière –, exchange stories about personal experiences in a social environment (an organization, a community etc.). In this way, the &lt;i&gt;Story Telling Salon&lt;/i&gt; not only strives to generate meaningful collective narrations but also trust, collective identity and commitment in groups which suffer from social alienation. We show how the &lt;i&gt;Story Telling Salon&lt;/i&gt; applies collective storytelling as a strategic means towards community building and the empowerment of people. This will be exemplified by the example of “Lusatia at one table” (&lt;i&gt;Lausitz an einen Tisch&lt;/i&gt;) – a regional development project that aims at strengthening social cohesion and facilitating civic commitment in the disadvantaged rural region of Lusatia / Germany. The paper presents the empirical findings of a one-year observation of “Lusatia at one table”.</dc:description>
          <dc:source xml:lang="de">DIEGESIS. Interdisziplinäres E Journal für Erzählforschung / Interdisciplinary E-Journal for Narrative Research ISSN 2195-2116 https://www.diegesis.uni-wuppertal.de Heft 02 (2016) Seite 84-100 5. Jahrgang</dc:source>
          <dc:subject>800 Literatur » 800 Literatur, Rhetorik, Literaturwissenschaft » 800 Literatur und Rhetorik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Geistes- und Kulturwissenschaften » DIEGESIS » Jg. 5 (2016) H. 2</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Texte » PeriodicalPart</dc:type>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>