<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>oai:elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de:3666</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:54:540</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">Novel Organocatalysts with Pyrrolidine and Brönsted Acids for Aldol Reaction and other Reactions</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Tang, Gongkun</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2018-01-22</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/chemie/diss2012/tang</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=3666</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20120725-120018-8</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-3757/dc1211.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;p&gt;This dissertation describes the development of several novel organocatalysts. At first novel&#13;
imidazolidinone derivatives, which have a carboxylic group at the 5-position, have been&#13;
synthesized and tested. Secondly, several novel proline amide derivatives have been&#13;
synthesized and tested with aldol reactions and Mannich reactions. The best enantioselectivity&#13;
(ee over 98%) has been obtained from the reactions catalyzed by the novel&#13;
N-trifluoromethylsulfonyl-L-proline amide in both reactions. Besides this, it could generally&#13;
been concluded from the results that the acidity of the catalysts plays a very important role in&#13;
selectivity.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Based on this conclusion, several novel proline imidazole derivatives, which combine diverse&#13;
Brönsted acids, have been designed and synthesized by a novel route. In the tests, high&#13;
enantioselectivity (ee over 98%) has been obtained by several of these catalysts. In tests with&#13;
the same catalyst and different acids, it could be proved that the acidity of the catalysts mainly&#13;
determine the selectivity of reactions. A value of the pka of the added acid solution, with&#13;
which the reactions exhibit high selectivity, could be given. Several other reactions have been&#13;
tested with these catalysts.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Besides, novel peptidic organocatalysts have been designed and tested in aldol reactions.&#13;
Novel BINOL catalysts with imidazole functionalities have also been synthesized and tested.&#13;
But the results showed that the catalytic activity of the other novel catalysts is much higher&#13;
than BINOL derived phosphoric acid derivatives.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 540 Chemie » 540 Chemie und zugeordnete Wissenschaften</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Chemie » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>