<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>6660</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:54:540</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">Electrogenerated Films of Carbazole- and Thiophene-Based Microporous Polymer Networks</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Palma Cando, Alex Uriel</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2018-01-22</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/chemie/diss2016/palmacando</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=6660</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20170210-142131-6</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-6455/dc1636.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;p&gt;Electrochemical oxidative polymerization of rigid, multifunctional monomers allows for the&#13;
generation of microporous thin films with high surface areas. In this work, multifunctional&#13;
carbazole- and thiophene-based rigid monomers were utilized as tridimensional building&#13;
blocks (tectons) toward the electrogeneration of microporous polymer films. The monomer&#13;
structure plays an essential role on the properties of the resulting microporous polymer&#13;
networks. A distinct correlation is observed between the number of electroactive substituents&#13;
in the monomers and the specific surface area of the corresponding microporous polymer&#13;
films. Potential applications were explored for the chemical and electrochemical detection of&#13;
nitroaromatic compounds using optimized microporous polymer films.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="de">&lt;p&gt;Die oxidative, elektrochemische Polymerisation starrer, multifunktioneller Monomere&#13;
ermöglicht die Erzeugung dünner mikroporöser Filme mit hoher Oberfläche. In dieser Arbeit&#13;
wurden multifunktionelle, dreidimensionale Carbazol- und Thiophen-basierte rigide&#13;
Monomere (Tektone) dazu verwendet, elektrochemisch dünne mikroporöse Filme zu&#13;
generieren. Die Struktur der Monomere spielt für die Eigenschaften der dabei entstehenden&#13;
mikroporösen Polymernetzwerke eine entscheidende Rolle. Es wird ein Zusammenhang&#13;
zwischen der Anzahl der elektroaktiven Gruppen des Monomeres und der spezifischen&#13;
Oberfläche des entsprechenden Polymerfilmes beobachtet. Einige dieser mikroporösen&#13;
Polymernetzwerke wurden für Anwendungen als Sensormaterial sowohl für die chemische,&#13;
als auch die elektrochemische Detektion von Nitroaromaten untersucht.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 540 Chemie » 540 Chemie und zugeordnete Wissenschaften</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Chemie » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>