<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>6993</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:8:80:800</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="de">Die Kehrseite des Wissens</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="de">Körperarbeit am Text – und was sie für  die Narratologie bedeutet</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Söffner, Jan</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Schomacher, Esther</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2018-01-22</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=6993</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20170606-142108-1</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-6777/dej17060104.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;p&gt;When toddlers and younger children first encounter stories, they evince a strong tendency to act them out. They use role play and toys for enactment and thereby to experience the dynamics of a storyline, to pursue possible variations, to embody divergent perspectives, to learn about characters and their attitudes, and to cope with the narrated situations. In analogy with Lev Vygotsky’s (1962) basic insight that thinking is to be considered as an interiorized form of spoken language, it may accordingly be argued that the mental imagery which readers experience in following a narrative is (at least partially) to be understood as an interiorized form of playful enactment. Drawing on insights of the cognitive sciences, phenomenology and research on embodiment, this article pursues this hypothesis and takes a few first steps towards an enactivist perspective on literary narrative. In doing so, embodied knowledge – as opposed to propositional knowledge – will be the main issue.</dc:description>
          <dc:source xml:lang="de">DIEGESIS. Interdisziplinäres E Journal für Erzählforschung / Interdisciplinary E-Journal for Narrative Research ISSN 2195-2116 https://www.diegesis.uni-wuppertal.de Heft 01 (2017) Seite 58-75 6. Jahrgang</dc:source>
          <dc:subject>800 Literatur » 800 Literatur, Rhetorik, Literaturwissenschaft » 800 Literatur und Rhetorik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Geistes- und Kulturwissenschaften » DIEGESIS » Jg. 6 (2017) H. 1</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Texte » PeriodicalPart</dc:type>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>