<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>7010</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:6:60:600</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="de">Optimierung der Gebrauchstauglichkeit von CNC-Maschinensteuerständen als Beitrag zur menschengerechten Arbeitsgestaltung</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Levchuk, Inna</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2018-01-22</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbd/sicherheitstechnik/diss2017/levchuk</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=7010</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20170612-162318-4</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-6793/dd1703.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;p&gt;The technical progress of the past few decades have substantially changed the work&#13;
environment by new technologies. While computers, laptops and tablets have replaced&#13;
typewriters in the administrative area, Computerized Numerical Control (CNC) is being used&#13;
more and more on machinery tools in manufacturing industry in order to make manufacturing&#13;
more flexible, efficient and faster.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;The step-by-step implementation of CNC technology has challenged and is still challenging&#13;
employees and companies in various ways. On the one hand, elder employees, who have&#13;
always carried out physically strenuous work on conventional machines, are being&#13;
confronted more and more with knowledge-based computerized systems that are often&#13;
unfamiliar to them. On the other hand, at the time of demographic changes with the&#13;
increasing of employee's age, companies face an issue to still be competitive on the&#13;
international market. The CNC technology is in constant development. That is why ''lifelong&#13;
learning'' of workers in manufacturing area is essential for the competitiveness of companies.&#13;
This paper observes work place of machine operator and, especially, adaptation of the CNC&#13;
system to the worker. Emphasis is placed on the possibility to find an appropriate design of&#13;
information means of the CNC control unit, e.g. control elements and displays.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;Based on studies in this paper, the usability of the system “CNC machine” was tested for the&#13;
phases of first and further education with objective measurement methods and procedures.&#13;
Besides this, also the subjective aspects of the work of CNC machine tools have been&#13;
observed. To achieve this, was checked whether the operation of a CNC machine is&#13;
designed in such a way that it can be easily operated by users of any age, experience level&#13;
or experience background. Also the physical strain presented after the implementation of the&#13;
CNC technology was observed.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;In the pilot study, general information about weaknesses and possible issues of manmachine-&#13;
interface of CNC machine were detected. For this purpose, a survey was carried&#13;
out among 122 users in several training centers in the region of Bergisches Land. The survey&#13;
has been carried out by a standardized questionnaire, which has been developed for this&#13;
purpose. Based on received data, working hypotheses were derived and further examined in&#13;
three different studies, here called “loops”.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;In Loop 1, first of all the technical aspect of operating CNC machines has been observed.&#13;
Usability tests were carried out on CNC machines in training centers with 24 users. As a&#13;
result the subjective data collected in the pilot study was added by objective data from&#13;
measurements during the operation CNC machines. Tests were conducted with the help of&#13;
the so-called Eye-Tracking system that can be used to record the performance of a person&#13;
while operating a CNC machine.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;In Loop 2, about 800 job task analyses describing the system ''machine operator'' at&#13;
workplaces derived with the help of so-called “Ergonomic Risk Assessment” (BDS) were&#13;
analized. It was found out which part of working time machine operator spends for the&#13;
operating a CNC machine and which part for other activities which is usually done. Especially&#13;
body posture, load handling and work intensity were observed.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&#13;
Loop 3 was focused on the human body size. During a cross-section study made among 800&#13;
people, the current anthropometric data of a representative sample of the German resident&#13;
population was obtained and analyzed.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&#13;
The pilot study (standardized survey of users) firstly indicated age-specific differences in the&#13;
evaluation of interaction systems (CNC control interfaces) of various producers. Operating&#13;
errors were also traced to varying designs of operating elements, multiple assignments of&#13;
buttons and their unclear pressure point. The dimensions of the operating elements are often&#13;
criticized to be too small. Different aspects of the organization of the work place e.g. access&#13;
to the machining space or the position and arrangement of the operating panel are&#13;
connected with partly unfavorable body postures and complaints in the musculoskeletal&#13;
system.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;Loop 1 (field tests with the help of an eye-tracking system) provided information's about the&#13;
performance on different CNC machines. As a result, intra-individual as well as interindividual&#13;
differences in operation were found. Here, design of visual and tactile information&#13;
means on various control panels was observed. The comparison of two control panels with&#13;
shopfloor programming (version H1: Shopfloor programming using input mask and version&#13;
H3: Shopfloor programming with DIN/ISO-programming) showed a significant better&#13;
performance among users in favor of the version with input masks. However, none of the&#13;
tested control panels completely met the user requirements. Moreover, unfavorable handarm&#13;
positions and body postures were often taken during programming and operating&#13;
activities.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;The results from Loop 1 were also confirmed in the job analyses in field data collecting (Loop&#13;
2). It shows that some jobs, e.g. monitoring the machining procedure can take up to 100% of&#13;
the workday and are mostly done only in standing or partly in a forward-leaning position.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;Apart from the actual work on CNC machines, machine operators have to often carry out&#13;
extensive manual handling of loads.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&#13;
The analysis of the anthropometric data from Loop 3 showed different trends of the observed&#13;
data. In comparison to the available data from the current standards and literature,&#13;
increasing of the 95th percentile of thumb width and at the same time decreasing of the 5th&#13;
percentile of the forefinger thickness was detected.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;Based on the gained knowledge, recommendations for choosing and designing of CNC&#13;
control unit were developed for users and buyers. These provide specific instructions for&#13;
design possibilities of CNC machine and its elements in the working system. It should help to&#13;
increase the part of ergonomic and demographic work places in companies and make it&#13;
possible for employees of any age to do their work.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;All this shows the needs of further development and research to transfer results of this study&#13;
to other activities and working systems.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>600 Technik, Medizin, angewandte Wissenschaften » 600 Technik » 600 Technik, Technologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Maschinenbau und Sicherheitstechnik » Sicherheitstechnik » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>