<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>7060</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:51:510</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">High-Order Methods for Parabolic Equations in Multiple Space Dimensions for Option Pricing Problems</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Hendricks, Christian</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2018-01-22</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/mathematik/diss2016/hendricks</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=7060</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20170704-143448-0</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-6836/dc1642.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;p&gt;The pricing of derivatives plays an important role in modern financial markets. The fair value of an&#13;
option can be computed by solving the corresponding partial differential equation (PDE). In&#13;
financial engineering these PDEs are in general of convection-diffusion type and are usually multidimensional.&#13;
Apart from certain exceptions no analytical solution is available and numerical&#13;
techniques have to be applied.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;In this thesis we derive efficient numerical techniques to solve PDEs arising in computational&#13;
finance. The work is divided into five main parts. In the first section we give a brief introduction to&#13;
financial option pricing problems. Here, we formulate the PDEs to price European plain vanilla&#13;
options within the Black-Scholes framework and under stochastic volatility. Further, we briefly&#13;
discuss various numerical techniques to compute the option price.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;In the second section grid based methods to approximate the spatial differential operator are&#13;
presented. Besides standard and high order compact finite differences, we employ pseudo spectral&#13;
methods. Since grid based methods suffer from the so called 'curse of dimensionality', we employ&#13;
the sparse grid combination technique to reduce the number of grid points. The combination&#13;
technique relies on a certain anisotropic error splitting structure. This motivates our analysis of the&#13;
splitting structure of finite difference and pseudo spectral schemes. The theoretical investigation of&#13;
the properties of both approaches is followed by illustrating numerical experiments.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Afterwards we employ Alternating Direction Implicit (ADI) time stepping methods. Four prominent&#13;
schemes are considered: Douglas, Craig-Sneyd, modified Craig-Sneyd and the Hundsdorfer-Verwer&#13;
scheme. ADI schemes allow to decompose the spatial discretization matrix into one dimensional&#13;
problems, which can be solved sequentially. In the case of a high-order compact (HOC)&#13;
discretization in space we prove bounds for unconditional stability. In the case of pseudo spectral&#13;
schemes we perform a thorough numerical analysis.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;In the fourth section the numerical techniques are applied to PDEs arising in computational finance.&#13;
We compose different numerical techniques tailored to the regularity of the problem, which makes&#13;
the schemes especially efficient. In numerical experiments we compare the novel methods to&#13;
benchmark methods and additionally validate their theoretical properties.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;In the last part we summarize the results. Further, we give a concise outlook about possible future&#13;
research directions.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 510 Mathematik » 510 Mathematik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Mathematik und Informatik » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>