<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>715</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:54:540</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="de">Capsaicinoide in Capsicum-Früchten definierter Herkunft und ihre Stabilität bei Verarbeitung und Lagerung</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Hiepler, Constanze</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2004-06-08</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/chemie/diss2004/hiepler</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=715</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20040280</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-811/dc0405.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">Capsaicinoids are found only in the fruits of Capsicum plants. While their biosynthesis is largely established, accumulation and degradation are still not&#13;
completely understood. Some study groups assume hot pepper peroxidases are responsible for the degradation.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;In a two year study the capsaicinoid contents of more than 400 individual fruits, representing the whole harvest of seven plants, were investigated with regard to&#13;
dependence on fruit age and fruit position. Capsaicinoid contents in fruits of the same plant harvested at the same day differed considerably, although mean values and&#13;
range were similar in both years. Due to the wide heterogeneity no dependence of capsaicinoid levels on fruit age or node position was observed. The statistical&#13;
evaluation illustrated the problem to obtain representative values. Highly varying pungency contents of individual fruits may lead to mistakes when taking samples&#13;
which are composed of only a small number of fruits for the observation of biosynthesis, degradation curves and environmental influences. In future experiments&#13;
heterogeneity and natural fluctuation in individual fruits have to be considered during planing and evaluation.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The storage of minced and homogenised fruit material showed that enzymes take part in the reduction of capsaicinoid content. Storage parameters that are favourable&#13;
to peroxidases led to a fast loss of pungency. Intensity of degradation varied with fruit age: minced material from young fruits showed the fastest and strongest loss of&#13;
capsaicinoids, while capsaicinoids in material from old fruits were not degraded. Subsets of isozymes expressed at different times and locations, e. g. outer cuticle of&#13;
the pericarp, may contribute.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;Cellular disruption was always a pre-requisite, an enzymatic metabolism in the intact fruit was not observed.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 540 Chemie » 540 Chemie und zugeordnete Wissenschaften</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Chemie » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>