<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>7160</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:1:15</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">Neurofeedback as a psychophysiological treatment for disinhibited eating – An analysis of efficacy and mechanisms</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Schmidt, Jennifer Sabrina</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2018-01-22</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbg/psychologie/diss2016/schmidt</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=7160</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20170802-084604-2</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-6930/dg1605.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;p&gt;Disinhibited eating (DE) behaviors - such as overeating or binge eating - are common dysfunctional behaviors, especially in female populations. These behaviors can contribute to developments of overweight or obesity, and associated negative health consequences, like non-communicable diseases or eating disorders. Still, treatments for DE show moderate efficacy and may benefit from improvements. Recently, experts called for more research on brain-directed treatments to target DE and related eating disorders. Neurofeedback (NFB), using electroencephalographic (EEG) activity, is a well-established and safe neuromodulatory approach, based on an acquisition and online feedback of EEG-signals. It enables patients to regulate brain activity associated with dysfunctional psychological states or behaviors. However, EEG NFB had - to date - not been evaluated for the treatment of DE.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The present doctoral thesis reports on the development and evaluation of an EEG NFB protocol for the treatment of DE. The protocol is based on a synthesis of current theories on the etiology of DE, empirical findings regarding associated psychophysiological activity, and adaptable treatment components. It consists of ten sessions and incorporates self-regulation of tense physiological arousal, marked by EEG high beta activity, after exposure with personalized food cues.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Two randomized controlled trials and an experimental EEG study aimed at the evaluation of the general and specific treatment efficacy, as well as treatment mechanisms of the NFB. The studies were conducted in subclinical samples of female restrained eaters with DE. &lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Study 1 (initial sample: n = 34) compared a NFB group to a waitlist group and yielded evidence for the general efficacy of the NFB in reducing DE episodes. Results remained stable to a three-month follow-up. Further, the new NFB was well-accepted by the participants.&lt;/p&gt; &#13;
&lt;p&gt;In Study 2 (initial sample: n = 75), NFB and an additional intervention with a highly comparable treatment (mental imagery) were compared to a waitlist condition. NFB, but not the alternative intervention, resulted in significant post-treatment reductions of DE episodes compared to the waitlist. Results remained stable to a three-month follow-up and indicated specific efficacy of the NFB approach.&lt;/p&gt; &#13;
&lt;p&gt;Study 3 (n = 36) aimed at an evaluation of relevant treatment mechanisms in NFB. The experimental study compared the presence and influence of physiological learning (regulation of EEG high beta activity) and psychological learning (enhanced somatic self-efficacy) in the NFB and control intervention group. Analyses showed that physiological learning was only present in the NFB group and showed stronger relations to treatment outcomes than somatic self-efficacy. According to these results, physiological learning constitutes a relevant treatment mechanism in the developed NFB protocol.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;In summary, the developed NFB could be evaluated as an efficacious and physiologically-based treatment approach for the treatment of DE. It may be a beneficial adjunct for treatments of eating disorders (e.g., binge eating disorder). Based on the results of this dissertation project, replications in clinical groups are now warranted. Additional implications for research and practice are discussed.&lt;/p&gt;</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="de">&lt;p&gt;Heißhungeranfälle, als Variante enthemmten Essverhaltens, sind insbesondere unter Frauen weit verbreitet. Sie können die Entstehung von Übergewicht und assoziierten negativen Gesundheitsfolgen begünstigen. Aktuelle Behandlungen für enthemmtes Essen mit Heißhungeranfällen sind langfristig jedoch nur moderat wirksam. Zur Behandlungsoptimierung sollten Verbesserungsmöglichkeiten daher systematisch untersucht werden. Experten stellen hierbei vor allem die Erforschung neurophysiologisch basierter Behandlungsmethoden in den Fokus.&lt;/p&gt; &#13;
&lt;p&gt;Eine sichere und etablierte Variante in diesem Feld ist das Neurofeedback (NFB) basierend auf dem Elektroenzephalogramm (EEG). Im EEG-NFB wird die elektrische Hirnaktivität in Echtzeit erfasst und an Patienten zurückgemeldet. Hierdurch sollen Patienten lernen ihre Hirnaktivität bewusst zu regulieren und damit assoziierte dysfunktionale Prozesse im Erleben und Verhalten zu beeinflussen. Für die Behandlung von enthemmtem Essverhalten wurde das EEG-NFB allerdings bislang nicht evaluiert.&lt;/p&gt; &#13;
&lt;p&gt;Die vorliegende Dissertation beschreibt die Entwicklung und Evaluation eines neuen NFB-Protokolls zur Behandlung von Heißhungeranfällen. Dieses basiert auf einer Synthese einflussreicher Theorien des Essverhaltens, verhaltenstherapeutischer Behandlungselemente und empirischer psychophysiologischer Befunde. Das resultierende Protokoll besteht aus zehn Sitzungen in denen NFB zur Regulation der High-Beta-Aktivität im EEG - einem Korrelat physiologischer Erregungszustände - bei Konfrontation mit Heißhunger-auslösenden Nahrungsmittelreizen eingesetzt wird.&lt;/p&gt; &#13;
&lt;p&gt;Zwei randomisiert-kontrollierte Studien und eine experimentelle EEG-Studie dienten der Evaluation des NFB-Protokolls in Hinblick auf seine generelle und spezifische Wirksamkeit sowie zugrundeliegende Wirkmechanismen. Die Studien wurden in subklinischen Stichproben weiblicher Probanden mit gezügeltem Essverhalten und Heißhungeranfällen durchgeführt.&lt;/p&gt; &#13;
&lt;p&gt;Studie 1 (Ausgangsstichprobe: n = 34) diente dem Vergleich einer NFB-Gruppe mit einer Wartekontrollgruppe und zeigte erste Evidenz für eine generelle Wirksamkeit von NFB in der Reduktion von Heißhungeranfällen. Die NFB-Behandlung wurde von den Teilnehmerinnen gut akzeptiert und die Effekte blieben in einer Drei-Monats-Katamnese stabil.&lt;/p&gt; &#13;
&lt;p&gt;In Studie 2 (Ausgangsstichprobe: n = 75) wurden NFB und eine hochvergleichbare Alternativbehandlung (Mental Imagery) mit einer Wartekontrollgruppe vergleichen. In der NFB-Gruppe, jedoch nicht in der Alternativbehandlung, zeigte sich zum Behandlungsabschluss eine signifikante Reduktion der Heißhungeranfälle im Vergleich zur Wartekontrollgruppe. Die Ergebnisse blieben wiederum zur Drei-Monats-Katamnese stabil und weisen auf eine spezifische Wirksamkeit des NFB hin.&lt;/p&gt; &#13;
&lt;p&gt;Studie 3 (n = 36) diente der Evaluation relevanter Wirkmechanismen des NFB. In dieser experimentellen Studie wurden das Vorliegen und der Einfluss physiologischer Lerneffekte (Regulation der High-Beta-Aktivität im EEG) und psychologischer Lerneffekte (Stärkung der körperbezogenen Selbstwirksamkeit) in NFB und der alternativen Kontrollbehandlung untersucht. Die Analysen zeigen, dass physiologische Lerneffekte spezifisch in der NFB-Gruppe auftraten und hier eine stärkere Prädiktionskraft für die Behandlungseffekte vorwiesen als psychologische Lerneffekte. Entsprechend kann physiologisches Lernen als relevanter Wirkmechanismus des NFB-Protokolls angesehen werden.&lt;/p&gt; &#13;
&lt;p&gt;Zusammenfassend konnte das entwickelte NFB-Protokoll als wirksamer neurophysiologisch-fundierter Behandlungsansatz evaluiert werden. Entsprechend könnte NFB eine vielversprechende Methode in der Behandlung enthemmten Essverhaltens mit Heißhungeranfällen (z.B. bei der Binge-Eating-Störung) darstellen. Die Ergebnisse dieser Dissertation bilden eine solide Basis für zukünftige Evaluationen in klinischen Gruppen. Weitere Implikationen für Forschung und Praxis werden diskutiert.&lt;/p&gt;</dc:description>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="en">&lt;p&gt;4. Study 1: General efficacy of neurofeedback for disinhibited eating&lt;/br&gt;&#13;
Title: Neurofeedback reduces Overeating Episodes in female Restrained Eaters – A Randomized Controlled Pilot-Study&lt;/br&gt;&#13;
Authors: Jennifer Schmidt &amp; Alexandra Martin&lt;/br&gt;A version of this manuscript has been published in: Applied Psychophysiology and Biofeedback, 40(4), 283-295 (2015), doi: 10.1007/s10484-015-9297-6.&lt;/p&gt;</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="en">&lt;p&gt;5. Study 2: Specific efficacy of neurofeedback for disinhibited eating&lt;/br&gt;&#13;
Title: Neurofeedback against Binge Eating – A Randomized Controlled Trial in a female subclinical threshold sample.&lt;/br&gt;&#13;
Authors: Jennifer Schmidt &amp; Alexandra Martin&lt;/br&gt;A version of this manuscript has been published in: European Eating Disorders Review, 24(5), 406-416 (2016), doi: 10.1002/erv.2453.&lt;/p&gt;</dc:rights>
          <dc:subject>100 Philosophie und Psychologie » 150 Psychologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Human- und Sozialwissenschaften » Psychologie » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>