<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>730</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:3:33:330</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">Monetary Policy and European Unemployment</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Schettkat, Ronald</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Sun, Rongrong</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2018-01-22</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=730</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20080495</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-1521/</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;p&gt;In the long history of rising and persistent unemployment in Europe almost all institutions - employment&#13;
protection legislation, unions, wages, wage structure, unemployment insurance, etc. - have been alleged&#13;
and found guilty to have caused this tragic development at some point in time. Later, welfare state&#13;
institutions in interaction with external shocks were identified as more plausible causes for rising&#13;
equilibrium unemployment in Europe. Monetary policy has managed to be regarded as innocent. Based on&#13;
the assertion of the neutrality of money in the medium and long run, the search for causes of European&#13;
unemployment has shied away from the policy of central banks. But actually the institutional setup&#13;
regarding monetary policy is very different between the FED and the Bundesbank (ECB). We argue that&#13;
the interaction of negative external shocks and tight monetary policies may have been the major - although&#13;
probably not the only - cause of unemployment in Europe remaining at ever higher levels after each&#13;
recession. We identify the monetary policy of the Bundesbank as asymmetrical in the sense that the Bank&#13;
did not actively fight against recessions, but that it dampened recovery periods. Less constraint on growth&#13;
would have kept German unemployment at lower levels.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;JEL Classification : E23, E24, E42, E43, E52, E58&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Dateigröße: 657,9 KB</dc:description>
          <dc:source xml:lang="de">Schumpeter Discussion Papers&#13;
SDP08002&#13;
ISSN 1867-5352&#13;
Published : October 2008</dc:source>
          <dc:subject>Production</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Employment</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Unemployment</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Monetary Policy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Central Banks and Their Policies</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>300 Sozialwissenschaften » 330 Wirtschaft » 330 Wirtschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Wirtschaftswissenschaft/Schumpeter School of Business and Economics » Schumpeter Discussion Papers (SDP)</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Texte » Book</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>