<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>750</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:3:33:330</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">Financial System and Innovations-Determinants of Early Stage Venture Capital in Europe</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Schröder, Christian</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2018-01-22</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=750</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20090572</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-1529/</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">This paper highlights the role of financial development in producing innovative products and&#13;
services. After a general overview of the function of the financial structure as well as financial&#13;
development in realizing product and service innovations, this work examines a financial&#13;
intermediary which is particularly specialized to finance high-tech innovations - the venture&#13;
capitalist (VC). We employ a panel analysis to illustrate whether technical opportunities,&#13;
taxes, stock market development, relative size of the banking sector, GDP growth and laterstage&#13;
venture capital influence early stage venture capital investments. The empirical analysis&#13;
was conducted in 15 European countries and looked at the period from 1995 to 2005. The&#13;
results show that technical opportunities, size of the stock market and banking sector, interest&#13;
rate growth and the amount of later-stage venture capital have a significant positive and&#13;
corporate tax rate a negative impact on the amount of early stage risk capital. The structure of&#13;
the national financial system seems not to have a significant influence.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;JEL Classification : G23&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Dateigröße: 777,7 KB</dc:description>
          <dc:source xml:lang="de">Schumpeter Discussion Papers&#13;
SDP09004&#13;
ISSN 1867-5352&#13;
Published : March 2009</dc:source>
          <dc:subject>Early Stage Venture Capital</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Risk Capital</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Financial System</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Financing Innovations</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>300 Sozialwissenschaften » 330 Wirtschaft » 330 Wirtschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Wirtschaftswissenschaft/Schumpeter School of Business and Economics » Schumpeter Discussion Papers (SDP)</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Texte » Book</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>