<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>774</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:54:540</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="de">Untersuchungen an einem neuen spirocyclischen Glycinbaustein, abgeleitet von Menthon</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Kotthaus, Andreas F.</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2005-06-30</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/chemie/diss2005/kotthaus</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=774</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20050214</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-871/dc0506.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">In this work the use of a new spirocyclic &lt;i&gt;N&lt;/i&gt;,&lt;i&gt;N&lt;/i&gt;-acetal (&lt;i&gt;iso&lt;/i&gt;-MI) derived from&#13;
glycinamide and (-)-menthone with special regard to the synthesis of enantiomerically pure&#13;
α-amino acids was investigated.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
It was shown that &lt;i&gt;iso&lt;/i&gt;-MI is a highly valuable building block for the flexible synthesis of&#13;
several glycine anion equivalents and nitrone- and imine-derivates as cation equivalents.&#13;
Side chains were easily introduced via these building blocks and in most cases the reactions occured&#13;
under high stereocontrol from the side &lt;i&gt;anti&lt;/i&gt; to the isopropyl group of the menthyl ring.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
Due to the possibility to use different protecting groups, the release of amino acids caused no&#13;
problems. In case of the lactimether-protected system &lt;b&gt;29&lt;/b&gt;, releasing occurred under very mild&#13;
conditions. Starting from &lt;i&gt;iso&lt;/i&gt;-MI, amino acids with bulky side chains like adamantlyglycine&#13;
as well as racemisation sensitive amino acids like vinylglycine were thus synthesized with high&#13;
enantiomeric excess. &lt;p&gt;&#13;
&#13;
Furthermore a very effective chiral derivatizating reagent (DNFB-&lt;i&gt;iso&lt;/i&gt;-MI) was synthesised from&#13;
&lt;i&gt;iso&lt;/i&gt;-MI to determine the enantiopurity of amino acids by HPLC with a nonchiral reversed phase&#13;
column.&lt;p&gt;&#13;
&#13;
A further application investigated in this work is the use of &lt;i&gt;iso&lt;/i&gt;-MI and MMI as&#13;
organocatalysts. It was shown exemplarily that MMI catalyses a Diels-Alder reaction between&#13;
1,3-cyclohexadiene and acrolein with good yields and enantiomeric excess.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 540 Chemie » 540 Chemie und zugeordnete Wissenschaften</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Chemie » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>