<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>779</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:54:540</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="de">Neuartige kreuzförmige Oligomere aus Thienylen und Phenylen-Bausteinen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Bilge, Askin</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2006-09-05</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/chemie/diss2006/bilge</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=779</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20060465</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-876/dc0610.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">Thiophene- and phenylene-based π-conjugated oligomers have been widely investigated and&#13;
applied in different areas such as organic field-effect transistors (OFETs), charge- transportmaterials,&#13;
organic light emitting diodes (OLEDs), and solar cells. One of the most attractive&#13;
features of oligomeric materials for OFETs and OLEDs is their defined molecular structure&#13;
and the possibility to process them by solution-based techniques such as ink-jet printing or&#13;
spin-coating. The solubility of linear thiophene-and phenylene-based oligomers, even with&#13;
solubilizing terminal alkyl chains, is still a problem for solution-based device fabrication. The&#13;
work presented in this thesis focuses on the preparation of novel thiophene- and phenylene&#13;
based swivel-cruciform molecules as soluble oligomeric materials for OFET- and OLED&#13;
applications. The term swivel-cruciform, hereby, relates to the fact that there is some&#13;
conformational freedom within the cruciform molecule.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;In chapter 4, the synthesis of unsubstituted swivel-cruciform oligothiophene dimers of&#13;
different lengths as well as hexyl-substituted swivel-cruciform oligothiophene dimers are&#13;
described. The dimers have been fully characterized by NMR, UV/Vis and DSC analysis.&#13;
Cyclic voltammetry (CV) measurements were carried out in order to elucidate the&#13;
electrochemical properties of the hexyl-substituted swivel-cruciform oligothiophene dimers.&#13;
For OFET investigations FET devices based on the unsubstituted and hexyl-substituted&#13;
swivel-cruciform oligothiophene dimers were built up from solution by spin-coating. The&#13;
results of the OFET measurements are presented as well as AFM investigations of the film&#13;
morphology. The OFET measurements show particularly high charge carrier mobilities and&#13;
on/off ratios for the hexyl-substituted swivel-cruciform oligothiophenes.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;Chapter 5 presents synthesis and characterization (NMR, UV/Vis and DSC analysis) of&#13;
swivel-cruciform oligophenylene dimers with different substitution pattern. A single crystal&#13;
X-ray structure analysis of a naphtyl substituted swivel-curiciform oligophenylene illustrates&#13;
the cruciform structure with conformational flexibility. These materials have been used for in&#13;
OLED investigations as emitter material as presented in this chapter.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;In Chapter 6 the synthesis and characterization of another type of swivel-cruciforms, so called&#13;
oligotriphenylamine dimers, is described. For comparison, also two oligotriphenylamines with&#13;
a star-shaped structure are presented. For these oligomers, CV measurements have been once&#13;
again recorded and illustrate the potential of these cruciforms as hole-transport layers for&#13;
multilayer OLEDs.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 540 Chemie » 540 Chemie und zugeordnete Wissenschaften</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Chemie » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>