<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>787</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:54:540</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="de">Bestimmung von Alkylpolyglucosiden in komplexer Matrix mittels MEKC-PAD und GCxGC-(TOF)MS</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Hübner, Jane</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2007-06-05</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/chemie/diss2007/huebner</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=787</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20070615</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-884/dc0706.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">In the work presented here, two independent methods were developed for the analysis of&#13;
alkylpolyglucosides (APGs) in technical mixtures and in commercial products. The methods are based&#13;
on micellar electrokinetic chromatography with pulsed amperometric detection (MECC-PAD) and&#13;
two-dimensional gas chromatography with mass-spectrometric detection (GCxGC-MS). While, of the two&#13;
detection principles applied, MECC-PAD exhibits high selectivity for the analysis of the APGs,&#13;
GCxGC-(TOF)MS, because of its high separative power, makes possible the collection and&#13;
quantification not only of the APGs, but also, after appropriate sample preparation, of other&#13;
classes of tensides.&#13;
&#13;
&lt;p&gt;For carrying out the MECC-PAD analysis, a detection cell was designed, with which disturbances of&#13;
the detection signal could be eliminated. This made possible routine measurements with high&#13;
reproducibility. An important step in the separation and optimization of the method was the use of&#13;
two different electrolytes for the separation and detection. During the APG investigations two&#13;
separation buffers were used:&#13;
&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Dehydol LS 50 (2500 mg/mL); SDS (12 mM) in Na&lt;small&gt;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/small&gt;HPO&lt;small&gt;&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&#13;
(10 mM; pH 9.5)&lt;br&gt;&#13;
Na-tetradecylsulfonate (3 mM); Brij 58 (5000 mg/mL);&#13;
in Na&lt;sub&gt;&lt;small&gt;2&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;HPO&lt;small&gt;&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/small&gt; (10 mM; pH 9.5); ACN 25 %(v/v)&#13;
&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Separation buffer (1) was suitable for the determination of short-chained APGs in technical&#13;
products without sample preparation. The analysis of APG&lt;sup&gt;®&lt;/sup&gt;-220 (Cognis Deutschland&#13;
GmbH &amp; Co. KG) resulted in 16.18 ± 0.31 % n-octyl-α-D-glucopyranoside&#13;
(αC&lt;small&gt;&lt;sub&gt;8&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/small&gt;) and 8.22 ± 0.26 %&#13;
n-octyl-ß-D-glucopyranoside (ßC&lt;small&gt;&lt;sub&gt;8&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/small&gt;) and confirmed thereby quite well the&#13;
manufacturer` data (23.26 % αßC&lt;small&gt;&lt;sub&gt;8&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/small&gt;). The&#13;
detection limit of the method were to 0.070 g/L&#13;
(αC&lt;small&gt;&lt;sub&gt;8&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/small&gt;) and 0.075 g/L&#13;
(ßC&lt;small&gt;&lt;sub&gt;8&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/small&gt;). With neither separation buffers was it not possible to achieve&#13;
complete separation of all homologues and anomers. Thus the separation of anomers with the&#13;
separation buffer (1) succeeded up to αßC&lt;small&gt;&lt;sub&gt;10&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/small&gt;,&#13;
but all higher homologues were detected unseparated as a single signal. Although separation buffer&#13;
(2) permitted homologue separation up to αßC&lt;small&gt;&lt;sub&gt;12&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/small&gt;,&#13;
no separation of anomers could be observed. This separation buffer was preferred because with it&#13;
the homologue distribution in technical and commercial products could be determined.&#13;
&#13;
&lt;p&gt;With GCxGC-(TOF)MS the separation limits of the MECC-PAD could be overcome. In the case of the&#13;
APGs, the sample preparation amounted to nothing more than silylation. Thus not only the homologues&#13;
(discrimination according to alkyl chain length and number of glucose units) and anomers&#13;
(α,ß), but even the pyranosides and furanosides could be separated&#13;
completely from each other. In addition, the high peak capacity and the better detection limit of&#13;
GCxGC-(TOF)MS made possible the determination of other tenside classes like fatty alcohol&#13;
ethoxylates (FAEO) and cocamidopropylacetobetaines (CAPB) in a single run. In order to determine&#13;
the fatty alcohol sulfates (FAS) and fatty alcohol ether sulfates (FAES) at the same time, the&#13;
samples had to be hydrolyzed before the silylation. In an excellent confirmation of the&#13;
manufacturer's data, the analysis of a model shampoo (Cognis Deutschland GmbH &amp; Co. KG) resulted in&#13;
1.96 ± 0.02 % (APG), 2.5 ± 0.4 % (FAEO), 4.5 ± 0.03 % (CAPB) and 6.5 ± 1.2 % (FAES).</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 540 Chemie » 540 Chemie und zugeordnete Wissenschaften</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Chemie » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>