<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>792</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:54:540</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="de">Entwicklung eines optischen Biosensor-Assays mit Elementen aus der Resistenzforschung zum Screening auf Tetracyclin-Rückstände in Lebensmitteln</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Möller, Nadine</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2007-04-27</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/chemie/diss2007/moeller</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=792</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20070559</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-889/dc0705.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">A tetracycline specific-screening assay for residue analysis in honey and raw milk using the surface&#13;
plasmon resonance (SPR) technology is described. For this purpose the principle of the most frequent&#13;
bacterial resistance mechanism against tetracycline in gram negative bacteria was utilized as guide&#13;
for method development. The synthesis of a tetracycline efflux protein is regulated by the repressor&#13;
protein TetR, which normally bound to a short DNA sequence representing the tetracycline operator&#13;
&lt;i&gt;tet&lt;/i&gt;O. When tetracycline enters a resistant bacterial cell, it induces a conformational change&#13;
of the TetR protein and its release from the &lt;i&gt;tet&lt;/i&gt;O DNA sequence with succeeding synthesis of&#13;
the efflux protein.&#13;
&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Three different assay formats based on TetR and &lt;i&gt;tet&lt;/i&gt;O were compared. In the direct assay&#13;
TetR was immobilised on a sensor chip and tetracycline was injected over the chip surface to be&#13;
bound to the protein. The mass bound to the chip is directly correlated to signal height.&#13;
Correspondingly, this format showed a rather poor sensitivity due to the low molecular weight of&#13;
tetracycline. Therefore an alternative assay format was developed with immobilising &lt;i&gt;tet&lt;/i&gt;O&#13;
onto the sensor chip. The repressor TetR was added to the sample prior to SPR analysis. Within&#13;
absence of tetracyclines, TetR was able to couple to &lt;i&gt;tet&lt;/i&gt;O and caused an SPR signal.&#13;
Correlated to the amount of tetracyclines being present in the sample, the association of TetR and&#13;
&lt;i&gt;tet&lt;/i&gt;O was partially or fully blocked. In a third assay format, the first step was to load TetR&#13;
to the chip-bound &lt;i&gt;tet&lt;/i&gt;O. TetR was then released when injecting a tetracycline containing&#13;
solution over the chip. This format using the molecular mass protein for indirect detection of&#13;
tetracycline resulting in the highest test sensitivity and was used for further studies.&#13;
&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Several TetR variants - BD, S135L, V113A, P184Q and scTetR – were expressed as recombinant&#13;
proteins and purified over ion-exchange and gel filtration chromatography. The variants were&#13;
compared with respect to their assay sensitivity and cross reactivity for tetracycline,&#13;
oxytetracycline, chlortetracycline and doxycycline. BD and S135L showed the best sensitivity while&#13;
V113A exhibited a uniform cross reactivity for all tetracyclines. BD was chosen for the development&#13;
of the tetracycline-specific SPR assay. Since the use of tetracycline in honey production is not&#13;
approved by the European Union, residue analytical methods should be as sensitive as possible to&#13;
identify non-compliant samples. Test optimations therefore aimed at high sensitivity.&#13;
&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The analysis of tetracyclines in honey was possible after diluting the samples 1 to 10 with&#13;
buffer. No differences between raw honey and blended commercial honeys were observed. The analysis&#13;
of 20 different honey samples showed a high variation between the individual blanks leading to a&#13;
limit of detection (LOD) of 14 µg/kg tetracycline in honey, when applying the mean of blank honey&#13;
signals plus 3 times standard deviation for calculating the LOD.&#13;
&#13;
&lt;p&gt;In order to reduce the matrix effects of raw milk, the samples had to be defatted, diluted 1 to 5&#13;
with buffer and heated for a short time prior SPR analysis. Applying this sample preparation the&#13;
limit of detection could be estimated within 31 µg/kg. This was sufficient to use the assay as a&#13;
routine screening method for tetracycline residues in milk to survey the maximum residue limit  of&#13;
100 µg/kg.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 540 Chemie » 540 Chemie und zugeordnete Wissenschaften</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Chemie » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>