<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>801</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:54:540</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">Novel Polyfluorene Based Copolymers for Optoelectronic Applications</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Galbrecht, Frank</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2008-07-18</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/chemie/diss2008/galbrecht</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=801</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20080323</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-898/dc0809.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">Organic light emitting diodes (OLEDs) have gained increasing attention because of there&#13;
remarkable properties and application potential. Therefore chemists are aiming for suitable&#13;
organic materials for optoelectronic applications. Prominent materials are semiconducting&#13;
polymers e.g. polyfluorenes. A major problem hereby is the colour purity of the blueemitting&#13;
polyfluorene-type materials caused by degradation processes during device&#13;
operation. Besides the well-characterized keto defects in degraded polyfluorenes which emit&#13;
at a peak maximum of approximately 530-550 nm, we investigated an additional emission&#13;
feature localized at 485/515 nm. This particular green emission feature was attributed to&#13;
alkylidenefluorene defect structures. This proposal is supported with the synthesis of model&#13;
copolymers and their optical characterization as described in chapter 2.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;One focus of material chemists is to design materials with increase of performance in&#13;
optoelectronic devices. There has been much interest in the application of cyclometalated&#13;
complexes as emitting components in such devices. The metal complexes may allow for the&#13;
efficient utilization of both singlet and triplet excitons generated upon electronic operation.&#13;
Consequently, internal quantum efficiencies approaching 100% may be achieved. Tuning of&#13;
the emission colour by manipulating the ligand sphere of the metal atom is also a very&#13;
attractive goal. Up to the present, there are still relatively few examples of&#13;
electrophosphorescent (co)polymers as single–component OLED materials. These examples&#13;
include semiconducting polyfluorenes with side-chain or main-chain iridium complexes,&#13;
ladder poly(para-phenylene)s with electrophosphorescent palladium centers, self-assembled&#13;
Schiff base polymers and platinum-based side chain copolymers. Transition metal (Co, Ni,&#13;
Zn) Schiff base polymers have been prepared by oxidative polymerisation, transesterification&#13;
and condensation of salen-type monomers but they have not been applied in OLEDs.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;An often observed disadvantage of blend-based devices is a phase separation of polymer and&#13;
phosphorescent dye. One strategy to inhibit this phase separation is to incorporate the&#13;
electrophosphorescent dye into the polymer backbone. The approach presented in chapter 3&#13;
describes the covalent incorporation of phosphors into the backbone of a solutionprocessable&#13;
semiconducting copolymer. The synthesis of platinum(II) salen complexes and&#13;
the corresponding polyfluorene-based copolymers is reported in this chapter.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;OLEDs were subsequently fabricated and showed promising efficiencies and also&#13;
demonstrated the potential of this stratagem. Further optimization of the copolymer&#13;
structure includes modification of the ligand sphere as well as a variation of the backbone&#13;
e.g. incorporation of suitable comonomers such as benzophenone which should allow for a&#13;
more efficient and directed energy transfer between the backbone polymer and the&#13;
chromophore.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;Another remaining task is to improve the lifetime and the efficiency of these materials&#13;
during their application in OLEDs. The synthesis and characterization of new matrix&#13;
polymers for triplet emitters is presented in chapter 3.3. The incorporation of&#13;
benzophenone units into the main chain of polyfluorenes resulted in an improved lifetime&#13;
for operating OLEDs. Further investigations include the variation of the benzophenone&#13;
content and the incorporation of phosphorescent metal complexes into the main chain of&#13;
such copolymers.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 540 Chemie » 540 Chemie und zugeordnete Wissenschaften</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Chemie » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>