<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>806</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:54:540</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">Triphenylamine and Carbazole-Based Hole Transporting Materials - and their Applications in Organic Field-Effect Transistors</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Souharce, Benjamin</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2008-07-09</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/chemie/diss2008/souharce</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=806</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20080287</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-903/dc0806.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">Hole transporting materials based on π-conjugated organic compounds have already&#13;
been the focus of intense research and investigation. Nevertheless, the charge transport&#13;
mechanism occurring in such materials and its relation to the device stability in oxidizing&#13;
atmosphere remains not fully clear. It has been demonstrated many times that the stability&#13;
issue for p-type organic materials is one of the key features for their application in organic&#13;
field-effect transistors.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;In a conjoint work with the Evonik Degussa Creavis, research were lead to develop a&#13;
series of novel polymeric compounds usable as semiconducting layers of organic&#13;
field-effect transistors (OFETs) e.g. for printed radio frequency identification tags (RFID&#13;
Tags) being processed and working under ambient conditions.&#13;
In this regard, arylamine-based aromatic materials such as triphenylamine- or&#13;
carbazole-type polymers constitute ideal candidates for such applications due to their&#13;
good environmental stability and OFET properties coupled with an easy processability of&#13;
the polymeric materials.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;In chapter 2, a series of six main chain polytriphenylamines (PTPAs) with different alkyl&#13;
substituants and aromatic systems will be described. Chapter 3 deals with different N-aryl&#13;
substituted 3,6-polycarbazoles and their use as active layer in OFETs. At last, higher&#13;
condensed aromatic systems based on the phenazine unit comprising model compounds&#13;
as well as the corresponding polymers are presented in chapter 4. In each chapter, the&#13;
key reactions are depicted including history, mechanism and the application for our&#13;
approach. Additionally, a short introduction presents the state-of-the-art for the mentioned&#13;
classes of compounds.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;All the materials synthesized during this work were intensively analysed by spectroscopic&#13;
methods and most of them tested as semiconducting layer in OFET devices in order to&#13;
determine the influence of certain structural factors on the intrinsic electronic properties of&#13;
the compounds. The stability problem has been intensively addressed and discussed with&#13;
the goal to provide a better understanding of the oxidation/degradation mechanism taking&#13;
place in OFET devices while operating.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 540 Chemie » 540 Chemie und zugeordnete Wissenschaften</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Chemie » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>