<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>809</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:54:540</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="de">Konjugierte Donor/Akzeptor-Copolymere für Elektronikanwendungen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Tsami, Argiri</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2008-08-14</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/chemie/diss2008/tsami</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=809</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20080394</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-906/dc0812.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="de">Donor/Acceptor-Copolymers as so-called "low-bandgap" &lt;i&gt;π&lt;/i&gt;-conjugated polymers have been&#13;
widely investigated and applied in different areas such as organic photovoltaics (OPVs),&#13;
organic light emitting diodes (OLEDs) and organic field effect transistors (OFETs). Due to&#13;
the attractive features of those functional organic polymer materials such as light weight,&#13;
flexibility and produced in a cheap way they have attracted recent interest in research&#13;
development. Especially so-called "bulk heterojunction"-type solar cells consisting of blends&#13;
of conjugated donor polymers and "small" acceptor molecules have gained enormous&#13;
attention to their potential for solar ernergy energy conversion.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;In chapter 2, the synthesis of two series of random polyfluorene-type copolymers with on-chain&#13;
benzo[g]quinoxaline or quinoxaline acceptor units are described. The copolymers have&#13;
been characterized by gel permeation chromatography (GPC), nuclear magnetic resonance&#13;
spectroscopy (NMR), absorption and emission spectroscopy. Thermal properties were&#13;
analyzed by differential scanning calorimetry (DSC). For first OLED investigations single&#13;
layer devices based on the random copolymers as emissive layer were built. Additionally, by&#13;
adding a thin semiconducting polymer interlayer [poly(9,9-di-&lt;i&gt;n&lt;/i&gt;-octylfluorene-2,7-diyl)-&lt;i&gt;alt&lt;/i&gt;-&#13;
[1,4-phenylene-(4-&lt;i&gt;sec&lt;/i&gt;-butylphenylimino)-1,4-phenylene] (TFB)] between the hole&#13;
transporting (PEDOT:PSS) and the emissive random copolymer layer OLED devices with&#13;
improved performance have been reported. Using a thin TFB interlayer an enhancement of&#13;
the luminance efficiency of 172 % was observed. The OLED experiments are presented&#13;
together with atomic force microscopy (AFM) investigations of the film morphology.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;Chapter 3 presents the synthesis and characterization (NMR, GPC, UV/Vis and&#13;
photoluminescence spectroscopy) of a series of alternating fluorene/dithienyquinoxaline&#13;
copolymers with a different substitution pattern at the quinoxaline acceptor unit. The thin film&#13;
properties of the novel materials were investigated by using atomic force microscopy. Single&#13;
layer polymer light emitting diodes have been prepared by blending 3 wt.-% of the novel&#13;
alternating copolymers with poly(9,9'-di-&lt;i&gt;n&lt;/i&gt;-octylfluorene-&lt;i&gt;co&lt;/i&gt;-benzothiadiazole) (F8BT). This&#13;
blend composition provides optimimum device efficiency.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;Chapter 4 introduces the synthesis and characterization of novel alternating&#13;
quinoxaline/oligothiophene donor-acceptor copolymers. The optical and electronic properties&#13;
of theses materials showed an unexpected independence of absorption and&#13;
photoluminescence, as well as of the HOMO/LUMO energy levels, on the length of the&#13;
oligothiophene segments in the copolymer main chain. The electrochemical properties of the&#13;
quinoxaline/oligothiophene copolymers were investigated by cyclic voltammetry (CV). For&#13;
OFET investigations devices based on these copolymers were built up by solution processing&#13;
(spin-coating). The charge caries mobilities and on/off ratios of thin layers of the&#13;
quinoxaline/oligothiophene copolymers are increasing slightly with increasing number of&#13;
thiophene rings of the oligothiophene segments. In this chapter also, first OPV investigations&#13;
were carried out with the quinoxaline/oligothiophene copolymers. The power conversion&#13;
efficiencies of the resulting "bulk heterojunction"-type solar cells are reported.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;In chapter 5, the synthesis and characterization of further donor-acceptor copolymers based on&#13;
bisthiazole and thiophene units are described. The solubility of the bisthiazole/thiophene&#13;
copolymers was very low and, therefore, a solution-based device fabrication was problematic.&#13;
The bisthiazole/thiophene copolymers have been used as hole transporting material in first&#13;
OFET investigations.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;In the last chapter, the synthesis and characterization of novel cyclopentadithiophene (CPDT)-&#13;
based alternating copolymers is described. For a successful application in "bulk&#13;
heterojunction"-type solar cells CPDT-based copolymers with a mean average molecular&#13;
weight &gt; 10.000 g/mol seems necessary. The novel high molecular weight copolymers&#13;
showed rather promising power conversion efficiencies of &gt; 2 % in first device experiments.&#13;
The morphology of blends of the novel donor materials with fullerene acceptors were&#13;
investigated by AFM. For these copolymers, also OFET measurements have been carried out&#13;
since in addition to the blend morphology the charge carrier mobility within the donor phase&#13;
plays an important role for the performance of OPV devices.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 540 Chemie » 540 Chemie und zugeordnete Wissenschaften</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Chemie » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>