<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>811</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:54:540</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="de">Beitrag zur Biosensoranalytik von Tetracyclinrückständen in Lebensmitteln mittels Oberflächenplasmonresonanz</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Andree, Ulrike</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2009-06-16</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/chemie/diss2009/andree</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=811</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20090680</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-908/dc0902.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">In this work a major goal was to set up an indirect competitive assay format for the detection of&#13;
tetracyclines in food matrices using surface plasmon resonance technology. As a receptor for&#13;
tetracyclines TetR, a repressor protein binding tetracyclines in tetracycline-resistant bacteria,&#13;
was used. Doxycycline derivatives, attached to the sensor surface, were used as competitors. It was&#13;
shown that an indirect competitive assay format using TetR and doxycycline derivatives was possible&#13;
(proof of principle). The assay format was characterized to identify the most important parameters&#13;
for the optimization. After comparison of four different sensor chip surfaces (differing in surface&#13;
chemistry and layer thickness) a carboxymethyldextrane surface was found most suitable in terms of&#13;
minimal non-specific binding and good regeneration characteristics. Parameters that influenced the&#13;
immobilization of the doxycycline derivatives, binding of the receptor protein and regeneration of&#13;
the sensor surface were studied. Not only was the sensor surface shown to have crucial influence on&#13;
the assay characteristics, but also the spacer length at the doxycycline derivative imparted the&#13;
immobilization of the derivative and the subsequent binding of the receptor protein. A longer&#13;
spacer led to a higher immobilization degree; on the other hand this was counteracted by the&#13;
reduction of binding activity in the ligand-receptor system. This was proven for derivatives in&#13;
solution and can also be seen on the carboxymethyldextrane surface. However, when immobilized on a&#13;
monolayer sensor chip the doxycycline derivative with the longest spacer did not display lower&#13;
receptor binding. The non-competitive format had to cope with a poor stability of the system&#13;
accompanied by low precision and poor reproducibility. These rendered a sensitive analytics&#13;
impossible. &lt;br&gt;&#13;
Parallel to the studies with the competitive assay format, a tetracycline specific&#13;
screening assay described by Möller et al. [1] was validated. In this assay a gene regulation&#13;
mechanism occrring in tetracycline-resistant gram-negative bacteria is mimicked: In the resistant&#13;
bacterial cell the synthesis of a tetracycline efflux protein is controlled by a repressor protein&#13;
(TetR) that in absence of tetracycline binds to a short DNA sequence, the tetracycline operator&#13;
(&lt;i&gt;tet&lt;/i&gt;O) and thus blocks the expression of the efflux protein. Tetracyclines present bind to the&#13;
repressor protein and release it from the DNA. This mechanism was used for SPR measurements in honey.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
Another goal in this work was the evaluation of the robustness of the screening assay in terms of&#13;
reagent stability towards different storage conditions, different reagent lots and the application&#13;
of the assay in different laboratories. Suitable storage conditions for the sensor chips were found.&#13;
The repressor protein was very stable under all conditions tested, so were the sensor chips&#13;
pre-immobilized with the operator DNA sequence. No difference between different lots of TetR was&#13;
observed. Differing immobilization levels in loading sensor chips with the &lt;i&gt;tet&lt;/i&gt;O fragment relating to&#13;
different batches &lt;i&gt;tet&lt;/i&gt;O and sensor chips used could easily be levelled through variation of the&#13;
injection volumen of the fragment. The results obtained in the application of the screening assay to&#13;
honey samples in a laboratory in Japan were in good compliance with the results obtained in our&#13;
laboratory. Since the use of tetracyclines in honey production is not approved by the European Union&#13;
a screening test for the use in the EU should be able to detect tetracycline concentrations below&#13;
10 µg/kg. Thus, efforts were made to lower the limit of detection (LOD) for tetracyclines in honey.&#13;
Working parameters for the assay like injection time, injection volume and sample dilution were&#13;
optimized, but did not lead to a lower LOD altogether. Since interfering matrix compounds seemed&#13;
critical for the LOD, different approaches were made to find a sample preparation suitable to&#13;
eliminate matrix interferences. The approaches included extraction procedures as well as&#13;
deproteination, degradation of sugars and extraction of trace lipids. However, the complex&#13;
composition of honey and the differences in composition of honeys from different geographical and&#13;
floral origin in combination with the need for physiological conditions in the screening assay were&#13;
challenges that were not overcome by the techniques employed. &lt;br&gt;&#13;
Comparing both assay formats investigated it was pointed out that the application of the competitive&#13;
format had no advantage over the indirect assay with &lt;i&gt;tet&lt;/i&gt;O.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 540 Chemie » 540 Chemie und zugeordnete Wissenschaften</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Chemie » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>