<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>oai:elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de:3885</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:53:530</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">A systematic investigation of carbon, metallic and semiconductor nanostructures for field-emission cathode applications</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Serbun, Pavel</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2018-01-22</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/physik/diss2014/serbun</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=3885</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20140311-145531-0</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-3995/dc1402.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;p&gt;     In this work, various carbon, metallic and semiconductor nanostructures were fabricated within collaborations and systematically investigated for potential field emission (FE) cathode applications.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;     Various carbon-based cathodes were obtained by different chemical vapour deposition methods. Single-walled carbon nanotube (CNT) networks grown on n-Si substrates at ~150°C showed well-homogeneous FE with ~10&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt; emitting sites/cm&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; at low onset field E&lt;sub&gt;on&lt;/sub&gt; (1nA) ~2.5 V/μm. During the local measurements ∅ 150 μm sites yielded stable currents up to 0.2 mA. Integral measurements of the whole cathodes revealed fairly homogeneous FE resulting in at least 10 mA/cm&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;. Arrays of entangled CNT bundles of ~2 μm height, 2-3 μm patch and 100, 10 and 5 μm pitch were grown on n-Si wafers with trimetallic Mo/Al/Ni layers. Highly efficient and well-aligned FE at Eon (1nA) ~15 V/μm was obtained from CNT arrays with a pitch of 100 μm, however, the highest current up to 0.5 mA at 400 V was achieved from a spot of 150 μm for cathodes with a pitch of 5 μm. Integral measurements of the whole cathodes showed fairly homogeneous FE at currents up to 4.4 A/cm&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;. CNT columns of ∅=250 μm and different height (h = 70 or 350 μm) forming quadratic arrays with a pitch of 650 μm showed fairly aligned and efficient FE at comparatively low E&lt;sub&gt;on&lt;/sub&gt; (1nA) ~2 V/μm. Maximum current values up to 600 μA at 15 V/μm were achieved independently of the column height. The FE triode tests of single CNT columns yielded anode-cathode current ratio up to 97 % at a gate (anode) voltage of 247 (2500) V. Structuring of carbon nanowall (CNW) films was successfully performed with a laser for the optimization of their FE properties. Such cathodes exhibited fairly aligned and efficient FE at E&lt;sub&gt;on&lt;/sub&gt; (1nA) = 10-20 V/μm. Local FE measurements of selected CNW patches revealed maximum current values up to ~100 μA.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;     Mechanically stable and randomly distributed copper nanocones (Cu-NCs) were fabricated by ion-track template method. Depending on the process parameters, Cu-NCs of ~28 μm length, ~3 μm base, with different ~60-300 nm tip radius and number density were fabricated. The cathode with high number density of Cu-NCs (10&lt;sup&gt;7&lt;/sup&gt; cm&lt;sup&gt;-2&lt;/sup&gt;) yielded stable currents up to 280 μA at 100 V/μm from an emission spot of 30 μm. In contrast, the cathodes with a triangular patch array (∅ 150 μm, 320 μm pitch) of less Cu-NCs (10&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt; cm&lt;sup&gt;-2&lt;/sup&gt;) provided fairly homogeneous and well-aligned FE of all Cu-NC patches at much reduced E&lt;sub&gt;on&lt;/sub&gt; (1nA) &lt;10 V/μm and demonstrated an average current of 30 μA/patch at 32 V/μm. The FE performance of the Cu-NC cathode was improved by a thin Au coating resulting in an average current of 151 μA at 50 V/μm. Integral FE measurements on the whole Cu-NC cathode showed fairly homogeneous FE at 8 A/cm&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;     Silicon technology is the most suitable for fabrication of highly-uniform arrays of bare p- and n-type Si tips. Rather homogeneous and well-aligned FE from all tips and stable currents up to ~0.1 (0.6) μA for p-(n-) type tips were achieved. In comparison, Au-coated n-type Si tips showed improved FE uniformity and at least 5 times higher current values (i.e. ~3 μA/tip), at ~30% higher extraction field though. P-Si tips showed a current saturation region of about 10 nA. In this region, emitters provide the highest current stability (&lt;5%) and an optical current switching ratio of ~2.5.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;     Potential applications of the described above materials are discussed.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 530 Physik » 530 Physik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Physik » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>