<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>8510</id><datestamp>2018-07-19</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:3:33:330</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">Early Detection of Students at Risk - Predicting Student Dropouts Using Administrative Student Data and Machine Learning Methods</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Berens, Johannes</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Oster, Simon</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Schneider, Kerstin</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Burghoff, Julian</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2018-07-19</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=8510</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20180719-085420-5</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;p&gt;To successfully reduce student attrition, it is imperative to understand which students are at risk of dropping&#13;
out. We develop an early detection system (EDS) to predict student success in tertiary education as a basis&#13;
for a targeted intervention. The EDS uses regression analysis, neural networks, decision trees and the&#13;
AdaBoost algorithm to identify student characteristics which distinguish potential dropouts from graduates.&#13;
The developed method can be implemented in every German university, as it uses student performance and&#13;
demographic data collected and maintained by legal mandate. Therefore the EDS self-adjusts to the university&#13;
where it is employed. The EDS is tested and applied on a state university and a private university of applied&#13;
sciences. Both institutes of higher education differ considerably in their organization, tuition fees and studentteacher&#13;
ratios. Our results indicate a prediction accuracy at the end of the first semester of 79% for the state&#13;
university and 85% for the private university of applied sciences. After the fourth semester, the accuracy&#13;
improves to 90% for the state university and 95% for the private university of applied sciences.&#13;
&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Dateigröße: 1,52 MB</dc:description>
          <dc:source xml:lang="de">Schumpeter Discussion Papers&lt;br&gt;&#13;
SDP18006&lt;br&gt;&#13;
ISSN 1867-5352&lt;br&gt;&#13;
Published : July 2018</dc:source>
          <dc:subject>300 Sozialwissenschaften » 330 Wirtschaft » 330 Wirtschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Wirtschaftswissenschaft/Schumpeter School of Business and Economics » Schumpeter Discussion Papers (SDP)</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Texte » Book</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>