<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>8610</id><datestamp>2018-09-17</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:54:540</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">Design of drugs for the inhibition of the cancer related proteins MIA, Rheb and K-Ras</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Müller, Jasmin</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2018-09-17</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/chemie/diss2018/mueller</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=8610</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20180806-114148-2</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-8112/dc1810.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;p&gt;Cancer is one of the leading causes of morbidity and mortality worldwide. The three cancerrelated&#13;
proteins Rheb, &lt;i&gt;K&lt;/i&gt;-Ras and MIA were chosen as targets. In the course of this thesis, the&#13;
structure-activity-relationship of molecules, which bind to these proteins, were examined. During&#13;
preliminary studies, four molecules were identified as good binders. The structure-activityrelationship&#13;
of the compounds was thoroughly investigated. Molecular modelling was used as a&#13;
tool to identify promising compounds. Complexes of the compounds and the corresponding&#13;
proteins were computed using Autodock/Vina and/or Glide. Selected molecules were then&#13;
synthesized and tested for their interaction with the protein by heteronuclear NMR measurements.&#13;
The observed shifts were used for HADDOCK calculations to predict the binding conformation&#13;
of the compound and the corresponding protein.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
For Rheb, a molecule incorporating an additional hydroxy group in comparison to 4,4’-biphenol&#13;
was found to exhibit a binding constant that is approximately six times stronger. Surprisingly,&#13;
reducing the number of hydroxy groups has the same effect on the binding affinity. All in all, the&#13;
Rheb protein tolerates only small additional substituents on the biphenol core structure.&#13;
In case of &lt;i&gt;K&lt;/i&gt;-Ras, alterations of the bisphenol A core mostly led to inactive compounds. These&#13;
will be interesting for other purposes than cancer treatment depending on the functional groups&#13;
of the molecules. Similar to Rheb, the &lt;i&gt;K&lt;/i&gt;-Ras protein does not tolerate introduction of large&#13;
substituents into the bisphenol A core structure.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
For the MIA protein, two molecules were identified from a screening of the ZINC database. The&#13;
structure-activity-relationship of one of these compounds regarding its substituents was&#13;
examined. In the following step, hybrid compounds derived from the two fragments were&#13;
synthesized. Precursor molecules showed no activity towards the protein. Consequently, a&#13;
comprehensive screening of the ZINC database was performed. A compound, which inflicts&#13;
significant shifts of all protein peaks in the 2D-NMR spectrum, was found.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 540 Chemie » 540 Chemie und zugeordnete Wissenschaften</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Chemie » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>