<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>883</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:53:530</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">Studies on the Optical Readout for the ATLAS Pixel Detector</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">Systematical Studies on the Functions of the Back of Crate Card and the Timing of the Pixel Detector</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Flick, Tobias</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2006-12-18</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/physik/diss2006/flick</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=883</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20060600</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-989/dc0615.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="de">Am europäischen Kernforschungszentrum CERN in Genf wird derzeit der Large Hadron Collider gebaut.&#13;
An diesem Beschleuniger werden vier Experimente aufgebaut. Das größte wird das ATLAS Experiment&#13;
sein.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
Der innerste Subdetektor des ATLAS Experimentes ist ein Silizium Pixel Detektor.&#13;
Dieser Detektorteil wird über 80000000 Kanäle aufweisen, die mittels einer optischen&#13;
Datenübertragungsstrecke kontrolliert und ausgelesen werden.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
Am detektorseitigen Ende dieser optischen Übertragungsstrecke wird ein Optoboard plaziert sein, das&#13;
andere Ende im Kontrollraum bildet die Back of Crate Karte. Auf dieser Back of Crate Karte findet&#13;
außer der opto-elektrischen Wandlung auch die komplette Justage des Zeitverhaltens des Pixel&#13;
Detektors und seiner Auslese statt.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
In dieser Arbeit wird die Funktionalität der Back of Crate Karte in verschiedenen Testszenarien wie&#13;
Produktionstests, Systemtests und Teststrahlaufbauten untersucht. Neben der Qualitätssicherung&#13;
während der Produktion und dem Test der Funktion der Karte wurde entsprechende Steuersoftware&#13;
entwickelt und getestet.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
In einem Teststrahlaufbau wurde die Back of Crate Karte mit dem Datennahmesystem integriert und&#13;
unter ähnlichen Bedigungen wie später im ATLAS Experiment die Kontrolle des Zeitverhaltens und deren&#13;
Auswirkung auf die Datennahme studiert.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">The particle physics is concentrating on the research of the structure of the matter which is&#13;
observable in our world. How is this world built. Which particles exist, which are necessary to&#13;
build up the world? How is this matter kept together, what are the interactions between the known&#13;
particles?&#13;
&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The answers to these questions are obtained by observing the known particles, to study their&#13;
properties, and to search new for particles. Models are developed to describe all the observations.&#13;
Experiments are performed to proove the models. The best prooven model to describe many of the&#13;
observations is the Standard Model. The Standard Model is elucidated in Chapter 1. It is tested very&#13;
precisely by experimental measurements in the last years, but cannot explain all phenomena of&#13;
nature. To discover the last not observed particle of the Standard Model, the Higgs boson, and to&#13;
extend the model further experiments are needed.&#13;
&#13;
&lt;p&gt;To study the elementary particles machines and instruments are necessary to produce and measure&#13;
the particles and their properties.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
In the last 50 years an enormous effort has been made to develop new machines to produce particles&#13;
at always higher rates and energies. The more massive the particles are the more energy is needed to&#13;
produce them. To increase the machine energy drives the physicists and engineers to develop new&#13;
machines and experimental instruments.&#13;
&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The newest machine will be the Large Hadron Collider which is under construction at CERN in&#13;
Geneva and will start operation in 2007. This machine accelerates protons in a ring to an energy of&#13;
7TeV in opposite directions. These protons will collide at four interaction points. Here experiments&#13;
will be installed to measure the products of the collisions: ALICE, ATLAS, CMS, and LHC-b.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
The ATLAS experiment is the largest experiment. It is described in Chapter 2. This work has been&#13;
done as a part of the development of the innermost subdetector of the ATLAS detector, the pixel&#13;
detector. The pixel detector and its readout is explained in Chapter 3.&#13;
&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The steering and the data readout of the more than 80000000 channels of the pixel detector is&#13;
performed through an optical data transmission line, the optical link. This optical link and&#13;
espacially its off-detector interface, the Back of Crate card, is the central topic of this thesis.&#13;
&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The Back of Crate card has been studied in its function and its operation performance in detail&#13;
for this work. The card has been examined starting with the production (see Chapter 5), introducing&#13;
it into system tests (see Chapter 6), and operating the card in a test beam experiment very similar&#13;
to the final ATLAS experimental usage (see Chapter 7).&lt;br&gt;&#13;
One important task of the Back of Crate card is the adoption of the timing for the pixel detector&#13;
and its readout. The timing functionality of the pixel detector was studied for the first time in a&#13;
real experimental environment using traversing particles in the test beam experiment.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
The behaviour of the Back of Crate card and the results for the test beam study promise a good&#13;
performance in the final ATLAS experiment.&#13;
&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Finally this work and the results are summerised and an outlook to the forthcoming tasks is given.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 530 Physik » 530 Physik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Physik » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>