<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>896</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:53:530</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">Study of the performance of the Pierre Auger Observatory and search for primary cosmic ray photons</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Scherini, Viviana</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2007-12-07</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/physik/diss2007/scherini</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=896</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20070890</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-1002/dc0716.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;p&gt;Astroparticle physics is now entering the very exciting phase in which the efforts to enhance&#13;
the detection capabilities of our instruments begin to turn out into clear answers.&#13;
In this context the Pierre Auger Observatory (PAO) has been conceived to study the&#13;
extensive air showers produced by the primary cosmic rays at energies above 10&lt;sup&gt;&lt;font size="2"&gt;18&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;eV in&#13;
their interaction with the Earth’s atmosphere, in order to solve the mystery of the origin&#13;
and nature of the highest energy particles.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;The PAO design combines the most advanced detection techniques and the largest exposure,&#13;
to provide high data quality together with unprecedented statistics. In addition, two&#13;
experimental sites, one nearly completed in the southern hemisphere and the other to be&#13;
built in the northern one will achieve full sky coverage, and the largest exposure ever.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;The PAO collaboration benefits from the contribution of about 300 scientists from 17&#13;
countries. The Wuppertal group is highly involved in physics analysis and the study and&#13;
monitoring of the detector performance. Moreover its tasks involve hardware development&#13;
and testing. More than half of the 11 000 optical modules for the fluorescence detector&#13;
telescopes have been qualified with a highly automatised test setup. Details on the experimental&#13;
requirements and test results are presented in Section 4.3, (see [24]).&#13;
&lt;br&gt;The performance of the fluorescence detector (FD) reconstruction algorithm has been studied&#13;
at different selection levels with dedicated simulations. In Chapter 5 the FD trigger&#13;
efficiency and the geometry resolutions are calculated. A realistic estimate of the hybrid&#13;
resolution of the physics observables (depth of shower maximum and energy) is also given,&#13;
see [108]. This work includes the extension of the reconstruction capabilities to the highest&#13;
energies covered by the FD dynamic range [136].&#13;
&lt;br&gt;Discrimination of different primaries is based on their expected shower features, for instance&#13;
the depth shower maximum, X&lt;sub&gt;&lt;font size="2"&gt;max&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;. In Chapter 6 the composition sensitivity of&#13;
other parameters connected to the shape of the longitudinal shower profile is evaluated&#13;
in order to achieve an enhancement of the separation power between photon and hadron&#13;
primaries [139].&#13;
&lt;br&gt;No claim for photon observation at the highest energies has been reported so far. For&#13;
this work an update of the first limit to the fraction of photons in cosmic rays above&#13;
10 EeV [119], based on the measurement of X&lt;sub&gt;&lt;font size="2"&gt;max&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; has been performed, see Section 7.2,&#13;
reported in [21]. Finally, limits above 2, 3.16, 5 and 10 EeV are derived using the Pierre&#13;
Auger hybrid data sample Jan 2004–July 2007, see Section 7.3. The expected impact of a&#13;
photon contamination of this order on the measurement of the inelastic proton-air cross&#13;
&lt;br&gt;section is briefly discussed in Section 7.4.&#13;
Our limits confirm the ones derived by ground-based experiments at higher energies and&#13;
they strongly constrain the non-acceleration models invoked to explain the origin of the&#13;
ultra high energy cosmic rays, thus favoring astrophysical scenarios.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 530 Physik » 530 Physik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Physik » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>