<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>oai:elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de:1792</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:54:540</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="de">Konjugierte „rod-rod" Diblockcopolymere</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Koenen, Nils</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2018-01-22</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/chemie/diss2010/koenen</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=1792</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20110202-150157-5</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-1953/dc1022.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">In the last years diblock copolymers have gained a large interest in different flields of material science due to their unique self-assembling properties. „Rod-coil" diblock copolymers with one conjugated block and one non-conjugated block have been successfull synthesized. They show promising self-assembling properties. However, such „rod-coil" diblock copolymers often show disadvantageous electronic properties due tot he presence oft he isolating coil blocks. Therefore, the synthesis of „rod-rod" diblock copolymers was developed.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;In chapter 2, the synthesis of fully conjugated fluorene-/thiophene- diblock copolymers is described. The first block is a monobrominated poly(3-alkylthiophene) generated via Grignard metathesis reaction, the second block is a nonpolar polyfluorene. In a polycondensation reaction of the fluorene monomer the polythiophene is added as a macromolecular endcapper to give the corresponding polyfluorene/polythiophene diblock copolymer. A bromo- functionalized alkyl chain of the polythiophene can be converted into a polar phosphonic ester function. The novel diblock copolymers show a solvent dependent aggregation behaviour, e.g. the ability to form vesicles.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;In chapter 3, the synthesis of a conjugated donor/acceptor diblock copolymer is described. One block is again a monobrominated poly(3-alkylthiophene), the second block is an alternating fluorene/dithienyl-benzothiadiazole block. The monomer is polycondensed in a Stille-type reaction and P3AT is added as macromolecular endcapper to give the diblock copolymer. If the P3AT contains monobromo-functionalized alkylsidechains, they can be converted into  hosphonic esters, phosphonic acids or cationic trimethylammonium functionalized sidechains. All polymers show promising self-assembly properties including solvent-selective aggregation behaviour.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;In chapter 4, the synthesis of the first isotactic polyfluorene with two different alkyl chains is described. For this, a new synthetic route has been developed. Here, the key step is a enantiomeric separation on the monomer level via chiral HPLC. The chiral AB-type monomers can be polycondensed in a Suzuki-type cross coupling reaction to obtain isotactic polyfluorene. For comparison the atactic counterpart was also generated. Both polymers differ in their packing behaviour as shown in 2D-WAXS experiments and in their thermal behaviour.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 540 Chemie » 540 Chemie und zugeordnete Wissenschaften</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Chemie » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>