<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>921</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:6:62:620</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="de">Finite-Infinite-Elemente-Modellierung zur Simulation der Boden-Bauwerk-Flüssigkeit-Interaktion unter dynamischer Anregung</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Mahran, Essam</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2004-12-15</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbd/bauingenieurwesen/diss2004/mahran</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=921</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20040550</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-1027/dd0410.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="de">Durch die in den letzten Jahren an Industriebauwerken aufgetretenen Schäden infolge&#13;
Erdbebeneinwirkung wurde das Interesse zur näheren Untersuchung der Interaktionseffekte&#13;
zwischen Boden, Bauwerk und Füllmedium gesteigert. Insbesondere sind es mit&#13;
Flüssigkeiten gefüllte Behälterbauwerke, die eine realistische Beschreibung der&#13;
Interaktion der einzelnen Komponenten benötigen. Durch die fortschreitende Steigerung der&#13;
Rechenkapazität und durch den Einsatz einer Finite-Infinite-Elemente-Formulierung ist es&#13;
möglich, das System Boden-Bauwerk-Flüssigkeit als Gesamtes zu diskretisieren und einer&#13;
Ein-Schrittanalyse zu zuführen.&#13;
&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Das ganze System wird in drei Gebiete unterteilt: das Flüssigkeitsgebiet, das&#13;
Bauwerksgebiet und das Bodengebiet. Das Flüssigkeitsgebiet wird mit Hilfe der Finite-Elemente-&#13;
Methode modelliert. Das Bauwerksgebiet wird durch die Finite-Elemente-Methode modelliert.&#13;
Das Bodengebiet wird als Halbraum in zwei Subbereiche unterteilt: Zum einen&#13;
in den Nahbereich, der durch die Finite-Elemente-Methode modelliert wird, zum anderen&#13;
in den Fernbereich, der entweder mit Hilfe der Infinite-Elemente- oder der Randelemente-&#13;
Methode modelliert wird.&#13;
&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Im Rahmen dieser Arbeit werden ein finites und ein infinites Bodenelement ebenso wie ein&#13;
Randelement - als Alternative zum infiniten Element - entwickelt, mit denen der Einfluss&#13;
der unendlichen Bodenausdehnung auf die Antwort des Systems bezüglich einer statischen&#13;
oder dynamischen Beanspruchung berücksichtigt wird. Außerdem wird ein&#13;
Flüssigkeitselement zur Modellierung der Behälterfüllung entwickelt.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">The interest for a closer look on the effects of interaction between soil, structure and filling&#13;
medium was risen in the recent years caused by damages on industrial buildings as a result&#13;
of earthquake excitations. Especially liquid filled tanks need a realistic description of the&#13;
interaction of the individual components. The proceeding increase of computer capacity&#13;
allows the modelling of the system soil-structure-liquid as a whole. After that an one-step&#13;
analysis can be carried out.&#13;
&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The concept of analysis is to divide the considered structure into sub-regions: the tank&#13;
region, the fluid region, and the soil region as a half-space, and to apply a numerical&#13;
method to solve the problem in an one-step calculation.&#13;
&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The soil region has been subdivided into tow sub-fields: the near field and the far field, the&#13;
near field is the domain around structure foundation, and may show nonlinear structural&#13;
behavior. It will be modelled by means of the finite element method. The far field is the&#13;
unbounded domain extended to the infinity, and is assumed to show linear structural&#13;
behavior. For modelling of unbounded soil domain (far field) it has been suggested to&#13;
apply either the boundary or the infinite element method. Then further information about&#13;
the effect of soil infinity on the structure can be achieved. Because of implementation&#13;
restrictions of another numerical method in the software system FEMAS of Bergische&#13;
University Wuppertal, which has been developed only for the finite element method, the&#13;
implementation of boundary element method has been succeeded only for static analysis.&#13;
In recent years the infinite element method (finite element for unbounded domains) has&#13;
been demonstrated as a very effective means for simulation the interaction problems with&#13;
unbounded domains. The combination of finite and infinite element method makes it&#13;
possible to carry out a non-linear analysis within the soil near field taking into account&#13;
the effect of soil infinity. Also it is possible to consider multi-layered half-space within the&#13;
near and the far field.&#13;
&#13;
&lt;p&gt;For modelling of structure the finite element method has been applied. In the software&#13;
system FEMAS there are many finite element codes for plate, shell and beam elements.&#13;
&#13;
&lt;p&gt;For modelling of fluid as a liquid there are two finite element formulations: displacement&#13;
formulation and pressure formulation. By displacement formulation the liquid will be&#13;
considered as an elastic body without shear strength. In this case it is not required to&#13;
model the structure-fluid coupling compared to the pressure formulation and the modal&#13;
analysis can be carried out easier.&#13;
&#13;
&lt;p&gt;In the present thesis a finite and an infinite soil element also a boundary element - as&#13;
alternative to infinite element - will be developed, which allows to consider the influence&#13;
of soil infinity on the static and dynamic response of structure. In addition a liquid finite&#13;
element will be developed for modelling of tank fill.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>600 Technik, Medizin, angewandte Wissenschaften » 620 Ingenieurwissenschaften » 620 Ingenieurwissenschaften und zugeordnete Tätigkeiten</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Architektur und Bauingenieurwesen » Bauingenieurwesen » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>