<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>9260</id><datestamp>2019-04-08</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:53:530</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">Optimization of the CBM-RICH detector geometry and its use for the reconstruction of neutral mesons using conversion method</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Kres, Ievgenii</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2019-04-08</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/physik/diss2019/kres</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=9260</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20190408-114416-1</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-8650/dc1903.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;p&gt;The reconstruction of photons is an essential task for modern heavy ion experiments, since they&#13;
are emitted during the entire space-time evolution of the colliding system and they leave the&#13;
medium unaffected. Reconstructed photons allow experimentalists to explore every single step of&#13;
such an evolution. Since years the conversion analysis method is applied in modern experiments as&#13;
ALICE or CMS to reconstruct particles decaying into photons. The obtained results show better&#13;
resolution of particle reconstruction than direct measurements, but with much smaller efficiency.&#13;
The large geometrical acceptance of the CBM detector allows to reconstruct particles decaying in&#13;
photons as well.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
&#13;
There are two main sources of photons in heavy ion collisions: π&lt;sup&gt;0&lt;/sup&gt; and η mesons. Those particles&#13;
give the major background contribution to the measurements of rare dilepton decays of ρ, ω, and&#13;
J= ψ , therefore it is very essential to reconstruct them with high precision.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
&#13;
The CBM-RICH detector is the main tool for the electron identification. Therefore, in this&#13;
work, a geometry optimization of the RICH detector in the CBM experiment is studied first.&#13;
In order to improve the electron identification of the converted lepton pairs a new cylindrically&#13;
shaped geometry is proposed. The performance of the proposed geometry is compared to the&#13;
default geometry using simulation of dilepton channels of ρ and ω mesons as signal events and π&lt;sup&gt;0&lt;/sup&gt;&#13;
decays as background events.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
&#13;
By using this proposed geometry the reconstruction efficiency of π&lt;sup&gt;0&lt;/sup&gt;  and η mesons using conversion&#13;
analysis of photons with conversion in the target and in the detector material is studied.&#13;
Different cut values for particle reconstruction are discussed and the most suitable cuts are suggested.&#13;
Later on, obtained π&lt;sup&gt;0&lt;/sup&gt; results are tested in order to extract the slope parameter from the&#13;
transverse momentum spectrum of reconstructed particles. Received results are compared to the&#13;
expected value from the UrQMD generator.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
The reconstruction of η mesons using double conversion method requires data sample of large&#13;
statistics. Due to the limited storage space, one can not manage sufficient statistics using the&#13;
present simulation software framework. In this work several alternative ways of simulation are&#13;
considered, which allow users to get high statistics simulation in conditions with a limited storage&#13;
space. The obtained results from the η  analysis show the ability of the CBM experiment to&#13;
reconstruct η mesons via double conversion method from central Au+Au collisions.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 530 Physik » 530 Physik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Physik » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>