<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>9290</id><datestamp>2019-05-02</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:3:33</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">A Quantitative Approach to Tower Crane Selection and Positioning on Construction Sites</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Dienstknecht, Michael</dc:creator>
          <dc:contributor>Briskorn, Dirk</dc:contributor>
          <dc:contributor>Bock, Stefan</dc:contributor>
          <dc:date>2019-05-02</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbb/wirtschaftswissenschaft/diss2019/dienstknecht</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=9290</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20190502-113205-9</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-8700/db1901.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;p&gt;Tower cranes are a key factor in construction projects from both an operational and an economic perspective as they are the predominant lifting equipment and are among&#13;
the most expensive construction equipment. A literature review revealed that the academic literature lacks appropriate problem formulations and optimization approaches&#13;
despite of tower cranes' real-world importance.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The thesis at hand addresses this gap and introduces two optimization problems concerning the selection and on-site location of tower cranes, namely the tower crane&#13;
selection and positioning problem (TCSPP) and the tower crane selection and positioning problem in a grid (TCSPP-GRID). Both are focused on a set of crane types&#13;
differing in their specifications, i.e. rental cost, maximum operating height and maximum weight-dependent lifting radius. Cranes need to be selected and located on a&#13;
given polygonal construction site in order to cover pairs of supply and demand areas with polygonal ground plans. Demand areas, in addition, have a certain height&#13;
which may prevent certain crane types from serving the pair associated with the respective demand area and they have a maximum load weight to be lifted at any point of&#13;
the demand and the supply area. When locating cranes it has to be taken into account that a crane may neither be located in a supply or a demand area nor in crane&#13;
type-specific forbidden areas of polygonal ground plan (e.g. due to ground conditions). A pair is said to be covered if at least one crane can establish an&#13;
uninterrupted lift path for the pair's maximum weight between any two points of the demand and supply areas corresponding to the pair. The objective is to find a&#13;
minimum cost selection of cranes and their on-site locations so that each crane is in a feasible position and each pair is covered by at least one crane.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&#13;
&lt;p&gt;In the TCSPP, cranes may be located continuously in every point not occupied by a demand, supply or forbidden area and a pair is considered to be covered by a specific&#13;
crane if both the demand and the supply area are completely within the crane's maximum operating radius for the pair's maximum load weight and if the crane has&#13;
sufficient operating height. The problem is shown to be NP-complete. We prove that we can restrict ourselves to a finite set of potential crane locations without loss&#13;
of optimality which, in turn, allows us to employ the classic set cover problem for solving an instance of the TCSPP. The approach is computationally tested and&#13;
analyzed and turns out to perform favorably.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The TCSPP-GRID, in contrast to the TCSPP, respects crane interdependencies in terms of minimum distances and crane interferences as well as interferences of cranes&#13;
with given on-site obstacles. However, cranes may not be located continuously, but may only be positioned at the intersection points of a grid being laid over the&#13;
construction site. The problem is proven to be NP-hard despite of this artificial discretization. We show how to derive inputs that allow for linear models from the&#13;
given, mainly geometric instance data. Four mixed-integer linear programming formulations are presented as well as a branch and bound approach. A computational study&#13;
is conducted comparing the performance of the branch and bound approach and standard solver CPLEX based on the mixed-integer models. It is found that the former turns&#13;
out to compete favorably against the latter.&lt;/p&gt;</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>300 Sozialwissenschaften » 330 Wirtschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Wirtschaftswissenschaft/Schumpeter School of Business and Economics » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>