<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>9600</id><datestamp>2019-07-17</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:53:530</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">Study on a miniaturized satellite payload for atmospheric temperature measurements</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Liu, Jilin</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2019-07-17</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/physik/diss2019/liu</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=9600</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20190717-122302-5</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.25926/hm6f-nf38</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-8946/dc1914.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;p&gt;The atmospheric temperature reflects the thermal balance of the atmosphere and is a&#13;
valuable indicator of climate change. It has been widely recognized that the atmospheric&#13;
gravity wave activity has a profound effect on the large-scale circulation, thermal and&#13;
constituent structures in the mesosphere and lower thermosphere (MLT). Temperature&#13;
distribution in this region is an essential component to identify and quantify gravity&#13;
waves. Observation from remote sensing instruments on satellite platforms is an effective&#13;
way to measure the temperature in the MLT region.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
A miniaturized satellite payload is developed to measure the atmospheric temperature&#13;
in the MLT region via observing the O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;A-band emission. Following a Boltzmann&#13;
distribution, the relative intensities of the emission lines can be used to derive the temperature&#13;
profile. Based on the spatial heterodyne spectroscopy, this instrument is capable&#13;
of resolving individual emission lines in the O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;A-band for the spatial and spectral&#13;
information simultaneously. The monolithic and compact feature of this spectrometer&#13;
makes it suitable for operating on satellite platforms.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
In this work, the characterization of the instrument is investigated for the purpose&#13;
of simultaneously measuring multiple emission lines of the O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;A-band. The instrument&#13;
is explored through a series of experimental methods, providing characteristics of the&#13;
instrument and evaluation of its performance. In spatial and spectral domain, Level-&#13;
0 and Level-1 data processors are developed to convert the raw data to the calibrated&#13;
spectral radiance for further temperature and gravity wave characterization.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
Within this framework, the performance of the utilized detector is evaluated along&#13;
with its radiation tolerance in space environment. In the processor, the detector artifacts&#13;
are corrected based on the measurements in laboratory or in space. The radiometric&#13;
response of the instrument is characterized on a pixel-by-pixel basis using a blackbody.&#13;
An interferogram distortion correction algorithm is developed to correct for the spatial&#13;
and phase distortion induced by the detector optics. Further, localized phase distortion&#13;
correction is implemented to correct for the remaining phase error. Unwanted ghost&#13;
emission lines are removed based on two dimensional Fourier transform. In the spectral&#13;
domain, the processing steps mainly consist of wavelength calibration and instrument&#13;
spectral response correction, including filter response correction and modulation efficiency&#13;
correction.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
As an in-orbit verification, the AtmoSHINE instrument was successfully deployed&#13;
in space on 22th of December, 2018. In the first test phase, the functionality and the&#13;
performance of the instrument in space were verified. The detector dark current measurement&#13;
in orbit is consistent with the ground-based results. Based on the the calibration&#13;
procedures and the developed data processing algorithms, the O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;A-band emission&#13;
lines can be successfully resolved. A cross-verification of the AtmoSHINE limb radiance&#13;
profile with other satellite payload measurements indicates that the radiometric&#13;
performance of the instrument is within the expectation. The retrieved temperature parameters&#13;
are studied with respect to different number of samples and different objective&#13;
functions in the optimization. This work verifies the ability of the instrument to derive&#13;
the atmospheric temperature in the MLT region and its potential application in gravity&#13;
wave detections.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 530 Physik » 530 Physik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Physik » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>