<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>961</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:6:60:600</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="de">Entwicklung eines Modells zur Überprüfung des Niveaus der betrieblichen Informationssicherheit</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Tietze, Manfred R.</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2007-05-14</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbd/sicherheitstechnik/diss2007/tietze</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=961</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20070609</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-1067/dd0702.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="de">Informationen und die für die Informationsverarbeitung und Kommunikation&#13;
benutzten Anwendungen und Einrichtungen sind wertvolles und schützenswertes&#13;
Unternehmensgut. Aus diesem Grund wird die Frage nach dem "betrieblichen Niveau&#13;
der Informationssicherheit" auf Mitarbeiterebene und Möglichkeiten dem Aspekt der&#13;
"Human Firewall" effektiv entgegenzutreten in Konzernen, Behörden und Betrieben&#13;
immer stärker.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#13;
Das Ziel dieser Arbeit richtet sich in erster Linie auf die Entwicklung eines Modells&#13;
zur überprüfung des betrieblichen Niveaus der Informationssicherheit. Zur&#13;
Realisierung dieser Aufgabe wird in einem ersten Schritt der Status quo der&#13;
Informationssicherheit auf der Ebene der Mitarbeiter hinsichtlich relevanter Faktoren&#13;
ermittelt. Hierzu wird ein Fragebogeninstrument entwickelt, das zum einen eine&#13;
Einschätzung des Führungsverhaltens und der organisatorischen Gegebenheiten aus&#13;
Sicht der Mitarbeiter verlangt. Zum anderen wird von den Mitarbeitern eine&#13;
Selbsteinschätzung bzgl. der betrieblichen Informationssicherheit in Anlehnung an die&#13;
Theorie des geplanten Verhaltens von AJZEN &amp; MADDEN (1986) und an die&#13;
wahrgenommene "Soziale Unterstützung" durch Kollegen und Vorgesetzte gefordert.&#13;
In zweiter Linie werden neben dem entwickelten Fragebogen weitere bereits&#13;
standardisierte Fragebögen zur Analyse der "Belastung am Bildschirmarbeitsplatz"&#13;
und "Softwareergonomie" eingesetzt.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#13;
Die aus den Fragebögen gewonnenen Ergebnisse werden sowohl zwischen "ITAnwender"&#13;
und "IT-Experten", als auch mit innerhalb der Gruppen ermittelten Typenprofilen&#13;
in Beziehung gesetzt, ausführlich diskutiert und Umsetzungsmaßnahmen&#13;
empfohlen.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">Information as well as the applications and devices used for information processing&#13;
and communication are a company’s own capital that is precious and worth to be&#13;
protected. Therefore, the issues regarding the "internal level of information security"&#13;
on employee-level as well as the possibilities of handling the aspect of the "human&#13;
firewall" in enterprises, authorities and business are getting more and more important.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The prime target of this work is the development a model that enables to review the&#13;
internal level of information security. For realisation of this target, the status quo of&#13;
information security on employee-level in view of the relevant factors will be&#13;
determined as a first step. For this purpose, a questionnaire will be designed that&#13;
demands an assessment of managerial behaviour and organisational structures from the&#13;
employees’ point of view on the one hand. On the other hand, the employees are asked&#13;
to do a self-assessment regarding the internal information security following the&#13;
theories of AJZEN &amp; MADDEN (1986) as well as the percieved "social support" by&#13;
colleagues and superiors. Secondly, standardised questionnaires for analysis of "strain&#13;
by on-screen work" as well as "software ergonomics" will be used besides the&#13;
designed questionnaire mentioned above.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#13;
The results of the questionnaires will be set in relation between "IT-users" and "ITexperts"&#13;
as well as between the types of characters determined within a single group.&#13;
Afterwards, the results will be discussed and measures for realisation will be&#13;
recommended.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="fr">Information as well as the applications and devices used for information processing&#13;
and communication are a company’s own capital that is precious and worth to be&#13;
protected. Therefore, the issues regarding the "internal level of information security"&#13;
on employee-level as well as the possibilities of handling the aspect of the "human&#13;
firewall" in enterprises, authorities and business are getting more and more important.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The prime target of this work is the development a model that enables to review the&#13;
internal level of information security. For realisation of this target, the status quo of&#13;
Les informations ainsi que les applications et les installations utilisées pour le&#13;
traitement de l’information et la communication sont un bien précieux et digne de&#13;
protection de l’entreprise. C’est pourquoi la question « du niveau de la sécurité de&#13;
l’information au sein de l’entreprise » devient de plus en plus importante à l’échelon&#13;
des collaborateurs dans les konzerns, les administrations et les entreprises, de même&#13;
que les possibilités pour faire face de manière efficace à l’aspect du « Human&#13;
Firewall »&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#13;
L’objectif de ce travail vise en premier lieu la réalisation d’un modèle de contrôle du&#13;
niveau de la sécurité de l’information au sein de l’entreprise. En vue de réaliser cette&#13;
tâche, il s’agit dans un premier temps de déterminer le statu quo de la sécurité de&#13;
l’information à l’échelon des collaborateurs quant aux facteurs significatifs. A cet&#13;
effet, un instrument contenant un questionnaire doit être élaboré qui demande d’un&#13;
côté une appréciation du comportement de la direction et de la réalité de l’organisation&#13;
dans l’optique des collaborateurs. De l’autre côté, l’on demande aux collaborateurs&#13;
une auto-évaluation relative à la sécurité de l’information au sein de l’entreprise sur le&#13;
modèle de la théorie du comportement prévu de AJZEN &amp; MADDEN (1986) et de «&#13;
l’assistance « des collègues et des supérieurs perçue. En second lieu, il s’agit d’utiliser&#13;
accessoirement au questionnaire réalisé d’autres questionnaires déjà standardisés en&#13;
vue d’analyser les « contraintes dues au poste de travail sur écran » et l’ergonomie&#13;
relative au logiciel.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#13;
Les résultats obtenus par les questionnaires sont mis en relation non seulement entre&#13;
les utilisateurs de l’informatique et les informaticiens mais aussi avec des profils type&#13;
établis à l’intérieur des groupes. Ils sont discutés en détail et des recommandations sur&#13;
les mesures à prendre pour une mise en pratique sont présentées.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>600 Technik, Medizin, angewandte Wissenschaften » 600 Technik » 600 Technik, Technologie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Maschinenbau und Sicherheitstechnik » Sicherheitstechnik » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>