<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>9720</id><datestamp>2019-09-03</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:3:33:330</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">Cross-functional coopetition in new product development: Can constraints drive integration? A case of the design–manufacturing interface of electrified cars</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Bix, Susanne</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2019-09-03</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbb/wirtschaftswissenschaft/diss2019/bix</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=9720</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20190903-120508-8</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.25926/hja7-zx02</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-9080/db1905.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;p&gt;Enhancing cross-functional integration in new product development becomes increasingly important for industrial players to keep up with shorter product life cycles in technological innovation dynamics.&#13;
Abundant research reflects the topic’s significance, yet ambiguity in empirical results persists and industrial adoption of existing methods remains incremental. &#13;
This thesis employs a qualitative approach to build a case study at the design-manufacturing interface of new product development of electrified cars. &#13;
Cross-functional coopetition, as the joint occurrence of cooperation and competition, is adopted to generate an in-depth understanding of integration dynamics.&#13;
Socio-organizational and contextual aspects are found to shape integration in a new product development context substantially. &#13;
A model of interface dynamics is developed which provides for analysis and prediction of these aspects’ impact on effective integration. &#13;
A grounded theory approach to enhance integration is explored that introduces constraints as stimuli to consider manufacturability aspects in the design process. &#13;
Constraint introduction is found to positively impact both cross-functional integration and creativity, with eight characteristics of constraint quality identified as moderating factors. &#13;
A theoretical model is contributed which outlines cause-effect relationships of constraints’ impact on antecedents of new product development success. &#13;
It substantiates constraints’ role in innovation contexts and encourages application for design-manufacturing integration as well as for other interfaces or purposes.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>300 Sozialwissenschaften » 330 Wirtschaft » 330 Wirtschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Wirtschaftswissenschaft/Schumpeter School of Business and Economics » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>