<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>9730</id><datestamp>2019-09-10</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:54:540</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">Organic Sensitizers and Luminogens for Optoelectronic Devices</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Bayseç, Şebnem</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2019-09-10</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/chemie/diss2019/baysec</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=9730</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20190910-101746-5</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.25926/3txq-wa08</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-9091/dc1920.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;p&gt;Among the world of materials, organic semiconductors have attracted great&#13;
attention due to their low cost, easy fabrication, and tunable properties. The development&#13;
of high-performance organic materials over the past years have led to increase of their&#13;
investigation and usage in optoelectronic field rapidly. So far, increasing the device&#13;
efficiencies have been the main issue. From the chemist’s point of view, tailoring the&#13;
properties of materials by facile synthetic modifications to enhance the efficiency of the&#13;
device and enlarging the application areas is a useful strategy.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
In that respect, different synthetic strategies have been applied to reach the desired&#13;
properties in this thesis. A variety of small molecules and polymers based on Borondipyrromethene&#13;
(BODIPY) and Tetraphenylethylene (TPE) have been synthesized,&#13;
characterized and properties of the materials with regard to their application in OFETs,&#13;
fluorescent-based chemical sensors, and OLEDs have been demonstrated. In addition, this&#13;
thesis provides an overview of recent developments in the field.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 540 Chemie » 540 Chemie und zugeordnete Wissenschaften</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Chemie » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>