<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>9820</id><datestamp>2019-10-09</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:53:530</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">Simulation and measurement of the Forward Beam Monitor detector signal for the KATRIN experiment</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Haußmann, Norman</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2019-10-09</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/physik/diss2019/haussmann</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=9820</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20191009-085446-9</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.25926/8q1y-6752</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-9179/dc1924.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;p&gt;The aim of the KArlsruhe TRItium Neutrino (KATRIN) experiment is to measure the effective&#13;
neutrino mass with a sensitivity of 0.2 eV (90% C.L.). In order to achieve that, high precision&#13;
beta spectroscopy from tritium beta decay is performed close to the endpoint of tritium. This&#13;
requires a high luminosity source. To reach the sensitivity goal, the systematic uncertainties of&#13;
the experiment, such as the stability of the beta Source, have to be known and kept at a low&#13;
level. One component to monitor the source stability is the Forward Beam Monitor (FBM). The&#13;
monitoring is done with two silicon&lt;i&gt; p-i-n&lt;/i&gt;-diodes detecting the beta electrons from the Source.&#13;
&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The goal of this thesis is to simulate the expected detector signal of the FBM and compare&#13;
against first measurements performed with the KATRIN experiment in summer 2018. In order&#13;
to simulate the Forward Beam Monitor detector signal, a response matrix approach is utilized.&#13;
Thus, the simulated beta emission spectrum is split into energy and polar angle bins. Each set of&#13;
events is propagated separately through the experiment. As a beta electron is bent by magnetic&#13;
fields and undergoes different scattering processes its polar angle and energy can be changed.&#13;
This leads to a certain probability of beta electrons from an initial energy and polar angle bin&#13;
to be distributed into different energy and polar angle bins. Probabilities are calculated for the&#13;
propagation through each component of the experiment, which is essential for the simulation of&#13;
the FBM detector signal.&#13;
&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The results of the rate simulation and the detected rate of beta electrons agree. The spectral&#13;
shape and intensity of the beta electrons above 8 keV are also comparable. Additionally,&#13;
the FBM is able to scan the transversal beta &#13;
flux distribution on a two-dimensional plane.&#13;
Therefore, the radial dependency of the rate is simulated, which also agrees with the measured&#13;
rate.&#13;
&#13;
&lt;p&gt;In this thesis, the different steps that need to be taken in order to simulate the FBM detector&#13;
spectrum are presented as well the simulation challenges. A new approach into simulating the&#13;
scattered beta spectrum of the source, which can be utilized in future for neutrino mass analyses&#13;
and source models, is also presented.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 530 Physik » 530 Physik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Physik » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>