<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>9960</id><datestamp>2019-11-28</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:53:530</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">Development and investigation of the Forward Beam Monitor for the KATRIN experiment</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Ellinger, Enrico</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2019-11-28</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/physik/diss2019/ellinger</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=9960</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20191127-123110-5</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.25926/r160-7a40</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-9314/dc1932.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;p&gt;&#13;
The KArlsruhe TRitium Neutrino (KATRIN) experiment, which is housed at the Karlsruhe Institute of Technology (KIT), is designed to &#13;
&#13;
measure the mass of the electron antineutrino in a direct and model-independent way with a sensitivity of 0.2 eV/c&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; at 90 % &#13;
&#13;
confidence level. This is achieved by a precise measurement of the beta spectrum of tritium. The electrons originate from a high &#13;
&#13;
luminosity windowless tritium source and are measured spectroscopically in an electro static filter (MAC-E filter).&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&#13;
The topic of this work is the development, investigation and final integration of the Forward Beam Monitor (FBM) of KATRIN. The FBM is &#13;
&#13;
used in KATRIN to monitor the relative intensity of the electron flux, generated by the tritium source, with a precision of 0.1 %. &#13;
&#13;
Furthermore the FBM is able to record beta spectra with an energy resolution of σ&lt;sub&gt;FWHM&lt;/sub&gt; ≈ 2 keV for additional analysis. In &#13;
&#13;
order to achieve this degree of quality, the detector electronics, the detection device itself and its response to electron events must &#13;
&#13;
be well understood. Therefore measurements with electrons are performed as well as simulations which can reproduce the measured spectra.&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&#13;
The detector can be moved to any position in the flux tube’s cross section with a positioning accuracy of 0.1 mm. The positioning is &#13;
&#13;
realized by a more than two meter long vacuum manipulator. High demands on the hardware are made since the setup must be suitable for the &#13;
&#13;
use in ultra high vacuum environment, it has to be non-magnetic and must fulfill all criteria for the use in a tritium bearing system. &#13;
&#13;
The present work presents the developing process from the prototype to the final commissioning of the FBM at KATRIN.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 530 Physik » 530 Physik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Physik » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>