<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>oai:elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de:3268</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:54:540</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="de">Bestimmung von polyzyklischen aromatischen Kohlenwasserstoffen in Bedarfsgegenständen und Verbraucherprodukten</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="de">– Optimierung der Probenvorbereitung, der Aufreinigung und der Analyse mittels GC-MS und GCxGC-MS –</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Wydra, Nicole Elisabeth</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2018-01-22</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/chemie/diss2012/wydra</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=3268</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20130108-155028-8</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-3385/dc1226.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;p&gt;The gas chromatographic determination described in the document ZEK 01.2-08:&#13;
“Testing and Validation of Polycyclic Aromatic Hydrocarbons (PAH) in the course of&#13;
GS-Mark Certification” was introduced into an analytical laboratory and validated.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;Individual steps of the method were optimized systematically with respect to easier&#13;
handling and increased efficiency during sample preparation and clean-up.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;Sample grinding was automated by the use of a cutting mill, which made quick and&#13;
homogeneous size reduction possible for very hard and large-sized products, as well&#13;
as elastic and soft materials. The device’s robustness allowed the crushing of&#13;
elastomers and rubber products previously made brittle by immersion in liquid&#13;
nitrogen.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;The time-consuming sample clean-up over glass columns manually packed with&#13;
silica gel was improved by the use of industrially made, more densely packed silica&#13;
gel cartridges. This limits laborious preparation of sorbent and glassware prior to&#13;
analysis. The optimized clean-up also saves time and amount of solvent and&#13;
achieves more effective purification of the sample extracts.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;The majority of consumer goods and plastic products analysed in the various&#13;
categories showed either no detectable level or only low levels of polycyclic aromatic&#13;
hydrocarbon content. The concentrations determined are significantly below the&#13;
maximum levels set in the document ZEK 01.2-08 for the three categories of&#13;
materials expected to come into contact with the human skin. The results illustrate&#13;
that materials can be produced according to good manufacturing practice by the use&#13;
of appropriate and pure raw materials.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;During chromatographic analysis of the toluene extracts – especially from soft&#13;
materials, elastomers and rubbers – interferences arose that were due to additional&#13;
substances extracted from the sample. These dissolved matrix components have&#13;
vapour pressures similar to those of the analytes under investigation and interfere&#13;
with the qualitative and quantitative determination of the aromatics. Not even&#13;
clean-up with modified sorbents or polymeric-phase cartridges could facilitate&#13;
successful separation of these substances, which were especially problematic when&#13;
they occurred in the molecular mass range between m/z 178 and 228 Da. Neither the&#13;
method according to the ZEK document nor the optimized clean-up procedure&#13;
presented in this work allowed the total separation of interfering matrix components.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;Fractional elution of an exemplary sample extract, performed on manually filled silica&#13;
gel glass columns, demonstrates that these interfering substances have not only&#13;
similar vapour pressure but similar polar properties, as well, as they do not interact&#13;
with the solid phase. They can therefore only with difficulty be separated from the&#13;
aromatic compounds under investigation.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;In a second focus, the separation efficiency of two-dimensional comprehensive gas&#13;
chromatography was demonstrated for the analysis of complex matrices.&#13;
With this highly efficient separation, complex matrices of extracts from plastic&#13;
products are analysed not only in terms of their composition but also for an&#13;
instrumental separation of interfering matrix components from the analytes to be&#13;
determined. Investigation of some extracts contaminated with matrix components&#13;
showed successful separation. By means of mass spectrometric detection, both&#13;
identification and quantification were achieved with this technique.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;The efficiency of this two-dimensional system could be demonstrated in further&#13;
studies of selected consumer products purchased in local stores. In agreement with&#13;
the strong aromatic odour of the samples, high amounts of PAH could be determined&#13;
by the method presented here. As a result of the different and independent&#13;
separation mechanisms – separation according to the analytes’ vapour pressure in&#13;
the first dimension of the system followed by separation through their interaction with&#13;
the stationary phase in the second dimension – clusters and groups of similar&#13;
substances occurred within the two-dimensional plot. In addition to the 16 EPA-PAH,&#13;
many isomers and congeners of polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons could be&#13;
identified.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 540 Chemie » 540 Chemie und zugeordnete Wissenschaften</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Chemie » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>