<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>oai:elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de:776</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:54:540</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">Naphthalene Based Conjugated Materials</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Nehls, Benjamin S.</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2005-10-11</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/chemie/diss2005/nehls</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=776</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20050441</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-873/dc0511.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">The relationship between the chemical structure of π – conjugated polymers or oligomers and their&#13;
macroscopic optical and electrooptical properties is complex in nature and not fully understood at the&#13;
present. Fused aromatic rings are often incorporated into semiconducting organic materials in order to&#13;
realize a more extended π – conjugation. The simplest example of fused rings is naphthalene with two&#13;
condensed phenyl rings. Naphthalene has a versatile and well – developed substitution chemistry,&#13;
which provides different patterns for both polymerization and side – chain attachment. Therefore,&#13;
utilizing the naphthalene unit should allow some tuning of the electronic and optical properties of the&#13;
resulting materials. The work presented in this thesis is focused on incorporating naphthalene units&#13;
into conjugated poly – and oligomers.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;In chapter 2, naphthalene is incorporated into alternating copolymers as the simplest way of&#13;
introducing new building blocks into new polymers. To get a better understanding different model&#13;
compounds have been synthesized and compared with the polymers. Some of the model compounds&#13;
are under investigation as active layers in organic field effect transistors (OFETs).&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Chapter 3 presents a series of novel polyarylene – type ladder polymers containing 1,5- and 2,6- linked&#13;
naphthalene units. This includes the first example of such ladder polymers consisting exclusively of&#13;
six membered rings. The substitution patterns and linkage positions allow some fine tuning of the&#13;
optical properties. One of the ladder polymers is also utilized as the gain material of a distributed&#13;
feedback (DFB) polymer laser.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The polymers in chapter 4 utilize the 1,1'-binaphthyl unit as the central unit of a new class of&#13;
potentially helical, conjugated ladderpolymers. Due to the interrupted conjugation across the&#13;
binaphthyl moiety, some tuning of the optical properties is possible. To investigate the substitution&#13;
patterns two model compounds have been synthesized and characterized via NMR and X-ray&#13;
crystallography.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Chapter 5 introduces novel statistical copolymers of (9,9-dioctylfluorene) containing various amounts&#13;
of binaphthyl units. Herein the binaphthyl unit shows its capability to suppress side chain&#13;
crystallization and leads to completely amorphous materials. Second order (DFB) polymer lasers&#13;
based on thin films of these materials showed extremely low lasing thresholds. The materials allow a&#13;
dramatic improvement of polyfluorene based solid state lasers.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;In the last chapter a new family of star – shaped oligoaryl dimers based on binaphthyl or biphenyl&#13;
cores are described. An extensive investigation of their structure and electronic properties including&#13;
UV/Vis and NMR spectroscopy as well as X – ray analysis is presented, especially related to&#13;
intramolecular π - π – interactions.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 540 Chemie » 540 Chemie und zugeordnete Wissenschaften</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Chemie » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>