<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>oai:elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de:723</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:54:540</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="de">Entwicklung analytischer Methoden zur Objektivierung sensorischer Qualitätskontrollen von Haselnusskernen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Sies, Anke</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2004-08-10</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/chemie/diss2004/sies</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=723</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20040370</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-819/dc0407.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">An analytical method was developed for the rapid determination of sensory quality deviations of&#13;
hazelnuts. The method is based on the investigation of aroma spectra via direct thermal desorption&#13;
of lipids and on the identification of relevant components using a time of flight mass spectrometer&#13;
after chromatographic separation (DTD/Fast-GC/TOF-MS).&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The sample preparation is quite simple and the application as fast-GC shortens the analysis time&#13;
substantially. Small deviations in the sensory impression correlated with measurable changes in&#13;
the aroma profile obtained by the developed method. A classification and consequently an&#13;
evaluation of the quality of the nuts was achieved using different models of statistical evaluation&#13;
and discriminant analysis.&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The compounds used as markers for quality deviations of hazelnuts in the DTD/Fast-GC/TOF-MS&#13;
analysis were identified by applying aroma extract dilution analysis (AEDA) and olfactory&#13;
investigations of thermal desorbed oils from hazelnuts (TCT-HRGC-O). We identified&#13;
homologous aldehydes from hexanal to undecanal as well as 2,4-(E,E)-nonadienal and&#13;
2,4-(E,E)-decadienal as autoxidation products of lipids and original constituents like the&#13;
monoterpenes α- and β-pinene, camphene and Δ-3-caren.&#13;
&lt;p&gt;To clarify the cause of peroxidative deterioration of hazelnuts, hydroperoxy fatty acids as&#13;
precursors of aroma compounds from peroxidation products were investigated using HPLC and&#13;
MEKC. It was shown that the peroxidative damage of hazelnuts was mostly caused by&#13;
lipoxygenase activity.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 540 Chemie » 540 Chemie und zugeordnete Wissenschaften</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Chemie » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>