<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>oai:elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de:3900</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:53:530</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="de">Charakterisierung und Einsatz eines PTR-ToF-MS zur Messung von flüchtigen organischen Verbindungen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Sonderfeld, Hannah</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2018-01-22</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/physik/diss2013/sonderfeld</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=3900</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20140403-101422-2</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-4010/dc1325.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="de">&lt;p&gt;This work describes the characterization of a PTR-ToF-MS and results from laboratory&#13;
experiments as well as in-situ measurements of VOC during a field campaign.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
Initially, the fragmentation of organic compounds in the drift tube of the instrument&#13;
was investigated. Organic compounds of different classes were analysed to determine the&#13;
different fragments and their ratios. Some typical fragment patterns were confirmed such&#13;
as the loss of H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O from aldehydes, a fragment of mass 81 for monoterpenes, protonated&#13;
benzene as a fragment from substituted aromatics and NH&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; for some amines. &#13;
A signal of the same mass as protonated toluene was identified as a fragment from monoterpenes.&#13;
The consideration of the fragmentation for the analysis of all following measurements is&#13;
described step by step.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
The relative transmission for protonated analytes depending on the mass was determined&#13;
by measuring two gas standards covering the mass range from 33 to 181. Several&#13;
correction terms were included. The investigations showed that the temperature of the&#13;
gas standard influences the steepness of the transmission curve while the relative humidity&#13;
of the sample does not.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
For each compound (methanol, acetaldehyde, acetone/propanal, toluene, ethylbenzene/&#13;
xylene, pinene) the best conditions to determine the normalized sensitivity were&#13;
defined and long-term measurements showed a good overall stability. Under laboratory&#13;
conditions the lower limit of detection ranged from 8 pptV for ethylbenzene/xylene to&#13;
180 pptV for methanol.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
The advantages of PTR-ToF-MS such as high mass and time resolution are presented&#13;
using the example of two product studies at reaction chambers. It was found that 70% of&#13;
toluene was removed at a TiO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; surface under radiation with UV-light. Some oxygenated&#13;
VOC were identified as products, but only in amounts close to the lower detection limit&#13;
of the PTR-ToF-MS. In a photooxidation study of 3-methyl-2-nitrophenol one primary&#13;
(C&lt;sub&gt;7&lt;/sub&gt;H&lt;sub&gt;7&lt;/sub&gt;NO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;) and one secondary (C&lt;sub&gt;7&lt;/sub&gt;H&lt;sub&gt;5&lt;/sub&gt;NO&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;) &#13;
product was identified. In combination with cAPECI the structure of the secondary product could be determined.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
The PTR-ToF-MS was used to perform continuous real time measurements of VOC&#13;
at Kleiner Feldberg, Taunus, Germany, during the PARADE campaign in 2011. Varying&#13;
meteorological conditions influenced the mixing ratios. Oxygenated VOC were found to&#13;
be mainly of biogenic origin with some anthropogenic influence. Compared to measurements&#13;
in 2000 the mixing ratios of methanol and acetaldehyde increased by a factor of&#13;
10 and 20, respectively. As well as the OVOCs, monoterpenes showed a good agreement&#13;
with modelled mixing ratios by a simple temperature dependent emission modell. In&#13;
contrast to the OVOCs 80% less toluene was measured on average in 2011 compared&#13;
to 2000. In comparison with the wind directions a source apportionment of toluene and&#13;
ethylbenzene/xylene became apparent.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 530 Physik » 530 Physik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Physik » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>