<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>oai:elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de:298</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:53:530</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="de">Nichtbeschattbarkeit durch Dimensionsvariabilität in dynamischen Systemen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Sinde, Erik</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2001-02-16</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fb08/diss2000/sinde</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=298</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20010124</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-392/d080004.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">Numerical simulations of dynamical systems often rely inexplicitely on the hypothesis&#13;
that the simulated pseudo-trajectory represents a true trajectory of the system in the sense&#13;
that both the pseudo-trajectory and the true trajectory stay close to each other for arbitra-rily&#13;
long time. This is guaranteed to hold for hyperbolic systems by the shadowing lemma&#13;
(Anosov 1967, Bowen 1975). However, this is not the case in general. Virtually, all real&#13;
systems which physicists encounter, are nonhyperbolic, and in most systems the shado-wing&#13;
property does not hold. Dynamical systems with unstable dimension variability&#13;
have recently gained interest as a source both of nonhyperbolicity and nonshadowability.&#13;
Some recent publications[7] claim that the nonshadowability due to unstable dimension&#13;
variability is particularly severe.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;In this work for a very simple dynamical system driven by one out of three input systems&#13;
is investigated. Numerical evidence is presented, that all the combined systems are prac-tically&#13;
unshadowable due to the same mechanism, although only two of them can have&#13;
unstable dimension variability, the third being a quasiperiodic map which has no periodic&#13;
orbits.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;In order to show numerically for the first and second input system that both singly and&#13;
doubly unstable periodic orbits are embedded into the attractor, a new method is applied&#13;
to one of the systems to show that the attractor fills a region of the phase space densely.&#13;
This method consists of iterating particular lines which are known to be subsets of the&#13;
attractor instead of points and consecutively applying a Poincaré surface-of-section-like&#13;
technique. For one of the studied maps this can reduce the dimensionality of the system&#13;
by one.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;For the three model systems, the probability distribution of the shadowing times is inve-stigated&#13;
through simulation. Additionally, a new deterministic measure to quantify the&#13;
severeness of nonshadowability due to unstable dimension variability is introduced and&#13;
applied to the model systems. This quantity estimates by how many digits the calculus&#13;
precision has to exceed the required closeness to a true trajectory on average for a given&#13;
trajectory length. It is argued and verified numerically that for the case of unstable dimen-sion&#13;
variability the number of additionally needed calculus precision digits is proportional&#13;
to the logarithm of the trajectory length. Thereby even pseudo-trajectories with arbitrarily&#13;
small one step errors cannot be shadowed by true trajectories for arbitrarily long time.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The nonshadowability can however in the same time be rigorous and very small, so that&#13;
for some practical purposes this system can be regarded as almost shadowable. On the&#13;
other hand, the same mechanism can produce similar results for systems where unstable&#13;
dimension variability does not occur. In those systems there is an upper limit to the addi-tionally&#13;
needed calculus precision. This limit can be so large that for practical purposes&#13;
this system behaves as a nonshadowable one although it is shadowable in the sense of the&#13;
shadowing lemma.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 530 Physik » 530 Physik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Physik » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>