<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>oai:elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de:10350</id><datestamp>2020-03-05</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:51:510</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">On Shape Calculus with Elliptic PDE Constraints in Classical Function Spaces</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Bittner, Laura</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2020-03-05</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/mathematik/diss2019/bittner</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=10350</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20200305-111846-5</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.25926/pkfr-kr55</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-9668/dc1948.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">In this thesis we develop a functional analytic framework for shape optimization with elliptic partial differential equation (PDE) constraints in classical function spaces (Hölder spaces). &#13;
This approach is motivated by shape optimization problems, which are subjected to linear elasticity constraints and involve a special class of shape functionals which calculate &#13;
the failure rate of a mechanically loaded device w.r.t. the component shape. These objectives are ill-defined for &lt;i&gt;H&lt;/i&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;-solutions of the state equation and the shape derivatives are not defined &#13;
for &lt;i&gt;H&lt;/i&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;-material derivatives. Thus, the resulting optimal reliability problems can not be solved by the already existing methods of shape calculus. We develop a general concept on Banach and &#13;
Hilbert spaces which is based on parameter depending variational equations, classical PDE Solutions, Schauder estimates and compact embeddings and which allows to transfer differentiability &#13;
in lower Banach space topologies to higher ones. We apply this framework to the linear elasticity equation and its variational formulation, given that the domain is transformed according &#13;
to the speed method. We prove the existence of material and local shape derivatives in Hölder spaces, the existence of shape derivatives and derive adjoint equations. &#13;
We also give a classification of the &lt;i&gt;L&lt;/i&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;-shape gradient w.r.t. its regularity and its potential to sustain the domain regularity along a descent flow.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 510 Mathematik » 510 Mathematik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Mathematik und Informatik » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>