<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>oai:elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de:3563</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:53:530</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">Study of the Potential of the ATLAS Detector to Observe a Higgs Decay into t¯t in the Fully Hadronic Decay Mode</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Siebel, Anca-Mirela</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2018-01-22</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/physik/diss2006/siebel</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=3563</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20130605-115407-0</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-3664/dc0622.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;p&gt;In this thesis a pre-study of the search for heavy super-symmetric Higgs bosons H and A with the ATLAS experiment is presented.&#13;
Studied is the fully hadronic decay channel into six jets via an intermediate top-antitop pair. Special consideration is paid to the &#13;
improvement of the discovery potential by adding a b-tagging algorithm to the level 2 trigger system of ATLAS. &#13;
The study is based on simulated events corresponding to an integrated luminosity of 35.8 inverse femtobarn. &#13;
While with the standard trigger menu no exclusion limit on a Higgs contribution could be given, it was found that the addition of&#13;
a b-tagging procedure to the trigger system allows for the exclusion of Higgs contributions for Higgs masses up to 720 GeV.&#13;
A distinctive peak-dip structure due to interference effects, which was introduced into the simulated data for this study, proved to be crucial for the sensitivity to Higgs contributions.&lt;/p&gt;</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 530 Physik » 530 Physik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Physik » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>