<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>oai:elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de:355</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:53:530</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="de">Remote Sensing and Modelling of the Earth's Middle Atmosphere: results of the CRISTA Experiment</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Riese, Martin</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2001-12-07</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fb08/habi2000/riese</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=355</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20010706</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-449/h080001.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="de">The CRISTA experiment&#13;
        provided high-quality limb observations of atmospheric infrared emission with high spatial resolution. The inversion of these observations to&#13;
atmospheric temperature and trace gas distributions is based on an efficient data system. The fast measurement technique of CRISTA results in a large amount of radiance&#13;
data. The radiative transfer calculations required to retrieve atmospheric pressures,&#13;
temperatures, and trace gas mixing ratios (level 2 data) are very complex and several iterations of the whole retrieval process have to be performed in order to achieve&#13;
high-quality retrieval results. The CRISTA forward radiance model therefore uses&#13;
fast radiative transfer codes based on precalculated atmospheric emissivity lookup&#13;
tables which account for the details of the CRISTA spectroscopy. The forward model&#13;
is the core of a multiple-emitter multiple-spectral sampling point onion-peeling algorithm, which proved to be well suited to resolve horizontal and vertical atmospheric&#13;
structures.&#13;
&lt;p&gt;      CRISTA provides information on the most prominent&#13;
atmospheric wave types,&#13;
e. g. on thermal tides and on planetary waves. Temperatures measured by CRISTA-1&#13;
(November 1994) show pronounced tidal structures which can be described by the&#13;
linear theory as implemented in the GSWM (Global Scale Wave Model, Hagan et&#13;
al., 1995). Planetary wave-two signatures observed during CRISTA-2 are consistent&#13;
with those expected from a migrating planetary wave with an ozone signature, which&#13;
is dynamically driven at lower altitudes (below 35 km) and photochemically driven&#13;
at higher altitudes. CRISTA results above the middle stratosphere show a better&#13;
agreement with photochemical equilibrium calculations than previous analyses.&#13;
&lt;p&gt;      CRISTA observations are especially suited for analyses of atmospheric transport&#13;
processes. In the equatorial stratopause region (50 km) circulation cells arising from&#13;
inertially unstable conditions were present during the CRISTA-1 observation period.&#13;
Two separate circulation cells in different longitude bands with opposite phases were&#13;
observed. Another new finding is that the upper stratospheric circulation cell appears&#13;
to be linked to a lower-stratosphere Kelvin wave with a zonal wavenumber of one.&#13;
Since the Kelvin wave has about the same vertical scale as the circulation cells (»&#13;
10 km), and is approximately in phase with it, interactions between these two dy-&#13;
namical features may have occurred. The vertical motion associated with the Kelvin&#13;
&#13;
wave could have affected the inertially unstable flow, e. g. by controlling its vertical&#13;
scale. The temperature perturbations observed by CRISTA are rather small and may&#13;
have been below the detection limit of previous observations. Circulation cells arising from inertially unstable conditions could be more common than previous studies&#13;
would indicate and thus play a significant role for tracer transport in this atmospheric&#13;
region.&#13;
&lt;p&gt;      High resolution stratospheric trace gases distributions measured by CRISTA are&#13;
ideally suited for studies of stratospheric transport related to planetary wave activity, especially when they are used in conjunction with a three-dimensional transport&#13;
model. The CRISTA missions took place during periods of disturbed dynamical&#13;
conditions characterized by relatively large wave activity and associated exchange of&#13;
tropical and extra-tropical air. As a result, numerous small and medium-scale structures were present in the trace gas distributions measured by CRISTA. The detailed&#13;
structure of the observed constituent distributions has been modeled with the NCAR&#13;
ROSE chemical transport model. The modeled trace gas distributions capture most&#13;
of the measured planetary-scale and medium-scale structures, especially at high and&#13;
middle latitudes.&#13;
&lt;p&gt;      For quantitative studies of transport and photochemical processes the ROSE CTM&#13;
has been used as the core of a sequential data assimilation system. Sequential assimilation of long-lived species and chemical families appears to be an attractive technique&#13;
to create synoptic trace gas fields from asynoptic satellite observations. The assimilation system provides synoptic distributions that are consistent with the CRISTA&#13;
measurements at each time step of the model (20 min). Data gaps are filled and&#13;
the measured trace gas distributions are extrapolated towards higher latitudes. The&#13;
assimilation system provides, in addition, distributions of unmeasured species (con-&#13;
sistent with the measurements). The main advantage of assimilated trace gas distributions is the availability of synoptic trace gas fields derived from observations on the&#13;
temporal and spatial grid of the meteorological fields. This allows, for example, for&#13;
quantitative studies of eddy fluxes and of their influence on the temporal evolution of&#13;
the background atmosphere. Horizontal eddy fluxes of CFC-11 (31.6 mbar) calculated&#13;
for CRISTA-1 from the assimilated trace gas concentrations are in reasonable agreement with respective fluxes calculated from modeled trace gas fields without data&#13;
assimilation. Both data sets indicate a large degree of temporal cancellation of eddy&#13;
transport during the time period of the CRISTA-1 measurements. A study of the CH4&#13;
budget at 4.6 mbar indicates that irreversible transport processes are rather important&#13;
at this pressure level during the time period of the CRISTA-1 measurements. Most&#13;
interesting is a pronounced mixing event from mid-latitudes into the tropics, which is&#13;
also evident in measured and calculated zonal mean CH4 mixing ratio tendencies.&#13;
&lt;p&gt;    To study chemical processes of short-lived species under realistic conditions, the&#13;
assimilation system has been extended to chemical families such as NOy, Clx, and Ox.&#13;
Through this approach, simulations of short-lived species such as N2O5 and NO2 can&#13;
be constrained by CRISTA observations of long-lived species, and total amounts of&#13;
chemical families, derived from measurements of individual family members. This allows for meaningful comparisons of measured and modeled short-lived species. In the&#13;
present case, the approach has been successfully used to perform a study of the partitioning ratios of the nitrogen family. In particular, the dependence of the partitioning&#13;
on assumptions made for the aerosol loading and key gas-phase reaction rates was&#13;
investigated. Very good agreement between measured and modeled fields was found&#13;
in terms of significant diurnal variations and large longitudinal variations. Sequential&#13;
assimilation of chemical families appears to be an attractive method to investigate&#13;
global fields of chemically active species provided by satellite observations, thereby&#13;
testing our current understanding of photochemical processes.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 530 Physik » 530 Physik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Physik » Habilitationsschriften</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Habilitation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>