<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>oai:elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de:492</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:54:540</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="de">Untersuchungen zur Darstellung von Iminozuckersystemen auf Nojirimycinbasis über zentrale Bausteine</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Ostrowski, Jens</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2002-05-28</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fb09/diss2001/ostrowski</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=492</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20020200</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-587/d090116.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;p style="TEXT-ALIGN: justify"&gt;As carbohydrates are important for a large&#13;
variety of biological functions, the development of specific inhibitors of&#13;
glycosidases and glycosyl transferases has become a major field for synthetic&#13;
organic chemists. One group of these inhibitors is known as iminosugars. These&#13;
resemble normal sugar molecules, except that the ring oxygen is replaced by&#13;
nitrogen.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p style="TEXT-ALIGN: justify"&gt;In this thesis the bicyclic compound “Aza-&lt;i&gt;iso&lt;/i&gt;-levoglucosenone”&#13;
&lt;b&gt;42&lt;/b&gt; is envisioned as a flexible key compound that offers the opportunity&#13;
to synthesize a large variety of polyhydroxylated piperidines of the&#13;
nojirimycin type. The structure of &lt;b&gt;42&lt;/b&gt; is reminiscent of another&#13;
“Building-Block” often used in the synthesis of natural products, the&#13;
well-known &lt;i&gt;iso&lt;/i&gt;-levoglucosenone. Its functionality is derived from a&#13;
structurally biased rigid bicyclic framework. The 1,6-anhydro bridge supersedes&#13;
the necessity for protecting groups at the anomeric carbon and the primary&#13;
hydroxy group at C-6. Furthermore the β-D-face of the molecule is&#13;
hindered. This selectivity, observed in &lt;i&gt;iso&lt;/i&gt;-levoglucosenone, is also&#13;
present in compound &lt;b&gt;42&lt;/b&gt; and augments its great potential as a versatile&#13;
key compound.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p style="TEXT-ALIGN: justify"&gt;&lt;b&gt;42&lt;/b&gt; was synthesized by a novel route starting from furyl glycine which gave&#13;
access to the molecule in large quantities. &lt;b&gt;42&lt;/b&gt; could be functionalized&#13;
by several transformations of the carbonyl group and the double bond as well.&#13;
From these reactions a large number of precursors for iminosugars could be&#13;
obtained.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p style="TEXT-ALIGN: justify"&gt;In the second part, several routes were&#13;
developed to known and unknown iminosugars of the nojirimycin type. The first&#13;
synthesis demonstrates the application of &lt;b&gt;42&lt;/b&gt; to the facile preparation&#13;
of the known 1-deoxygulonojirimycin in only eight steps which is one of&#13;
shortest synthesis ever published.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p style="TEXT-ALIGN: justify"&gt;In the second preparation racemic &lt;b&gt;143&lt;/b&gt; is&#13;
obtained in only three steps from &lt;b&gt;42&lt;/b&gt;. This molecule represents a new&#13;
potential glycosidase inhibitor with an interesting substitution pattern at C-4&#13;
and is the first member of a new family of nojirimycin derivatives.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p style="TEXT-ALIGN: justify"&gt;Finally the first synthesis of enantiopure (+)-&lt;b&gt;148&lt;/b&gt;&#13;
is developed. The key step is a stereoselective addition of benzyl alcohol to&#13;
the double bond. Reduction and deprotection led to&#13;
(+)-1,3-dideoxygulonojirimycin &lt;b&gt;148&lt;/b&gt; in only five steps. Potentially this&#13;
reaction sequence could be modified to enable the synthesis of all four isomers&#13;
of this class.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p style="TEXT-ALIGN: justify"&gt;In summary it could be shown that &lt;b&gt;42&lt;/b&gt;&#13;
provides multiple paths to hydroxylated piperidine compounds of nojirimycin&#13;
type.&lt;/p&gt;</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 540 Chemie » 540 Chemie und zugeordnete Wissenschaften</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Chemie » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>