<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>oai:elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de:1403</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:54:540</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="de">LC-MS/MS-Methoden zur Rückstandsanalyse von Penicillinen, Cephalosporinen und Aminoglycosid-Antibiotika</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Becker, Matthias</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2018-01-22</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/chemie/diss2005/becker</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=1403</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20050106</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-1500/dc0501.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">In today’s livestock farming and milk production, therapeutic, metaphylactic and prophylactic use&#13;
of ß-lactams (penicillins, cephalosporins) and aminoglycosides is inevitable. However, improper&#13;
use of these antibiotics may lead to residues in milk and edible tissues and can cause human&#13;
health hazards as well as technological problems in dairy industry. In general, antibiotics are&#13;
unwanted components in food, and it has to be ensured that the consumer is not exposed to&#13;
antibiotic residues at potentially harmful concentrations, i.e., above maximum residue limits&#13;
(MRLs) according to Council Regulation (EEC) 2377/90. Therefore, efficient analytical methods&#13;
are required to identify and to reliably quantify residues of these antibiotics.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;In this study, sensitive and selective liquid chromatographic-tandem mass spectrometric (LCMS/&#13;
MS) methods were developed for fifteen ß-lactams (penicillins, cephalosporins) in bovine&#13;
milk, muscle and kidney, for four aminoglycosides in bovine kidney and for the cephalosporin&#13;
ceftiofur in bovine milk. Electrospray ionisation (ESI) proved to be suitable for the generation of&#13;
positively ([M+H]&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;) and negatively charged ([M-H]&lt;sup&gt;-&lt;/sup&gt;) gas phase ions for all compounds studied.&#13;
The negative electrospray ionisation mode (ESI (-)) allowed a more sensitive analysis of the&#13;
monobasic penicillins and the cephalosporin cefoperazone than the positive mode. All other&#13;
compounds were measured with higher sensitivity using the positive electrospray ionisation mode&#13;
(ESI (+)).&#13;
&lt;br&gt;It was demonstrated that the ESI-mode leading to higher sensitivity was predictable by the&#13;
Henderson-Hasselbalch equation considering the substance specific pKs and the pH of the&#13;
eluent used for the chromatography. Collision induced dissociation (CID) with argon was used for&#13;
fragmentation of the pseudomolecular ions to achieve the required selectivity for substance&#13;
specific identification.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;By using the LC-MS/MS technique, it was possible to reduce the complexity of the required cleanup&#13;
procedures to a minimum of what is necessary with less selective methods.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;The fifteen ß-lactams were extracted from the food samples with acetonitrile/water and cleanedup&#13;
by a single reversed-phase solid phase extraction (SPE) step. Ceftiofur-related residues,&#13;
bound to milk proteins, were liberated using dithioerythritol, then derivatized with iodacetamide&#13;
and cleaned-up by a single reversed-phase SPE step. With the aminoglycosides it was sufficient&#13;
to apply a simple ultrafiltration step for clean-up prior to the LC-MS/MS analysis.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;A polar deactivated phenylether HPLC column was applicable for the chromatographic separation&#13;
of all ß-lactams in the reversed-phase mode as well as for the chromatographic separation of the&#13;
highly polar aminoglycosides in the hydrophilic interaction liquid chromatographic mode (HILIC).&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Adverse effects on the ESI caused by co-eluting endogenous matrix components were&#13;
investigated. Considerable signal suppression or enhancement effects could be observed for&#13;
most of the compounds studied. The results demonstrated that these matrix effects depend highly&#13;
on the type of matrix.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The methods for the ß-lactam antibiotics were validated closely to the EU requirements laid down&#13;
in Commission Decision 2002/657/EC. Incurred ß-lactam and aminoglycoside residues in 24&#13;
samples from official food control, tested positive with a class-specific receptor test (Charm IItest),&#13;
were identified and quantitatively analyzed using the developed LC-MS/MS methods.&#13;
Benzylpenicillin and dihydrostreptomycine were the most prevalent residues. Furthermore, a cow&#13;
suffering from postpartum metritis was treated with Excenel&lt;sup&gt;®&lt;/sup&gt; RTU, containing ceftiofur&#13;
hydrochloride as active component for 3 days. All milk samples obtained during medication were&#13;
analyzed quantitatively.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;CID-fragmentation studies were carried out on ceftiofur and desfuroylceftiofur using a triple&#13;
quadrupole and an ion-trap mass spectrometer to allow the postulation of fragmentation&#13;
pathways for these compounds.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 540 Chemie » 540 Chemie und zugeordnete Wissenschaften</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Chemie » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>