<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>oai:elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de:296</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:53:530</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="de">Messung und Modellierung von Gezeitenwellen in der mittleren Erdatmosphäre: Ergebnisse des CRISTA–Experiments</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Oberheide, Jens</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2001-04-10</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fb08/diss2000/oberheide</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=296</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20010270</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-390/d080008.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">High resolution stratospheric and mesospheric temperature measurements from the&#13;
CRyogenic Infrared Spectrometers and Telescopes for the Atmosphere (CRISTA) ex-periment&#13;
taken during the Space Shuttle missions STS 66 in November 1994 and STS 85&#13;
in August 1997 are analyzed for tidal signatures in the altitude range from 20-90 km.&#13;
Background fields corresponding to the flight conditions are deduced from the CRISTA&#13;
data and used as input to an updated version of the Global Scale Wave Model (GSWM)&#13;
that includes revised tidal heating and dissipation schemes. The CRISTA background&#13;
fields include temperature, ozone, pressure, mass density and geostrophic wind fields&#13;
(in geostrophic balance with the CRISTA temperatures). These model updates signifi-cantly&#13;
improve the agreement with the CRISTA observations at all latitudes and al-titudes.&#13;
The determination of the GSWM capability for reliable predictions of phases&#13;
and amplitudes of the migrating diurnal tide when realistic atmospheric background&#13;
conditions are used, provides some guidance in the way such models should be used&#13;
in the future. Furthermore, the understanding of the diurnal cycle of chemical active&#13;
species requires an accurate tidal prediction, due to the temperature dependencies of&#13;
the reactions and the transport processes associated with the tides.&lt;p&gt;&#13;
An examination of remaining observation/model differences shows the need for&#13;
an improved dissipation scheme in the GSWM model but also provides insight in non-linear&#13;
wave-wave coupling processes. Particularly the wind field update accounts for the&#13;
most profound model improvements. Daily maps of horizontally and vertically resolved&#13;
geostrophic wind fields are inferred from CRISTA temperature and pressure data. The&#13;
comparisons with ground based, and balloon- and rocket borne measurements show that&#13;
geostrophic wind fields taken from high spatial resolution satellite borne measurements&#13;
are a good approximation for the prevailing winds up to mesopause heights. Therefore,&#13;
they may be used as an input for further modeling efforts particularly in the mesosphere&#13;
where no wind data from standard analyses are available.&#13;
&lt;/P&gt;</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 530 Physik » 530 Physik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Physik » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>