<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>oai:elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de:4820</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:54</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="de">Konjugierte Polymere und Oligomere als Materialien für Anwendungen in hybriden und organischen Solarzellen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Zhang, Jinming</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2018-01-22</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/chemie/diss2015/zhang</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=4820</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20150518-113254-3</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-4723/dc1503.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;p&gt;This doctoral thesis deals with three subjects, namely the synthesis of nanocomposites&#13;
based on polymers and PbS as counterparts, the development of a donor-acceptor&#13;
polymer and the acquirement of a star-shaped dendrimer. All three materials show&#13;
potential use in organic solar cells. Following, the summary of the three&#13;
aforementioned subjects are presented.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
In &lt;b&gt;chapter 2&lt;/b&gt;, four copolymers &lt;b&gt;P1-P4&lt;/b&gt; were synthesized by microwave-assisted Stille&#13;
coupling reactions and characterized by means of NMR spectroscopy. A ligand&#13;
exchange procedure between polymer &lt;b&gt;P2&lt;/b&gt; and PbS nanocrystals led to the acquirement&#13;
of &lt;b&gt;NC2&lt;/b&gt;, which was investigated as donor component in a BHJ solar cell. The built&#13;
device exhibited a PCE (power conversion efficiency) of only 0.02%. Additionally,&#13;
five mixtures of &lt;b&gt; P2&lt;/b&gt;/PbS(wt%)/PC&lt;sub&gt;61&lt;/sub&gt;BM were investigated in BHJ solar cell devices.&#13;
The test trials showed a best PCE value of 0.34% for a device which active layer was&#13;
composed of a mixture of &lt;b&gt;P2&lt;/b&gt;/PC&lt;sub&gt;61&lt;/sub&gt;BM excluding PbS nanoparticles. Increasing the&#13;
amount of PbS nanocrystals, the PCE of the BHJ solar cell devices was reduced.&#13;
Based on the results of the BHJ solar cells comprising &lt;b&gt;NC2&lt;/b&gt;/PC&lt;sub&gt;61&lt;/sub&gt;BM and&#13;
&lt;b&gt;P2&lt;/b&gt;/PbS(wt%)/PC&lt;sub&gt;61&lt;/sub&gt;BM, it can be supposed that nanocomposites consisting of&lt;b&gt; P2 &lt;/b&gt;and&#13;
PbS nanocrystals influence negatively the PCE value, an aspect which should be&#13;
further investigated in terms of exploring the cause of such a diminishment.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
In the frame of &lt;b&gt;chapter 3&lt;/b&gt;, the synthesis and characterization of an alternating donoracceptor&#13;
copolymer is described, namely poly[dithienol[3,2-b:2',3'-d]pyrrole]-&lt;i&gt;alt&lt;/i&gt;-[2,2-&#13;
dihexyl-&lt;i&gt;2H&lt;/i&gt;-benzo[d]imidazole. The polymer was tested as donor component in BHJ&#13;
solar cell devices in combination to PC&lt;sub&gt;71&lt;/sub&gt;BM as the acceptor component. The best&#13;
result was obtained by preparing a polymer/PC&lt;sub&gt;71&lt;/sub&gt;BM system where the mixing ratio of&#13;
the two components in the active layer was 1:2 and an energy transformation&#13;
efficiency of 0.18% could be measured. Strategies in order to improve the&#13;
performance of the devices and optimize the morphology of the blends include the&#13;
attachment of side chains influencing solubility issues, the increase of the molecular&#13;
weight of the used polymer and the application of different solvent mixtures.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#13;
&#13;
In &lt;b&gt;chapter 4&lt;/b&gt;, a new star-shaped molecule was synthesized and characterized. The&#13;
star-arm, which is composed of a donor-acceptor-donor unity and is known in&#13;
literature, was obtained in good yields following a Suzuki coupling reaction.&#13;
Subsequent mono-bromination of the arm was followed by a Sonogashira coupling&#13;
reaction between the arm and 1,3,5-triethynylbenzene in order to end up with the starshaped&#13;
compound &lt;b&gt;S1&lt;/b&gt;. Due to its poor shape ability in organic solar cells, &lt;b&gt;S1&lt;/b&gt; could not&#13;
be investigated in terms of its implementation potential in solar cell devices. For this&#13;
reason the arms and/or the core of the star molecule had to be derivatized in order to&#13;
develop materials with more desirable properties.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 540 Chemie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Chemie » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>