<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>oai:elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de:491</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:54:540</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">Atmospheric Oxidation of Selected Aromatic Hydrocarbons</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Olariu, Romeo Iulian</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2002-01-31</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fb09/diss2001/olariu</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=491</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20020075</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-586/d090112.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">The objectives of this study were to measure the atmospheric reaction rates of dihydroxy(methyl)benzene and (methyl)benzoquinone&#13;
compounds with the OH radical and to elucidate  the atmospheric reaction mechanisms for phenol and the cresol isomers with both OH and&#13;
NO&lt;sub&gt;&lt;font size="1"&gt;3&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; radicals. The study has yielded the following results:&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&#13;
         Relative rate constants have been measured for the reactions of OH radicals with&#13;
1,2-dihydroxybenzene, 1,2-dihydroxy-3-methylbenzene, 1,2-dihydroxy-4-methylbenzene, 1,4-benzoquinone and methyl-1,4-benzoquinone.&#13;
The rate constants (in units of cm&lt;sup&gt;&lt;font size="1"&gt;3&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; molecule&lt;sup&gt;&lt;font size="1"&gt;-1&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;   s&lt;sup&gt;&lt;font size="1"&gt;-1&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;) were found to be (10.4 ± 2.1) x 10&lt;sup&gt;&lt;font size="1"&gt;-11&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; for 1,2-dihydroxybenzene;&#13;
(20.5 ± 4.3) x 10&lt;sup&gt;&lt;font size="1"&gt;-11&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and (15.6 ± 3.3) x 10&lt;sup&gt;&lt;font size="1"&gt;-11&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; for 1,2-dihydroxy-3-methylbenzene and 1,2-dihydroxy-4-methylbenzene, respectively;&#13;
(0.46 ± 0.09) x 10&lt;sup&gt;&lt;font size="1"&gt;-11&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and (2.35 ± 0.47) x 10&lt;sup&gt;&lt;font size="1"&gt;-11&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;  for 1,4-benzoquinone and methyl-1,4-benzoquinone, respectively. The present kinetic&#13;
data will improve the kinetic data base required to model the degradation mechanisms of aromatic compounds and to develop structure&#13;
reactivity relationships for OH radicals with VOCs especially for oxygenated aromatic compounds. Using the kinetic data obtained in&#13;
this study, in combination with an average tropospheric OH radical concentration of [OH] = 1.6 x 10&lt;sup&gt;&lt;font size="1"&gt;6&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; cm&lt;sup&gt;&lt;font size="1"&gt;-3&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; estimated atmospheric residence&#13;
times of the compounds due to reaction with OH radicals have been determined. From the results it can be concluded that the&#13;
1,2-dihydroxybenzenes have very short atmospheric lifetimes and probably will only influence the photochemical oxidant formation on&#13;
a local scale, whereas the benzoquinones with significantly longer lifetimes will have a more regional influence.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;         Product analyses of the OH and NO&lt;sub&gt;&lt;font size="1"&gt;3&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; radical&#13;
initiated oxidation of phenol and the cresol isomers under simulated atmospheric conditions were performed in a 1080 l quartz glass&#13;
reactor at Wuppertal University and in the EUPHORE outdoor smog chamber facility in Valencia/Spain.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;         In the case of the OH initiated oxidation of phenol (or cresols), besides the&#13;
already known nitrophenol products, new ring-retaining products were experimentally determined for the first time, namely,&#13;
1,2-dihydroxybenzene and 1,4-benzoquinone from phenol, 1,2-dihydroxy-3-methylbenzene and methyl-1,4-benzoquinone from&#13;
&lt;i&gt;ortho&lt;/i&gt;-cresol, 1,2-dihydroxy-3-methylbenzene, 1,2- dihydroxy-4-methylbenzene, methyl-1,4-benzoquinone and 3-methyl-4-nitrophenol&#13;
from &lt;i&gt;meta&lt;/i&gt;-cresol and 1,2-dihydroxy-4-methylbenzene from para-cresol.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;         From the results of the present study it can be concluded that 1,2-dihydroxy(methyl)benzenes isomers are the major gas-phase&#13;
reaction products of the OH radical initiated oxidation of phenol and the cresol isomers. Interaction of the OH - phenol and OH - cresol&#13;
adducts with O&lt;sub&gt;&lt;font size="1"&gt;2&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; will mainly lead to the formation of 1,2-dihydroxybenezenes and HO&lt;sub&gt;&lt;font size="1"&gt;2&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;. In addition, the large yields of&#13;
1,2-dihydroxybenzenes support that addition at the position &lt;i&gt;ortho&lt;/i&gt; to the OH substituent dominates. The results also support that&#13;
formation of (methyl)benzoquinone compounds, mainly via the OH addition channel. The close similarity of the nitrophenol formation&#13;
yields from phenol and cresol isomers with the fraction of overall OH radical reaction estimated to proceed by H-atom abstraction&#13;
from the OH group implies that the nitrophenol formation from phenolic compounds arises from the abstraction channel.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;         Based on the results of the product studies, general degradation mechanisms have been constructed for the OH initiated&#13;
oxidation of phenol and the cresol isomers.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#13;
         Studies of the NO&lt;sub&gt;&lt;font size="1"&gt;3&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; radical initiated oxidation of phenol and the cresol isomers have been carried out in two chamber systems:&#13;
1080 l quartz glass reactor at Wuppertal University and in the EUPHORE outdoor smog chamber facility in Valencia/Spain. The observed&#13;
oxidation products and their distribution can be used to improve the general degradation mechanism of phenol and cresol isomers towards&#13;
NO&lt;sub&gt;&lt;font size="1"&gt;3&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; radicals.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;         The products detected during this study were as follows: 2-nitrophenol and 4-nitrophenol from phenol; 6-methyl-2-nitrophenol&#13;
and 1,4-benzoquinone from &lt;i&gt;ortho&lt;/i&gt;-cresol; 3-methyl-2-nitrophenol, 3-methyl-4-nitrophenol, 5-methyl-2-nitrophenol and&#13;
methyl-1,4-benzoquinone from &lt;i&gt;meta&lt;/i&gt;-cresol; 4-methyl-2-nitrophenol from &lt;i&gt;para&lt;/i&gt;-cresol. HNO&lt;sub&gt;&lt;font size="1"&gt;3&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; has also been identified as important&#13;
co-product. The experimental results support that the degradation reactions initiated by NO&lt;sub&gt;&lt;font size="1"&gt;3&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; radicals of phenol and the cresol&#13;
isomers form large yields of HNO&lt;sub&gt;&lt;font size="1"&gt;3&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;. Formation of methyl-1,4-benzoquinone in low yield has been identified for the first time as an&#13;
oxidation product in the NO&lt;sub&gt;&lt;font size="1"&gt;3&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; radical initiated oxidation of &lt;i&gt;ortho&lt;/i&gt;- and &lt;i&gt;meta&lt;/i&gt;-cresol.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;         The results from this study show that major products from the NO&lt;sub&gt;&lt;font size="1"&gt;3&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; radical initiated reaction of phenol and cresol isomers&#13;
are mixtures of nitrophenol isomers and with low yield of methyl-1,4-benzoquinone.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;         The gas-phase reactions of the NO&lt;sub&gt;&lt;font size="1"&gt;3&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; radical with phenolic compounds have been postulated to proceed via an overall H-atom abstraction&#13;
mechanism which occurs through an NO&lt;sub&gt;&lt;font size="1"&gt;3&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; - aromatic adduct which can decompose back to reactants or to form methyl phenoxy radicals and HNO&lt;sub&gt;&lt;font size="1"&gt;3&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;.&#13;
The methyl phenoxy radicals thus formed will react with NO&lt;sub&gt;&lt;font size="1"&gt;2&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; to form nitrophenols isomers. The results of the present study show that&#13;
the abstraction reaction pathway leading to the phenoxy radical accounts for about 75 - 95% of the overall reaction of phenolic&#13;
compounds with NO&lt;sub&gt;&lt;font size="1"&gt;3&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; radicals. Consequently reaction pathways leading to ring cleavage products, if indeed taking place, will be of&#13;
minor as importance.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;         The data obtained within the present work, concerning the products of the OH and NO&lt;sub&gt;&lt;font size="1"&gt;3&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; radical initiated oxidation of phenol&#13;
and the cresol isomers, can be used to improve the knowledge on the atmospheric degradation mechanisms of aromatic hydrocarbons.&#13;
The mechanisms constructed for the degradation of phenol and cresol isomers can be incorporated into atmospheric models to obtain&#13;
more accurate estimates of production of O&lt;sub&gt;&lt;font size="1"&gt;3&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;, other photo-oxidants and HNO&lt;sub&gt;&lt;font size="1"&gt;3&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; through the photo-oxidation of aromatic compounds.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 540 Chemie » 540 Chemie und zugeordnete Wissenschaften</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Chemie » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>