<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>oai:elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de:1749</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:53:530</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="de">Scanning field emission investigations of structured CNT and MNW cathodes, niobium surfaces and photocathodes</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Navitski, Aliaksandr</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2018-01-22</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/physik/diss2010/navitski</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=1749</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20101222-111353-7</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-1908/dc1021.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">Scanning field emission (FE) investigations of structured carbon nanotube (CNT) &#13;
and metallic nanowire (MNW) cathodes, niobium surfaces and photocathodes are &#13;
reported in this thesis. A novel scanning anode FE microscope (SAFEM) has been &#13;
developed within this doctoral work. The microscope will be a part of the &#13;
systematic quality control of freshly prepared photocathodes at DESY. It is &#13;
designed to achieve dc surface fields of at least 200 MV/m and provides the &#13;
localization of field emitters with a spatial resolution of about 1 µm. Design, &#13;
control software, assembly and actual status of the microscope will be presented.&#13;
&#13;
&lt;br&gt;Varying arrays of CNT columns and blocks were fabricated by two different &#13;
chemical vapor deposition (CVD) methods. The properties of the structured cathodes &#13;
were measured by FE scanning (FESM) and scanning electron (SEM) microscopy. &#13;
Well-aligned FE from nearly 100% of the patches at electric field &#13;
&lt;10 V/µm was observed. High current capabilities of the columns up to mA and &#13;
stable currents up to 300 (100) µA for pure (TiO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; coated) CNT blocks, were &#13;
achieved. Integral FE measurements with luminescence screen (IMLS) and &#13;
processing under N&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; and O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; exposures of up to 3×10&lt;sup&gt;-5&lt;/sup&gt; mbar demonstrated rather &#13;
homogeneous current distribution and long-term stability of the CNT cathodes.&#13;
&#13;
&lt;br&gt;The cathodes containing regular patch arrays of random metallic &#13;
nanostructures, as an interesting alternative to the CNT, were fabricated by &#13;
an electrochemical deposition of Au and Pt nanowires (NW) in ion track-etched &#13;
templates and were systematically investigated with the SEM and FESM. FE with &#13;
about 90% efficiency was achieved. The current carrying capability of individual &#13;
patches, however, strongly varied between 40 nA and 90 µA. Actual current limits&#13;
are caused by heating and successive destruction of NW. Electro-thermal model  &#13;
calculations and the SEM images reveal geometrical constrictions in NW contact &#13;
region as a reason for the observed current limitations.&#13;
&#13;
&lt;br&gt;Systematic measurements of the surface roughness and local defects on high &#13;
purity Nb samples by means of optical profilometry, atomic force microscopy and &#13;
SEM, as well as their contribution to FE as measured by FESM and derived &#13;
geometrically are reported. Particulates and scratches were identified as&#13;
 potentially stronger field emitters than grain boundaries, round hills and &#13;
 holes. It was shown that the defects with electric field enhancement factor &#13;
 ß&lt;sub&gt;&lt;i&gt;E&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;  ≥ 50 for XFEL and ß&lt;sub&gt;&lt;i&gt;E&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;  ≥ 20 for ILC should be completely avoided for &#13;
 successful suppression of a parasitic FE load. Many large pits with crater-like centers &#13;
 and sharp rims found on the surface of real cavities as well as the hills and &#13;
 holes hint for problems with chemical surfaces treatments. They do not cause &#13;
 enhanced FE but have to be considered as sources of quenches and magnetic &#13;
 field limitations.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 530 Physik » 530 Physik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Physik » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>