<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>oai:elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de:503</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:54:540</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="de">Instabile Halogenphosphane FPO, FPS und PH&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;Br:&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;Erzeugung und rotationsschwingungs-spektroskopische Charakterisierung&lt;/small&gt;</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Paplewski, Peter</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2001-12-11</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fb09/diss2001/paplewski</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=503</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20010669</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-598/d090109.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="de">&lt;p&gt;In der vorliegenden Arbeit wurden die instabilen Moleküle PH&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;Br, FPO und FPS in freier Form in der Gasphase erzeugt und mittels rotationsaufgelöster IR-Spektroskopie zweifelsfrei identifiziert. Ihre Charakterisierung erfolgte durch Analyse der erhaltenen Rotations-Schwingungsspektren und der Millimeterwellenspektren.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Hierzu wurde PH&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;Br durch Reaktion von P&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;H&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; mit HBr generiert und erstmals FTIR-Spektren (Auflösung ca. 5 x 10&lt;sup&gt;-3&lt;/sup&gt; cm&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;) der Produkte dieser Gasphasenreaktion im Bereich von 360-1400 cm&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; aufgenommen. Bildung und Abbau von PH&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;Br verliefen wesentlich langsamer als die von analog dargestelltem PH&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;I. Während die PH-Streck- und Deformationsschwingungen vollständig durch Eduktabsorptionen verdeckt werden, konnten die beiden &lt;i&gt;a&lt;/i&gt;-Typ Grundschwingungen ν&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;  und ν&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; von PH&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;Br eindeutig registriert werden. Dennoch erschwerten Überlagerungen mit P&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;H&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;-Absorptionen die Aufnahme guter IR-Spektren im  ν&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;-Bereich von PH&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;Br.&lt;/li&gt;&#13;
&lt;li&gt;Die Rotationsanalyse der ν&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;-Bande bei 399 cm&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;, die von der ebenfalls analysierten heißen Bande 2 ν&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;-ν&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; begleitet wird, ermöglichte die Bestimmung der Rotations-und Schwingungsparameter der offensichtlich ungestörten &lt;i&gt;v&lt;/i&gt;&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; = 1 und 2 Zustände.&lt;/li&gt;&#13;
&lt;li&gt;Die Analyse der ν&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;-Bande bei 812 cm&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; war angesichts der verfügbaren Spektrenqualität äußerst schwierig. Die erhaltenen, schließlich voll befriedigenden Ergebnisse bestätigten die vorausgesagten Coriolisstörungen durch das nicht direkt beobachtete ν&lt;sub&gt;6&lt;/sub&gt; Niveau bei 795 cm&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;, dessen Schwingungsparameter neben den ν&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;-Parametern erhalten wurden.&lt;/li&gt;&#13;
&lt;li&gt;Mit der Thermolyse der μ-Chalkogeno-bisdifluorphosphane (F&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;P)&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O und (F&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;P)&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;S in einem Ar-Trägergasstrom wurde eine neue, selektive und ergiebige Synthese für die kurzlebigen, hochreaktiven Moleküle FPO und FPS (zusammen mit PF&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;) entwickelt. (F&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;P)&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O und (F&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;P)&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;S wurden aus PF&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;I und Cu&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O bzw. HgS gewonnen.&lt;/li&gt;&#13;
&lt;li&gt;Hochaufgelöste FTIR-Spektren (Δν͂&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt; = 6-10 x 10&lt;sup&gt; -3&lt;/sup&gt; cm&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;) von FPO bzw. FPS im Bereich der Grundschwingungen ν&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; (1297.5 cm&lt;/span&gt;&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; bzw. 803.2 cm&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;) und ν&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; (819.6 cm&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; bzw. 726.3 cm&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;) wurden aufgenommen und analysiert. Neben der Bestimmung der Rotationsparameter der ν&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; und ν&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; Zustände von FPO und FPS ergab die Analyse der ν&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; und ν&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; Banden auch Schätzwerte für die Zentren der jeweiligen ν&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;-Banden von 413.2 cm&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; und 314.4 cm&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;&#13;
&lt;li&gt;Für die jeweiligen Hauptisotopomere FP&lt;sup&gt;16&lt;/sup&gt;O bzw. FP&lt;sup&gt;32&lt;/sup&gt;S wurden die Grundzustandsparameter sowie die &lt;i&gt;v&lt;/i&gt;&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; = 1 Parameter bis zu sextischen Zentrifugaldehnungstermen durch Aufnahme und Analyse von Millimeterwellenspektren im Bereich zwischen 300 und 370 GHz bestimmt. Ebenso konnten die Grundzustandsparameter von FP&lt;sup&gt;34&lt;/sup&gt;S erhalten werden.&lt;/li&gt;&#13;
&lt;li&gt;Die 1/&lt;i&gt;e&lt;/i&gt; Lebensdauern von FPO bzw. FPS, die bei einem Gesamtdruck von 8-10 Pa bei Raumtemperatur durch eine modulierte elektrische Entladung in Vorstufen/ Edelgas-Mischungen erzeugt wurden, betrugen 8 ms bzw. 2 s.&lt;/li&gt;&#13;
&lt;li&gt;Aus den Molekülkonstanten wurden weiterhin genaue experimentelle Gleichgewichtsstrukturen beider Moleküle bestimmt:&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;FPO: &lt;i&gt;r&lt;/i&gt;(PO) = 145.28(2) pm, &lt;i&gt;r&lt;/i&gt;(PF) = 157.27(1) pm, ∠(FPO) = 110.16 (2)°;&#13;
&lt;br&gt;FPS: &lt;i&gt;r&lt;/i&gt;(PS) = 188.86(4) pm, &lt;i&gt;r&lt;/i&gt;(PF) = 158.70(3) pm, ∠(FPS) = 109.28(2)°.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Diese experimentellen Daten stimmen hervorragend mit den Strukturen aus &lt;i&gt;ab initio&lt;/i&gt; Berechnungen überein. Die theoretischen Daten waren eine wesentliche Hilfe bzw. Vorraussetzung für die Identifizierung und Charakterisierung dieser Moleküle.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;p&gt;This thesis deals with the generation of the free unstable molecules PH&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; Br, FPO and FPS in the gas phase, their identification by means of rotationally resolved IR spectroscopy, and their characterization by rotational analysis of the obtained infrared and millimeter wave spectra.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;For this purpose PH&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;Br was formed by reaction of P&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;H&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; with HBr in the gas phase, and high resolution FTIR spectra (resolution ca. 5 x 10&lt;sup&gt;-3&lt;/sup&gt; cm&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;) of the products in the 360-1400 cm &lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; region have been recorded for the first time. The formation and degradation of PH&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;Br was found to be much slower than that of PH&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;I generated by the analogous reaction. While the PH stretching and bending modes were completely hidden under absorptions of the precursors, the two &lt;i&gt;a&lt;/i&gt;-type fundamentals ν&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; and ν&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; of PH&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;Br were identified unambiguously. However, the ν&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; region is seriously blended by absorptions of P&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;H&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;, and considerable efforts had to be taken in order to record reliable spectra.&lt;/li&gt;&#13;
&lt;li&gt;The ν&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; band near 399 cm&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; is accompanied by the hot band 2ν&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;-ν&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;, and the rotational and rovibrational constants of the obviously unperturbed &lt;i&gt;v&lt;/i&gt;&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; = 1 and 2 states have been obtained by rotational analysis of these bands.&lt;/li&gt;&#13;
&lt;li&gt;Owing to the limited quality of the available spectra the analysis of the ν&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; band centered at about 812 cm&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; was very difficult. However, the obtained results are completely satisfactory and confirm a predicted Coriolis perturbation of the ν&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; band by levels of ν&lt;sub&gt;6&lt;/sub&gt; located near 795 cm&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;. Although no absorptions of ν&lt;sub&gt;6&lt;/sub&gt; were observed in the spectra its vibrational parameters were obtained in addition to the parameters of ν&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;&#13;
&lt;li&gt;A new, selective and convenient route (with side product PF&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;) to the short-lived, elusive species FPO and FPS was developed by pyrolysis of the μ-chalkogeno-bisdifluorophosphines (F&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;P)&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O and (F&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;P)&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;S, respectively, in a flow of Ar carrier gas. (F&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;P)&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O and (F&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;P)&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;S were prepared by the reaction of PF&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;I with Cu&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O and HgS, respectively.&lt;/li&gt;&#13;
&lt;li&gt;High resolution FTIR spectra (Δν͂&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt; = 6-10 x 10&lt;sup&gt;-3&lt;/sup&gt; cm&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;) of FPO and FPS covering the fundamentals ν&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; (1297.5 cm&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; and 803.2 cm&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;) and ν&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;(819.6 cm&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; and 726.3 cm&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;) were recorded and analyzed. Rotational parameters of the ν&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; and ν&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; states of FPO and FPS were obtained as well as estimated values for the band centers of the ν&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; bands at 413.2 cm&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; and 314.4 cm&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;&#13;
&lt;li&gt;Ground state as well as &lt;i&gt;v&lt;/i&gt;&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; = 1 parameters up to sextic centrifugal distortion terms were obtained for the main isotopic species FP&lt;sup&gt;16&lt;/sup&gt;O and FP&lt;sup&gt;32&lt;/sup&gt;S, respectively, through analysis of their millimeter wave spectra in the 300-370 GHz region. Furthermore the ground state parameters of FP&lt;sup&gt;34&lt;/sup&gt;S could be determined analogously.&lt;/li&gt;&#13;
&lt;li&gt;The 1/&lt;i&gt;e&lt;/i&gt; lifetimes of FPO and FPS generated by modulated electric discharges in precursor / noble gas (1:20) mixtures at total pressures of 8-10 Pa were 8 ms and 2 s, respectively.&lt;/li&gt;&#13;
&lt;li&gt;Accurate experimental equilibrium structures of FPO and FPS were determined using the obtained molecular constants:&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;FPO: &lt;i&gt;r&lt;/i&gt;(PO) = 145.28(2) pm, &lt;i&gt;r&lt;/i&gt;(PF) = 157.27(1) pm, ∠(FPO) = 110.16 (2)°;&#13;
&lt;br&gt;FPS: &lt;i&gt;r&lt;/i&gt;(PS) = 188.86(4) pm,&lt;i&gt;r&lt;/i&gt;(PF) = 158.70(3) pm, ∠(FPS) = 109.28(2)°.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;These experimental structures are in excellent agreement with their &lt;i&gt;ab initio&lt;/i&gt; calculated counterparts. The availability of theoretical data facilitated the identification and characterization of these molecules in an essential manner.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 540 Chemie » 540 Chemie und zugeordnete Wissenschaften</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Chemie » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>