<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>oai:elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de:889</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:53:530</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">Enhanced Field Emission  from Metallic Surfaces and Nanowires</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Dangwal, Arti</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2007-11-07</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/physik/diss2007/dangwal</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=889</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20070849</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-995/dc0713.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">            Metallic surfaces free from enhanced field emission (EFE) are prerequisite for getting &lt;br&gt;the optimum performance of high-voltage vacuum devices such as superconducting niobium &lt;br&gt;radiofrequency cavities for e&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;e&lt;sup&gt;-&lt;/sup&gt; accelerators. With the advancement of surface preparation&lt;br&gt; and cleaning techniques, high performance of superconducting multi-cell cavities with&lt;br&gt; surface fields typically up to 50 MV/m have been achieved. However, the onset of field&lt;br&gt; emission at higher fields still imposes the limitation for future linear accelerators like the&lt;br&gt; European X-ray Free Electron Laser and International Linear Collider. Therefore, systematic&lt;br&gt; field emission investigations were performed on broad area copper and niobium cathodes by&lt;br&gt; means of dc field emission scanning microscope, which has been modernized recently for fast&lt;br&gt; scans.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
            Dry ice cleaning is found to suppress EFE from polycrystalline Cu and Nb and single&lt;br&gt; crystal Nb surfaces more efficiently than the conventionally used high pressure water rinsing.&lt;br&gt; The cleaning effects on the emitting sites were investigated up to the fields of 250 MV/m.&lt;br&gt; The number density of emitters at given fields was drastically reduced by dry ice cleaning.&lt;br&gt; Fowler-Nordheim parameters are partially discussed with respect to the morphology and&lt;br&gt; impurity content of the emitters localized by means of a high resolution scanning electron&lt;br&gt; microscope equipped with energy dispersive x-ray spectroscopy. The microscopy results&lt;br&gt; prove the effective removal of field-emitting particulates down to 400 nm as well as the&lt;br&gt; partial smoothing of surface protrusions by the use of this technique.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
            Measurements on high purity single crystal and large grain Nb samples showed the&lt;br&gt; effects of surface preparation on EFE, with its onset observed at high fields (120 – 200&lt;br&gt; MV/m), due to very smooth surfaces. A low temperature (~ 150 °C) heat treatment in high&lt;br&gt; vacuum for 14 hours on a selected large grain Nb sample gives the evidence for the grain&lt;br&gt; boundary assisted field emission at very high fields above 250 MV/m. An interesting&lt;br&gt; correlation between sizes of all investigated emitters derived from SEM images with respect&lt;br&gt; to their respective onset fields has been found, which might facilitate the quality control of&lt;br&gt; superconducting radio-frequency cavities for linear accelerators.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
            Electron field emission from nanostructures has attracted wide attention in vacuum&lt;br&gt; micro/nano-electronics. Besides various nanostructures, metallic nanowires have been&lt;br&gt; investigated for this purpose. Copper, nickel and gold nanowires of varying wire lengths,&lt;br&gt; diameters and number densities were deposited electrochemically in to the pores of etched&lt;br&gt; ion-track membrane. Electric field maps on Ni nanowire cathodes show up to 10 % of&lt;br&gt; deposited wires as emitters. Thin gold coating on Cu and Ni nanowires has improved the&lt;br&gt; cathode emission properties in terms increased emitter number density and better emission&lt;br&gt; stability. Stable Fowler-Nordheim-like emission was obtained on average up to the currents&lt;br&gt; of ~ 8 µA for individual emission site on Au coated Ni nanowire sample.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
            Au nanowire cathodes yielded up to 40% of deposited nanowires as emitters. A&lt;br&gt; controlled field enhancement ß with the small spread factor (1.23) of individual emitting sites&lt;br&gt; was achieved for thin Au nanowire cathode. The emission current density up to 78 mA/cm&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;br&gt; was obtained from agglomerated Au nanowire cathode without any current saturation. Linear&lt;br&gt; dependence of ß on electrode spacing d has been established for all Au nanowire cathodes.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 530 Physik » 530 Physik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Physik » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>