<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>oai:elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de:2607</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:54:540</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="de">Untersuchungen zur oxidativen Entfärbung ausgewählter Reaktivfarbstoffe: Analyse der Abbauprodukte mittels hochauflösender LC-MS</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Schellenträger, Marc</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2018-01-22</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/chemie/diss2006/schellentraeger</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=2607</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20120229-120927-0</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-2750/dc0612.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;p&gt;The large amount of cotton that continues to be used for textiles means that reactive dyes are&#13;
still quantitatively the most significant group of dyes. Dying cellulose textiles with reactive&#13;
dyes is always accompanied by hydrolysis of the dye. The degree to which reactive dyes are&#13;
fixed to the cellulose fibre is between 70 and 95 %. The dye hydrolysates negatively affect the&#13;
wet fastness of the dyed textile. For this reason they have to be removed from the textile in an&#13;
extensive washing process, which means a high consumption of water, energy and time. The&#13;
resulting colour in the wastewater prevents both direct water recycling in textile finishing and&#13;
discharge into a sewer. Decolourisation of the wastewater is thus necessary. If it is possible to&#13;
attain a sufficient level of decolourisation, the water can be reused in the finishing process;&#13;
this recycling means a great reduction in the necessary chemicals, energy and time.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;This work describes the oxidative degradation of selected reactive dyes. The chemical&#13;
oxidative degradation with peroxodisulphate and an enzymatically catalysed oxidative&#13;
reaction (Baylase&lt;sup&gt;®&lt;/sup&gt; RP) are examined. To this end, certain commercial reactive dyes with&#13;
typical chromophores and anchor groups were chosen; these were provided to us in the form&#13;
of trade products with an exact declaration of the content of auxiliary substances. Three of&#13;
these dyes, called Black C, Yellow D and Red F, were used in extensive investigations of the&#13;
intermediates and products of oxidative degradation.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;After textile finishing, the dyes in the wastewater are present in the hydrolysed form, so that a&#13;
procedure for the quantitative hydrolysis of the dyes had to be worked out. It was possible to&#13;
hydrolyse the anchor groups without cleaving the chromophoric system.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;The redox potential of peroxodisulphate depends on the pH value of the solution and is large&#13;
enough to oxidize chloride to chlorine or hypochlorite. In the beginning of the work the&#13;
question arose as to whether oxidation in the presence of chloride, an important component in&#13;
dye-baths or wash-waters, leads to contamination with chlorinated aromatic compounds. For&#13;
this study, 1-naphthol was used as a model compound; an excess of chloride was added to it,&#13;
and the mixture was treated oxidatively. At pH values of 11 and above, no chlorinated&#13;
aromatic compounds were found among the oxidation products. The results were quite&#13;
different in acidic milieu, where a large number of chlorinated aromatic compounds were&#13;
formed. To prevent additional dangers for the environment, oxidative degradation with&#13;
peroxodisulphate thus has to take place in alkaline solution. All further studies were carried&#13;
out in the presence of the amount of base needed to neutralise the protons arising during the&#13;
reaction with peroxodisulphate.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;After the oxidation took place, the concentration of the intermediates was low. To improve&#13;
detection, the products were first enriched by solid-phase extraction; this also separated them&#13;
into polar and moderately polar fractions. The main moderately polar compounds were&#13;
characterised by reversed-phase chromatography with a UV/VIS diode array detector or by&#13;
mass spectrometry (LC-QTof with ESI). Precision masses, with in most cases deviations of =&#13;
5 ppm from the theoretical value (W-mode with phosphoric acid as an internal standard), led&#13;
in combination with plausibility considerations to proposals for the structures. These results&#13;
were supported in some cases by NMR spectra (&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;H- and &lt;sup&gt;13&lt;/sup&gt;C-NMR) of isolated degradation&#13;
products (preparative HPLC).&#13;
&lt;br&gt;The oxidative treatment of the hydrolysates led to intermediates in low concentrations. Only&#13;
in a few cases was further reaction of the intermediates slower than the degradation of the&#13;
hydrolysates themselves; in these cases products were observed to increase in concentration,&#13;
at least for a short time.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;At a point where the values required in supplement 38 of the German Waste Water regulation&#13;
(Abwasserverordnung) with 7 m&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; (λ = 436 nm), 5 m&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; (λ = 525 nm) and 3 m&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; (λ = 620 nm)&#13;
were satisfied, no hydrolysed dyes were detectable. The moderately polar intermediates&#13;
formed were also detectable only in traces. Mainly polar products with low molecular weights&#13;
were found.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;The structures of the intermediates based on MS and NMR data make the following&#13;
generalisations about the degradation pathway possible:&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#13;
&lt;ol&gt;• cleavage of the azo link and formation of OH, NH&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; or NO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; groups in its stead&lt;/ol&gt;&#13;
&lt;ol&gt;• loss of sulphate-ester and sulphonic-acid groups&lt;/ol&gt;&#13;
&lt;ol&gt;• loss of hydroxy-ethyl groups&lt;/ol&gt;&#13;
&lt;ol&gt;• formation of isoxazole compounds where the basic structure allows it&lt;/ol&gt;&#13;
&lt;br&gt;Comparison of the oxidation methods examined (with peroxodisulphate and Baylase&lt;sup&gt;®&lt;/sup&gt; RP)&#13;
showed two main differences, the speed of decolourisation on the one hand and the number of&#13;
observed degradation products on the other. Peroxodisulphate was proved to be very effective&#13;
for rapid decolourisation of dye hydrolysates: complete decolourisation, even of heavily&#13;
coloured samples, could be achieved within a few minutes. Baylase&lt;sup&gt;®&lt;/sup&gt; RP turned out to be&#13;
slower, decolourisation sometimes taking hours. The reason for this can be found in the&#13;
different pathways of decolourisation, radical vs. enzymatic mechanisms.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;The two oxidative methods differ in the number of degradation products formed. In spite of a&#13;
ten-fold greater amount of dye, oxidation with peroxodisulphate led to only a few detectable&#13;
degradation products. The enzymatic system generates a huge number of products, which can&#13;
be used to elucidate the dyes’ decomposition route. Studies with Baylase&lt;sup&gt;®&lt;/sup&gt; RP and a higher&#13;
concentration of dye (1 g L&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;) showed fewer degradation products, as with the chemical&#13;
oxidation with peroxodisulphate. It is possible that the surprisingly small number of products&#13;
is due less to the oxidation method than to some mass-spectrometric discrimination.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 540 Chemie » 540 Chemie und zugeordnete Wissenschaften</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Chemie » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>