<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>oai:elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de:808</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:54:540</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="de">Modifizierung und Anwendung einer kapillar- elektrophoretischen Methode zur Bestimmung  des genomweiten Methylierungsgrades</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Thiemann, Markus</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2008-11-20</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/chemie/diss2008/thiemann</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=808</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20080624</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-905/dc0821.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">In this work the capillary electrophoresis method developed by Schmitz for the determination of the&#13;
genome-wide DNA methylation level was used and further optimised.&lt;p&gt;&#13;
&#13;
The surplus of the fluorescence marker BODIPY FL EDA left after derivatisation leads with the method&#13;
used to fluorophoric decomposition products that produce interfering signals in the electropherogram&#13;
and after some hours' storage in the autosampler prevent the analysis of a sample. To increase the&#13;
sample throughput of the method, after the derivatisation the surplus of the fluorescence marker&#13;
was precipitated with sodium tetraphenyl borate, dissolved in dichloromethane and separated by&#13;
centrifugation from the aqueous phase, which contains the phosphoramidate to be analyzed. The sample&#13;
throughput was thereby increased from 75 to 250 analyses per week [1].&lt;p&gt;&#13;
&#13;
The method was to be used i. a. to examine whether the regulation of the methylation level is&#13;
suitable as a genotoxicity test. With &lt;i&gt;in vivo&lt;/i&gt; experiments, a significant change of the methylation&#13;
level in the small intestine and the lung of rats could be ascertained as early as 48 h after a&#13;
single application of 3-nitrobenzanthrone. &lt;i&gt;In vitro&lt;/i&gt; experiments then carried out with V79 cells&#13;
(which express cytochrome P450 enzyme) with four cancerogens showed, because of surprisingly low&#13;
DNA-adduct formation, no significant change in the methylation level. In order to understand these&#13;
unexpected results better, in collaboration with several European working groups, knock-out mice,&#13;
in which the cytochrome P450 was inactivated, were treated with&#13;
benzo[α]pyrene (B[α]P) and their&#13;
metabolism examined. To this end an HPLC method with fluorescence detection was developed, by means&#13;
of which the clearance of B[α]P from mouse blood could be determined.&#13;
In cooperation with the other working groups it was found that, as a result of the absence of the&#13;
cytochrome P450 activity, increased DNA-adduct formation took place [2]. This is contrary to the&#13;
popular opinion that the increased level of DNA adducts results from the formation of PAH&#13;
metabolites by cytochrome P450.&lt;p&gt;&#13;
&#13;
With the new sample preparation, the DNA-methylation level in non-mammals, such as the marbled&#13;
crayfish, could also be investigated for the first time. On account of the size of these animals,&#13;
only 1-μg DNA samples could be used. The methylation level was found to correlate with the size and&#13;
weight of the animals [3].&lt;p&gt;&#13;
&#13;
Further, the first experiments were carried out which might indicate a connection between oxidative&#13;
stress and the methylation level. For this, DNA samples of Israeli combat divers who dive with&#13;
hyperbaric oxygen were compared with those of non-diving elite soldiers. However, no significant&#13;
differences could be ascertained among the samples to be analysed. Perhaps there is no correlation&#13;
between oxidative stress and the methylation level, but it is also possible that the duration of the&#13;
oxidative stress (five months) was not long enough for a definitive statement to be made.&lt;p&gt;&#13;
&#13;
To determine whether the capillary electrophoresis method for determining the genome-wide&#13;
methylation level could be used to analyse tissue from tumour banks, as well, this study&#13;
examined whether the customary fixation of tissue with formalin has an influence on the&#13;
determinable methylation level. It turned out that the methylation level of frozen kidney tissue was&#13;
about 20% lower than in kidney tissue fixed with formalin. A follow-up study was therefore designed&#13;
to look at whether the fixation time had a significant influence on the methylation level. For this,&#13;
bladder tissue from five patients was fixed for 0, 6, 12, 18, 24, 30, 36, 42 and 48 h in formalin,&#13;
and in each case the DNA methylation level was analysed. The methylation level varied greatly in&#13;
both directions. This was probably due to the inhomogeneous samples, because it was afterwards&#13;
discovered that the bladder tissue in all cases was inflamed and in two samples a tumour was even&#13;
present. Even if the results of the study indicate the problems with tissue fixation, the relevance&#13;
of the methylation level in various illnesses nevertheless becomes clear.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 540 Chemie » 540 Chemie und zugeordnete Wissenschaften</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Chemie » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>