<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>oai:elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de:6470</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:51:510</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">Modeling Systemic Risk Contribution Using Copula</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Hakwa Wemaguela, Brice</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2018-01-22</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/mathematik/diss2016/hakwa</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=6470</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20170103-113524-4</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-6232/dc1633.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;p&gt;The financial crisis of 2008 highlighted the need for better regulation mechanisms&#13;
for the stabilization of financial systems. The innovations in financial&#13;
products and the evolution of financial market technologies and operations&#13;
observed in the last decades do not only offer new opportunities but also imply&#13;
systemic risks. They contributed to the establishment of interconnected&#13;
financial systems in which the failure of certain single financial institutions&#13;
(the so-called systematically important financial institutions: SIFI) can spread&#13;
through contagion effects, thus causing the failures of other financial institutions&#13;
and threatening the stability of a financial system.&#13;
The regulatory authorities reacted to this problem by designing and implementing&#13;
various new risk management concepts and tasks, such as 1) the estimation&#13;
of the potential financial loss suffered by the financial system if a given&#13;
financial institution defaults, 2) the identification of SIFIs 3) the calculation of&#13;
individual bank’s contribution to resolution funds and 4) the elaboration and&#13;
the performance of bail-in-operations. These tasks necessitate the development&#13;
of financial risk measures that are based not only on individual losses in isolation,&#13;
as are standard risk measures such as Value-at-Risk (VaR), but also&#13;
consider loss dependency. One of the main tools proposed for this purpose is&#13;
the CoVaR-method of Brunnermeier and Adrian [2011]. The CoVaR-method&#13;
is based on the statistic CoVaR, which is defined as the VaR of one financial&#13;
system conditional on the state of a given financial institution.&#13;
The main contribution of this thesis is the development of methods for the&#13;
computation of CoVaR in a wide variety of stochastic settings. We derive,&#13;
using copula theory, a general formula for CoVaR, which takes into account&#13;
all information on the involved distribution. This allows us to consider not&#13;
only the normal but also the extreme part of the assumed distributions as well&#13;
as different types of dependency structure. We make some illustrative applications&#13;
and related analysis. Also, using the theory of elliptical distributions&#13;
we derive an expression of CoVaR that is more accessible to financial practitioners.&#13;
Both approaches allow us to consider not only Gaussian- but also&#13;
non-Gaussian distribution. Furthermore, we highlight several inconsistencies&#13;
in the CoVaR-method and suggest alternative approaches.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 510 Mathematik » 510 Mathematik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Mathematik und Informatik » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>