<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>oai:elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de:1376</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:54:540</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="de">Möglichkeiten und Grenzen des modularen Ausbaus eines Kinetik-Surface Plasmon Resonanz-Instrumentes zur quantitativen Rückstandsanalytik</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Dau, Greta</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2018-01-22</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/chemie/diss2010/dau</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=1376</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20100339</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-1473/dc1005.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">In this work, a Reichert single-channel surface plasmon resonance (SPR) apparatus, which originally&#13;
was developed for kinetic analysis, was tested in the field of residue analysis. Parallel to the&#13;
examination of the separate components this system is assembled of, these components were&#13;
improved continuously in close cooperation with the manufacturing company and, thus, adjusted to&#13;
the standards for residue analysis. For this purpose, diverse pumps, including pump syringes, were&#13;
tested and, finally, the Reichert pump SR7500 with its own software was identified as pump that&#13;
fulfilled most residue analytical needs. Similarly, maintenance, cleaning and support protocols were&#13;
developed especially for the autosampler but also for the entire system. The performance&#13;
characteristics of the Reichert system was compared to the Biacore Q apparatus, which is widely&#13;
used in routine residue analytical laboratories. While the first was advantageous with regard to&#13;
acquisition cost, the latter was superior with ease of use and reliability. The residue analytical work in&#13;
this thesis was focused on beta-lactam antibiotics with the application of direct and indirect formats&#13;
utilizing different biosensor surfaces including synthesis and characterization of different betalactam-&#13;
protein conjugates for antibody-based SPR biosensor analysis.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 540 Chemie » 540 Chemie und zugeordnete Wissenschaften</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Chemie » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>