<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>oai:elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de:8751</id><datestamp>2018-09-20</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:3:33:330</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">The Behavioral Economics of John Maynard Keynes</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Schettkat, Ronald</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2018-09-20</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=8751</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20180920-120604-6</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;p&gt;After the publication of Keynes’ “General Theory,” economics was frequently described as&#13;
schizophrenia: (neo-) classical at the micro-level, but Keynesian at the macro-level. In actuality,&#13;
Keynes’ revolution was, to a substantial part, based on the behavioral micro-foundations of the i&gt;world&#13;
we live in&lt;/i&gt;, which has been dismissed as ad hocery, or simply ignored or reclassified in the&#13;
neoclassical synthesis. Keynes’&lt;i&gt; General Theory&lt;/i&gt; is truly general. It includes the full-employment&#13;
equilibrium as a special case. In addition, its microeconomic foundations are broader than the&#13;
extremely narrow behavioral assumption of the neoclassical model. Consequently, we argue that&#13;
Keynes’ microeconomics – although not fully worked out - is actually revolutionary. This may be&#13;
difficult for (neo-) classical economists to accept, but it is strongly confirmed by the recent results in&#13;
behavioral economics. Keynes’ macroeconomics is the result of his microeconomics. Keynes’ theory&#13;
is a criticism of (neo-) classical economics, where he offers alternatives from micro to macro. It is truly&#13;
a general theory, micro and macro.&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Dateigröße: 917 KB&#13;
&#13;
&lt;p&gt;JEL COde: A1, A13, B21, B22, B31, D01, D81, D84, D9, E12, E14, E7</dc:description>
          <dc:source xml:lang="de">Schumpeter Discussion Papers&lt;br&gt;&#13;
SDP18007&lt;br&gt;&#13;
ISSN 1867-5352&lt;br&gt;&#13;
Published : September 2018</dc:source>
          <dc:subject>Keynes’ economics</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>behavioral economics</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>microeconomics</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>macroeconomics</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>knowledge</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>information</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>uncertainty</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>animal spirits</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>300 Sozialwissenschaften » 330 Wirtschaft » 330 Wirtschaft</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Wirtschaftswissenschaft/Schumpeter School of Business and Economics » Schumpeter Discussion Papers (SDP)</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Texte » Book</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>