<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>oai:elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de:939</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:6:62:620</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">A Comparative Analysis of the Public Transport Systems of Santiago de Chile, London, Berlin and Madrid: What can Santiago learn from the European Experiences?</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Gschwender, Antonio</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2007-11-08</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbd/bauingenieurwesen/diss2007/gschwender</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=939</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20070850</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-1045/dd0706.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">In 2001, 58 % of the motorised trips on a typical day were made by using public transport in&#13;
Santiago, the capital of Chile. Comparing this with its proportion in 1991 (71 %) and 1977&#13;
(83 %) a clear decline in public transport use can be seen. The improvement of the public&#13;
transport system is crucial to stop its decline in the modal split, and to accomplish a more&#13;
sustainable urban transport system (together with complementary policies: for instance car&#13;
parking restrictions, bicycle facilities). Based on positive experiences provided by three&#13;
selected European metropolitan areas (Greater London, Berlin and Madrid) and taking into&#13;
account theoretic and empirical evidence investigated by the author in previous studies and&#13;
field trips, the aim of this research is to identify and analyse aspects in which the public&#13;
transport system of Santiago de Chile can be improved. An important part of this research is&#13;
the comparison and analysis of the socio-economic and transport data of the four&#13;
metropolitan areas. During this analysis, two topics were identified and selected for further&#13;
research: the institutional organisation of public transport (transport authority) and the fare&#13;
structure of public transport.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;In the case of the transport authority, the proposed solution for Santiago is the creation of a&#13;
regional transport authority, responsible for the planning and implementation of both public&#13;
and private transport policies, strategic plans and projects. It should also be responsible for&#13;
the non-motorised modes and for urban planning and land-use definitions at the regional&#13;
level. Responsibilities from other areas different to the transportation could also be&#13;
transferred to the regional authority, as long as they have a regional scope. The regional&#13;
government should change its appointment system, in the direction of directly elected head&#13;
and representatives.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Travelcards allowing unlimited public transport use in a certain period (e.g. a month) may&#13;
have a positive impact on public transport demand. Their implementation is recommended&#13;
for Santiago. No technical problems for its introduction are detected, being the main difficulty&#13;
an eventual unwillingness at the decision-making level. The relation between the fare and&#13;
the trip-length is discussed. A mostly flat fare is recommended for Santiago. The&#13;
differentiation of fares in peak and off-peak periods is also analysed. As shown in a&#13;
numerical simulation, it is possible to increase both patronage and revenue through this&#13;
measure. The average fare in Santiago is marginally lower than in Berlin and Madrid.&#13;
Comparing it with the disposable income of the population, the public transport in Santiago is&#13;
more expensive than in London, Madrid and Berlin. Unlike the European case study areas,&#13;
the public transport system in Santiago does not receive operational subsidies. These kind&#13;
of subsides are fully justified by the economic theory in the case of urban public transport,&#13;
and also represent a clear policy decision in the direction of giving incentives to the use of&#13;
public transport. A subsidy in Santiago would be more likely, if it were not financed by fiscal&#13;
expenditure but other sources (e.g. congestion charging). A regressive cross-subsidy from&#13;
full-fare payers to the students should be eliminated, providing a compensation for the&#13;
reduced students’ fare.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;During the time of this research the public transport system of Santiago was undergoing a&#13;
major change under the name “Transantiago”. All the analyses are made assuming that&#13;
Transantiago is already implemented, i.e. the recommendations are centred in future&#13;
improvement for the new system.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>600 Technik, Medizin, angewandte Wissenschaften » 620 Ingenieurwissenschaften » 620 Ingenieurwissenschaften und zugeordnete Tätigkeiten</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Architektur und Bauingenieurwesen » Bauingenieurwesen » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>