<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>oai:elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de:5381</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:51</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">On some classes of q-plurisubharmonic functions and q-pseudoconcave sets</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Pawlaschyk, Thomas Patrick</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2018-01-22</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/mathematik/diss2015/pawlaschyk</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=5381</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20151210-101726-1</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-5186/dc1526.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;p&gt;We introduce real q-convex functions on open subsets of the real Euclidean space. We study their properties and develop approximation techniques by continuous ones and by those who are real q-convex with corners. In the smooth case, a function is real q-convex if and only if its real Hessian has at most q negative eigenvalues. We compare these functions to their complex relatives: the q-plurisubharmonic functions defined on open sets of the complex Euclidean space. We show that each real q-convex function is q-plurisubharmonic. On the converse, each q-plurisubharmonic function, which is invariant in the imaginary part, is real q-convex. Another example for q-plurisubharmonic functions is given by those which are plurisubharmonic on leaves of a singular foliation by analytic sets of codimension q.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#13;
&#13;
The q-plurisubharmonic functions are used to define q-pseudoconcave sets. These are closed subsets S of an open set D in the complex Euclidean space for which the negative logarithm of the distance function to S is q-plurisubharmonic on D minus S. We prove that (Hartogs) q-pseudoconcave graphs of certain continuous mappings locally admit a foliation by complex submanifolds of dimension q. We construct generalized convex hulls of compact sets with respect to subfamilies of q-plurisubharmonic functions and compare them to each other and to hulls already existing in the literature (such as Basener's hull or the rationally convex hull).&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt; &#13;
&#13;
We verify that the Shilov boundary of a compact set for certain families of upper semi-continuous functions exists and coincides with the set of all peak points for the given family. As an application, we study the Shilov boundary of a convex body for q-plurisubharmonic functions and generalize Bychkov's result from 1981. More precisely, the complement of the Shilov q-boundary of a convex body K consists of all boundary points p with the following property: there exists an open neighbourhood U of p in the boundary of K such that each point z in U lies in some open part of a complex plane of dimension at least q+1.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 510 Mathematik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Mathematik und Informatik » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>