<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>oai:elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de:5380</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:54</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">Exposure assessment of N-acetyl-4- aminophenol (paracetamol), the urinary major metabolite of the ubiquitous environmental contaminant aniline, with the tools of human biomonitoring</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Modick, Hendrik</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2018-01-22</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/chemie/diss2015/modick</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=5380</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20151210-085105-0</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-5185/dc1525.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;p&gt;Aniline is an important source material in the chemical industry (e.g. rubber, pesticides, and pharmaceuticals).&#13;
The general population is known to be ubiquitously exposed to aniline. Thus, assessment of aniline exposure is&#13;
of both occupational and environmental relevance. Knowledge on human metabolism of aniline is scarce. We&#13;
orally dosed four healthy male volunteers (2 fast, 2 slow acetylators) with 5 mg isotope labelled aniline,&#13;
consecutively collected all urine samples over a period of two days and investigated the renal excretion of aniline&#13;
and its metabolites by LS-MS/MS and GC-MS.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#13;
After enzymatic hydrolysis of glucuronide and sulfate conjugates, &lt;i&gt;N&lt;/i&gt;-acetyl-4-aminophenol was the predominant&#13;
urinary aniline metabolite representing 55.7-68.9% of the oral dose, followed by the mercapturic acid conjugate&#13;
of &lt;i&gt;N&lt;/i&gt;-acetyl-4-aminophenol accounting for 2.5-6.1%. Acetanilide and free aniline were found only in minor&#13;
amounts accounting for 0.14-0.36% of the dose. Overall, these four biomarkers excreted in urine over 48h post&#13;
dose represented 62.4-72.1% of the oral aniline dose. Elimination half-lives were 3.4-4.3h for &lt;i&gt;N&lt;/i&gt;-acetyl-4-&#13;
aminophenol, 4.1-5.5h for the mercapturic acid conjugate and 1.3-1.6 and 0.6-1.2h for acetanilide and free&#13;
aniline, respectively. Urinary maximum concentrations of &lt;i&gt;N&lt;/i&gt;-acetyl-4-aminophenol were reached after about 4h&#13;
hours and maximum concentrations of the mercapturic acid conjugate after about 6h, whereas concentrations of&#13;
acetanilide and free aniline peaked after about one hour.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#13;
The present study is one of the first to provide reliable urinary excretion factors for aniline and its metabolites in&#13;
humans after oral dosage, including data on the predominant urinary metabolite &lt;i&gt;N&lt;/i&gt;-acetyl-4-aminophenol, also&#13;
known as an analgesic under the name paracetamol/acetaminophen.&#13;
&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt;&#13;
KEY WORDS: Aniline, Paracetamol, Metabolism, Excretion factors, Urine, Exposure assessment</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 540 Chemie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Chemie » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>