<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>oai:elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de:4310</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:7</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">Playful Customer Experience -  Examining the Integration of Playful Aspects into the Experience of Waiting at Family Physicians’ Offices</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Khazaei, Mitra</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2018-01-22</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbf/industrialdesign/diss2014/khazaei</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=4310</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20141029-103053-8</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-4308/df1401.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">Playful customer experience is an interdisciplinary Dissertation that examines the &#13;
interplay between the three disciplines of play studies, customer experience, and&#13;
design for services, and does so with a design-thinking view. The theoretical bases are&#13;
studied and developed so that they can be applied to design solutions. After providing&#13;
an overview of the current literature on the disciplines concerned, it focuses on&#13;
examining various aspects of integrating playful characteristics into customer&#13;
experience and provides a theoretical framework for playful experience design. Based &#13;
on the theoretical findings, the application of these characteristics is examined by&#13;
conducting a multiple-case study in a real service situation. The area chosen to&#13;
analyze the experience of waiting was family physicians’ offices: How can playful&#13;
aspects be integrated into the experience of waiting? As waiting is a typical case in&#13;
everyday experiences, the results of the study can also be applied to other areas. The&#13;
findings of the theoretical and empirical studies result in principles and practical&#13;
considerations regarding how to improve the experience of waiting by means of a&#13;
playful design approach. The playful design approach concentrates on ways to&#13;
increase the playfulness of an experience. At same time it applies playful&#13;
characteristics to improve aspects of customer experience according to the particular&#13;
requirements of the service situation. The main recommendations are discussed &#13;
under five categories, explained as playful experience components. These categories&#13;
are: &lt;i&gt;the presence of children, the play zone, the playful breeze, playful active waiting&lt;/i&gt;,&#13;
and &lt;i&gt;the waiting oasis&lt;/i&gt;, each of which demonstrates aspects of the playful approach to&#13;
the enhancement of the customer experience. Finally, the research introduces the&#13;
concept of &lt;i&gt;design for play-ception&lt;/i&gt; (playful perception) as a rich and human-centered&#13;
approach to the designing of customer experience.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="de">Spielerisches Kundenerlebnis (playful customer experience) ist eine interdisziplinäre&#13;
Arbeit, die das Zusammenwirken zwischen drei Themenbereichen: die Theorien des&#13;
Spiels, die Kundenerfahrung und das Design für Dienstleistungen mit dem Design-&#13;
Thinking-Ansatz untersucht. Dabei werden theoretische Grundlagen erarbeitet und&#13;
so verarbeitet, dass sie für gestalterische Lösungen verwertbar werden. Nach einem&#13;
Überblick über die aktuelle Literatur zu den betreffenden Themenbereichen&#13;
konzentriert sich die Arbeit auf die Untersuchung derjenigen Aspekte, welche die&#13;
Integration von spielerischen Eigenschaften in Kundenerlebnisse/Kundenerfahrungen&#13;
ermöglichen. Dies ergibt dann den theoretischen Rahmen für die&#13;
Erstellung von spielerischen Kundenerlebnissen. Auf der Grundlage dieser&#13;
Theoretischen Erkenntnisse wird durch eine Multiple-Case Study die explizite&#13;
Verwertbarkeit innerhalb einer realen Service-Situation untersucht. Als&#13;
Anwendungsbereich wird das Warten in Hausarzt-Praxen gewählt: Wie können&#13;
spielerische Aspekte in die Erfahrung des Wartens integriert werden? Warten ist ein&#13;
typischer Fall in Alltagserfahrungen, die Ergebnisse lassen sich deshalb auf viele&#13;
andere Bereiche übertragen. Die Ergebnisse der theoretischen und empirischen&#13;
Studien führen schließlich zu Grundlagen und praktischen Überlegungen für&#13;
mögliche Verbesserungen der Erlebnisse/Erfahrungen bezüglich des Wartens durch&#13;
einen spielerischen Design–Ansatz. Der spielerische Design-Ansatz konzentriert sich&#13;
auf verschiedene Möglichkeiten, die dabei helfen, die Spielerischen Eigenschaften&#13;
einer Erfahrung zu erhöhen, und untersucht zugleich auch, wie die Anwendung von&#13;
spielerischen Eigenschaften dazu beitragen kann, Kundenerfahrungen gemäß&#13;
Erfordernissen bestimmter Service-Situationen zu verbessern. Die wichtigsten&#13;
Empfehlungen werden unter fünf Komponenten diskutiert: &lt;i&gt;die Anwesenheit von&#13;
Kindern&lt;/i&gt;, die &lt;i&gt;Spielzone&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;die spielerische Brise&lt;/i&gt;, das spielerische aktive Warten&lt;/i&gt;, und die&#13;
&lt;i&gt;Warten-Oase&lt;/i&gt;. All diese Aspekte des spielerischen Umgangs zeigen Verbesserungen&#13;
der Kundenerfahrung. Letztlich stellt die Arbeit das Konzept des &lt;i&gt;Design für Play-&#13;
Ception&lt;/i&gt; (von Playful Perception) als einen nachhaltigen und menschenzentrierten &#13;
Ansatz für die Gestaltung von Kundenerlebnissen/ Kundenerfahrungen vor.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>700 Künste und Unterhaltung</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Design und Kunst » Industrial Design » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>