<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>oai:elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de:4410</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:54</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="de">Molekulare Erkennung von kleinen GTPasen der Ras-Superfamilie</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Düppe, Peter Markus</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2018-01-22</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/chemie/diss2014/dueppe</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=4410</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20141117-104956-5</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-4393/dc1425.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;p&gt;In 30 % of all human tumors are point mutations of Ras proteins, which lead to a loss &#13;
of the intrinsic and GAP-stimulated GTPase activity. Cause of the occurence of &#13;
oncogenic Ras mutations in these proteins encoding genes, these proteins become &#13;
oncogene. In this work, two ways were chosen for the disturbance of the oncogene Ras: &#13;
The identification of the ligands for the recognition of protein surfaces and the &#13;
synthesis of artificial receptors for the C-termini of proteins.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&#13;
The first part of this dissertation describes the development of a new head group for &#13;
peptide receptor libraries (based on an published synthesis by Anslyn et al.). The &#13;
association constants with carboxylate were determined in the range of 165-731 M-1 &#13;
(100% d6-DMSO). These constants decrease strongly with increasing water content &#13;
of the solvent.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
The second part deals with the synthesis and the screening of combinatorial libraries &#13;
of artificial receptors as well as their characterisation. The head group of Schmuck et &#13;
al. has a better affinity to carboxylates, for which reason this was used for the &#13;
synthesis of the receptor libraries. The resulting receptors showed affinity to the &#13;
target molecules, the C-terminal CaaX-peptides of the Ras proteins. The associated &#13;
association constants are determined in an organic solvent as well as in an &#13;
aquaeous solvent.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
The last part of this thesis consists of the screening and the identification of ligands &#13;
for the surface of the Ras proteins. Through the investigation of less than 100 &#13;
compounds, binding ligands of Rheb protein were identified in the lower millimolare &#13;
range: bisphenol A and 4,4'-biphenol. These bind with a KD of 1800 +/- 500 and 1500 &#13;
+/- 200 µM in one of the switch-II-region adjacent binding pocket. Bisphenol A binds &#13;
with greater affinity to the K-Ras4B protein (KD = 600 +/- 200 µM).</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 540 Chemie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Chemie » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>