<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>oai:elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de:868</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:53:530</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">Proton Induced Fragmentation of Gold Nuclei at Incident Energy of 2.5 GeV</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Bollini, Virginie</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2005-06-20</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/physik/diss2004/bollini</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=868</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20050175</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-974/dc0419.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="de">This thesis is concerning the presentation of the PISA experiment which the subject is the proton&#13;
induced reaction on gold at proton energy 2.5 GeV. Energy spectra have been measured at 3 different&#13;
angles: 35, 50 and 100° for Light Charged Particles (LCP, Z=2) and Intermediate Mass Fragments&#13;
(IMFs, 3≤Z≤8) produced in the mentioned reaction. The PISA experimental setup and the particle&#13;
identification method using silicon detectors are described. Emphasis has been put on measuring a&#13;
broad kinetic energy range of emitted particles as well as on isotope separation.  Different&#13;
theoretical approaches (INCL4.2+GEM model, moving source fit and Fisher's droplet model) are used&#13;
and are shown in order to try to describe the reaction mechanism responsible for the emission of&#13;
spallation products. At the end, a discussion of the results shows that production cross sections&#13;
are a great importance for models and code improvement. As for example it has been shown that&#13;
generally the emission from equilibrium processes can be well described by the INCL4.2+GEM model.&#13;
However currently there are no models on the market which are capable of describing the high energy&#13;
tails of kinetic energy distributions associated in particular with pre-equilibrium processes.&#13;
Therefore a reliable and comprehensive experimental data base for p-induced reactions should be&#13;
extended by further experimental investigations in the future in order to allow benchmarking of&#13;
newly developed models.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 530 Physik » 530 Physik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Physik » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>