<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>oai:elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de:2345</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:54:540</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="de">Konjugierte Donor-Akzeptor-Oligomere und -Polymere</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Breusov, Dietrich</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2018-01-22</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/chemie/diss2011/breusov</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=2345</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20111102-103227-3</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-2500/dc1114.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;p&gt;Various factors such as rising crude oil prices and increasingly common natural disasters in&#13;
recent years have accelerated the development of renewable energies. An interesting and&#13;
promising field of renewable energies is represented by the solar technology. Organic and&#13;
polymeric devices such as organic photovoltaics (OPVs) have attracted significant academic&#13;
and commercial interest for application in low-cost devices. Conjugated copolymers and&#13;
oligomers composed of electron-rich (donor) and electron-poor (acceptor) building blocks are&#13;
the focus of intensive research activities as photo active materials for OPVs. This approach&#13;
can also be used for applications both in organic light emitting diodes (OLEDs) and organic&#13;
field effect transistors (OFETs).&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;In &lt;i&gt;chapter 2&lt;/i&gt;, a series of donor-acceptor oligomers (D-A-oligomers) with different aromatic&#13;
acceptor units will be described. The oligomers function as model compounds for the&#13;
corresponding, well-known polymers with promising electronic properties. The central goal&#13;
of designing oligomers is an improved understanding of electronic properties of active&#13;
organic layers in organic solar cells including their interfaces. Another objective of the&#13;
development of the oligomers above is their potential use as dopants or sensitizers in organic&#13;
solar cells or light-emitting diodes.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;i&gt;Chapter 3&lt;/i&gt; deals with novel &lt;b&gt;CPDTz&lt;/b&gt;-polymers (CPDTz ≡ 7,7-dialkyl-7&lt;i&gt;H&lt;/i&gt;-cyclopenta[1,2-&#13;
d:4,3-d']dithiazole-2,5-diyl) and their use as active layer in “bulk-hetrojunction”-type solar&#13;
cells. The substitution of &lt;b&gt;CPDT&lt;/b&gt; (4,4-dialkyl-4&lt;i&gt;H&lt;/i&gt;-cyclopenta[1,2-b:5,4-b']dithiophen-2,6-diyl)&#13;
by &lt;b&gt;CPDTz&lt;/b&gt; allows some fine tuning of opto-electronical properties.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;i&gt;Chapter 4&lt;/i&gt; presents the investigation of selenium containing donor-acceptor (D-A) copolymers&#13;
with respect to an application in near-infrared OLEDs (NIR-OLEDs). These selenium based&#13;
polymers were investigated as emitters in the active layer of NIR-OLED-devices both with&#13;
and without host molecules.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Finally, synthesis and characterization of the novel &lt;b&gt;CPDT&lt;/b&gt;-based “low bandgap” polymers are&#13;
introduced in the &lt;i&gt;chapter 5&lt;/i&gt;.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;All the materials synthesized during this work were intensively analyzed by spectroscopic&#13;
methods. Many of the final products were tested as semiconducting layer in OPV devices or&#13;
NIR-OLEDs.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 540 Chemie » 540 Chemie und zugeordnete Wissenschaften</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Chemie » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>