<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>oai:elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de:6860</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">Research approach for individual team composition for the improvement of the application situation of methods in the area of design methodology</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Gust, Peter</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Garbe, Marie</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Kuhlmeier, Marco</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2018-01-22</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=6860</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20170502-111652-8</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-6680/ResearchApproachForIndividualTeamComposition.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;p&gt;A success factor for product development is the application of a design methodology.&#13;
Numerous studies have shown the advantages, including shorter development times and&#13;
reduced costs. However, other studies have shown that design methodology is often not (or&#13;
only inadequately) applied. The reasons for this are diverse. One reason is that design&#13;
methodology is considered very time-consuming, since the methods first have to be introduced&#13;
and explained, and employees have to be qualified. This leads to a further argument for&#13;
rejection, the assumption that the application is expensive. But the opposite is the case.&#13;
Methodology, however, cannot be seen as a panacea, and some methods no longer&#13;
correspond to the state of science. In addition, methods are often too rigid and difficult to adapt&#13;
to operational needs. One factor for this is the number of available employees, which is often&#13;
in conflict with the team sizes stipulated by scientific sources. To meet this discrepancy, this&#13;
paper presents a research approach that deals with the individualization of team sizes. Various&#13;
factors influencing team performance are described; these must be examined for their&#13;
relevance. The paper describes a process under development, which is intended to provide&#13;
an objective assessment of individual employees and an optimal team composition. In addition,&#13;
the actuality of methods has to be critically examined.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Maschinenbau und Sicherheitstechnik » Maschinenbau » Veröffentlichungen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Texte » WorkingPaper</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>