<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>oai:elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de:532</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:54:540</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="de">Synthese von Naturstoffen auf Inositolbasis ausgehend von para-Benzochinon</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Podeschwa, Michael Alois Linus</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2003-12-19</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fb09/diss2003/podeschwa</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=532</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20030485</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-628/d090306.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">Cyclitols, polyhydroxylated five- and six-membered carbocycles, are isolated from natural sources as single compounds or as part of more complex structures and play key functions in biological systems. Especially during the last two decades, a new level of attention was focused on inositol phosphates after the discovery, in 1983, that &lt;i&gt;myo&lt;/i&gt;-inositol-1,4,5-trisphosphate (Ins(1,4,5)P&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;) is a Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt;-mobilizing second messenger.&#13;
&lt;p&gt;In this work a &lt;i&gt;de novo&lt;/i&gt; strategy for the preparation of inositol derivatives is presented. Starting from &lt;i&gt;p&lt;/i&gt;-benzoquinone, optically pure compounds in both forms can be prepared easily via enzymatic resolution of derived diacetoxy conduritol B yielding the building blocks of this concept. &#13;
&lt;p&gt;In the first part, several &lt;i&gt;myo&lt;/i&gt;-inositol phosphates were synthesized by use of either a &lt;i&gt;C&lt;/i&gt;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;-symmetrical or a non-symmetrical approach. Among others, a new, very short and effective route to &lt;i&gt;myo&lt;/i&gt;-Ins(1,3,4,5)P&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;, &lt;i&gt;myo&lt;/i&gt;-Ins(1,2,3,4,5)P&lt;sub&gt;5&lt;/sub&gt;, &lt;i&gt;myo&lt;/i&gt;-Ins(1,2,4,5,6)P&lt;sub&gt;5&lt;/sub&gt;, &lt;i&gt;myo&lt;/i&gt;-Ins(1,2,3,5,6)P&lt;sub&gt;5&lt;/sub&gt; and &lt;i&gt;myo&lt;/i&gt;-Ins(2,3,4,5,6)P&lt;sub&gt;5&lt;/sub&gt; is presented. &#13;
&lt;p&gt;The second part further emphasizes the potential of this &lt;i&gt;de novo&lt;/i&gt; approach in the construction of non-racemic inositol phosphate derivatives. The obtained azido-conduritols were transformed into several azido-&lt;i&gt;myo&lt;/i&gt;-inositols on a multigram scale without the need for chromatographic separation. The described efficient, high-yielding routes allowed the introduction of nitrogen-containing functional groups in 1-, 3-, 4- and 6-position of the cyclitol ring system to give several pure azido- and amino-&lt;i&gt;myo-&lt;/i&gt;inositols in both enantiomeric forms. &#13;
&lt;p&gt;In the third chapter a practical route is described for the preparation of a wide variety of enantiomerically pure inositol isomers. The potential of this concept is demonstrated by easy synthesis of &lt;i&gt;myo&lt;/i&gt;-, &lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;span lang=EN-GB style="FONT-SIZE: 11pt; mso-ansi-language: EN-GB"&gt;L&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span lang=EN-GB style="mso-ansi-language: EN-GB"&gt;-&lt;i&gt;chiro&lt;/i&gt;-, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span lang=EN-GB style="FONT-SIZE: 11pt; mso-ansi-language: EN-GB"&gt;D&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span lang=EN-GB style="mso-ansi-language: EN-GB"&gt;-&lt;i&gt;chiro&lt;/i&gt;-, &lt;i&gt;scyllo&lt;/i&gt;-, &lt;i&gt;epi&lt;/i&gt;-, &lt;i&gt;allo&lt;/i&gt;- and &lt;i&gt;neo&lt;/i&gt;-inositol derivatives. &#13;
&lt;p&gt;In the fourth chapter a new synthetic approach is described for the preparation of branched cyclitols from conduritol B by stereoselective hydroformylation, thereby extending the synthetic potential of the versatile building blocks by transforming them in two steps into carbasugar systems.&#13;
&lt;p&gt;To demonstrate the potential of this versatile approach Mycothiol, a GSH-similarity on inositolbasis, is synthesized by a new and diastereoselective access in the last chapter.&lt;/p&gt;</dc:description>
          <dc:source xml:lang="de">Datei d090306.pdf ohne experimentellen Teil (ursprüngliche Fassung)&#13;
&#13;
Datei d090306a.pdf mit experimentellen Teil (Fassung vom 02.05.2005)</dc:source>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 540 Chemie » 540 Chemie und zugeordnete Wissenschaften</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Chemie » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>