<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>oai:elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de:419</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:54:540</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="de">Chalkonhaltige Polymere</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="de">&lt;font size="1"&gt;Synthese, Charakterisierung und Photochemie von chalkonhaltigen Kammpolymeren sowie Oxidationspolymerisation von Aminochalkonen&lt;/font&gt;</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Goretzki, Christian</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2001-02-08</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fb09/diss2000/goretzki</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=419</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20010100</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-513/d090026.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">The first part of the present work describes the synthesis, characterization and the&#13;
&lt;br&gt;photochemical behaviour of new comb-like polymers bearing chalcone (1,3-&#13;
&lt;br&gt;diphenyl-2-propen-1-one) groups in the side chains. The photochemical analysis of&#13;
&lt;br&gt;these polymers showed that homopolymers, in which the chalcone group is directly&#13;
&lt;br&gt;attached to the main chain, showing only the E/Z-isomerization during the irradiation&#13;
&lt;br&gt;with UV-light; while building in MMA-units in the chain, retardet the reaction. Building&#13;
&lt;br&gt;in different spacers between the main chain and the chalcone group, causes the&#13;
&lt;br&gt;polymers with 5- respectively 7 CH&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt;-units to be done during the irradiation&#13;
&lt;br&gt;a E/Z-isomerization and a [2+2]-photocycloaddition.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;    Further could the synthesis of a polyrotaxan with radical polymerization be&#13;
&lt;br&gt;realized. The prove of the existence of the complex would be realized with the help&#13;
&lt;br&gt;of NMR-spectroscopy and FAB-measurement. The comparison of the complex with a&#13;
&lt;br&gt;model compound showed prominent signal shifts, different solutionsattributs and a&#13;
&lt;br&gt;differenciated thermical behaviour, too. The photochemical analysis demonstated&#13;
&lt;br&gt;also that the complex did only the isomerization during the irradiation with UV-light,&#13;
&lt;br&gt;while the model compound showed beside also a crosslinking reaction.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;    The radical polymerisation of methacrylmonomers, which included the 3-(9-&#13;
&lt;br&gt;anthracenyl)-1-phenyl-2-propen-1-one group, could not be realized. This group&#13;
&lt;br&gt;inhibited in a still unknown way any chainstarting and so the polymerization.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;    The second part of the work is occupied in the enzymic polymerization of&#13;
&lt;br&gt;aminochalcons with HRP/H&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt;O&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt;. It could be shown, that proper aminochalcones,&#13;
&lt;br&gt;according to the period of reaction, react to oligomeres, polymers and insoluble&#13;
&lt;br&gt;products. These products are seen as thermicalstable polymers until ca. 300 &lt;SUP&gt;°&lt;/SUP&gt;C.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 540 Chemie » 540 Chemie und zugeordnete Wissenschaften</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Chemie » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>