<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>oai:elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de:885</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:53:530</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="de">Ein flugzeuggetragenes kryogenes Infrarotspektrometer zur Fernerkundung klimarelevanter Spurengase im Tropopausenbereich</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Kullmann, Andreas</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2007-03-13</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/physik/diss2006/kullmann</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=885</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20070137</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-991/dc0619.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">A reliable prognosis of climate change in the earth’s atmosphere as well as the distinction of&#13;
the relevant natural and anthropogenic influences is a prevailing scientific question and&#13;
necessitates a detailed understanding of energetic, dynamic and chemical processes in the atmosphere,&#13;
particularly in the tropopause region. The upper troposphere and lower stratosphere seems to proof&#13;
highly sensitive to changes in atmospheric parameters such as temperature and trace gas&#13;
distributions. Dynamic transport and exchange of chemical constituents between troposphere and&#13;
stratosphere may cause significant changes in the atmosphere’s chemical and radiative budget. In&#13;
spite of their great importance the involved processes are far from beeing well understood. To&#13;
assess the major uncertainties concerning the distribution, chemistry and radiative forcing of water&#13;
vapor, aerosols, ozone, the hydroxyl radical or the formation mechanisms of the various types of&#13;
cirrus clouds, processes ranging from synoptical scale to microscale have to be investigated&#13;
requiring different measurement techniques.&#13;
&#13;
&lt;br&gt;     While hitherto global satellite measurements are limited either by&#13;
their horizontal or vertical resolution, local in-situ instruments are limited by their little&#13;
spatial coverage. Therefore since 2003 the Research Center Jülich and the University of&#13;
Wuppertal have cooperated in the development of a new limb sounding infrared instrument aboard the&#13;
high altitude research aircraft M55-Geophysika aiming at measurements in the tropopause region,&#13;
combining high vertical resolution with reasonable regional coverage. The first mission of the new&#13;
CRISTA-NF (CRyogenic Infrared Spectrometers and Telescope for the Atmosphere - New Frontiers)&#13;
instrument took place during the extensive European SCOUT-O3 (Stratosphere Climate Ozone links with&#13;
emphasis on the UTLS) measurement campaign in Darwin, Australia, in November/December 2005.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;     Here, an overview of the instrument’s measurement technique is given,&#13;
followed by descriptions of the instrument calibration, the process of data analysis and retrieval.&#13;
Using these methods a set of preliminary data from the SCOUT campaign is analyzed concerning the&#13;
distribution of clouds as well as the mixing ratios of water vapor and the chlorofluorocarbon&#13;
CFCl&lt;sub&gt;&lt;small&gt;3&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;. Simulations by the Chemical Lagrangian Model of the Stratosphere&#13;
(CLaMS) are used for comparisons with the observed situation concerning processes of transport&#13;
and mixing.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 530 Physik » 530 Physik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Physik » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>