<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>oai:elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de:805</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:54:540</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="de">Entwicklung einer Multi-Purpose Ionenquelle für die AP-MS sowie Design und Anwendung von APLI-Ionisationslabeln</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Schiewek, Ralf</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2009-01-30</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/chemie/diss2008/schiewek</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=805</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20090039</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-902/dc0825.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">Atmospheric-Pressure Laser Ionization (APLI) was developed at the University of Wuppertal&#13;
as a sensitive atmospheric-pressure ionisation method for the analysis of non-polar aromatic&#13;
hydrocarbons. The coupling of liquid chromatography (LC) with APLI was first realised with&#13;
a Q-TOF Ultima (Waters) instrument in the form of LC-APLI-(TOF)MS. Because of its great&#13;
separating power, gas chromatography presents an interesting alternative to LC. A plan was&#13;
therefore drafted for coupling a gas chromatograph with the atmospheric-pressure ion source&#13;
of the Q-TOF Ultima for APLI. To this end, an appropriate electrically heated transfer line&#13;
was constructed. The front end of this transfer line could be mounted instead of a&#13;
volatilisation stage on the otherwise unmodified atmospheric-pressure ion source. The&#13;
parameters necessary to operate the source, such as the amounts of gas within the source and&#13;
settings on the mass spectrometer, were optimised. The efficiency of this new coupling was&#13;
demonstrated by the analysis of a number of standards (PAHs and hetero-PAHs).&#13;
&lt;br&gt;On the basis of this successful coupling, APLI was also coupled with another atmosphericpressure&#13;
mass spectrometer (micrOTOF, Bruker Daltonics). For this, a new ion source was&#13;
developed for the mass spectrometer, to replace the standard one. The central component of&#13;
the new source, which can be used for LC as well as for GC versions of APLI-(TOF)MS, is a&#13;
cube-shaped source body with several apertures. Various additional components, such as the&#13;
volatilisation stage of liquid chromatography or the newly developed transfer line, could be&#13;
mounted onto the body. After important parameters had been optimised, a number of&#13;
standards as well as real samples were analysed with both the LC-APLI-(TOF)MS and GCAPLI-(&#13;
TOF)MS systems, in order to show the potential of this coupling. Thus, in addition to&#13;
several aromatic oligomers used in the manufacture of organic light-emitting diodes, which&#13;
are difficult to analyse by other methods, transition-metal complexes used as triplet emitters&#13;
were successfully analysed by LC-APLI-(TOF)MS. Among examples of the application of&#13;
GC-APLI-(TOF)MS, several PAH and hetero-PAH standards were analysed, and the pyrene&#13;
metabolite 1-hydroxypyrene was detected in urine. For chrysene, a detection limit of 0.5 ng/L&#13;
was achieved with an injection volume of 2 µL.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;In order to use the advantages of such a flexible coupling, in which the costly high-resolution&#13;
mass spectrometer serves as detector for various chromatographic applications in conjunction&#13;
with the three important atmospheric-pressure ionisation methods (ESI, APCI, APPI), these&#13;
methods were integrated into the design. In addition, an improved version of the GC-transfer&#13;
line was developed. This new design of a Multi-Purpose API-Source (MPIS) has been made&#13;
commercially available by the company Bruker Daltonics as a flexible ion source for an&#13;
atmospheric-pressure mass spectrometer.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;Switching between various ionisation methods is convenient, requiring only that the&#13;
alternative components be exchanged at the apertures of the source body. For example, to&#13;
switch from GC-APLI-(TOF)MS to GC-APCI-(TOF)MS, only a quartz window is replaced&#13;
by the APCI needle assembly. Switching between LC und GC is possible in the same way:&#13;
here only the transfer line has to be replaced by a blind flange. In this design, the ionisation&#13;
methods can be applied either individually or in combination as true multimode ionisation&#13;
(e.g. APLI and APCI simultaneously). The efficiency of the individual modes was&#13;
demonstrated with several standards. With this source, ionisation techniques such as ESI,&#13;
APCI, APPI and APLI are available for both LC and GC. For LC, the additional multimode&#13;
ionisation techniques APLI+ESI and APLI+APCI can be used.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;APLI is a selective method for ionising non-polar aromatic compounds. On the one hand, this&#13;
represents a limitation to the general applicability of the method, but on the other hand it&#13;
makes it possible to ionise this class of compounds selectively in a complex matrix. Therefore&#13;
ionisation labels and corresponding strategies for derivatisation were developed for LC-APLI-&#13;
(TOF)MS and GC-APLI-(TOF)MS. These ionisation labels are aromatic compounds that can&#13;
be detected with high sensitivity. They have an anchor group for covalent coupling with nonaromatic&#13;
analytes. The derivative can then be detected sensitively by APLI. A study of&#13;
REMPI spectra of several derivatives under atmospheric pressure showed that they do not&#13;
differ significantly from those of the labels themselves, which indicates that the electronic&#13;
proportion of the aromatic system of the derivative is not significantly influenced by the&#13;
analyte. The practical application of the APLI ionisation labels was showen for LC-APLI-&#13;
(TOF)MS and GC-APLI-(TOF)MS by study of a number of samples such as Brij® 72 and&#13;
PEG 1000 and by the determination of the fatty acid content of vegetable oils and a technical&#13;
fatty alcohol mixture.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 540 Chemie » 540 Chemie und zugeordnete Wissenschaften</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Chemie » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>