<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>oai:elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de:833</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:51:510</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">A graph based approach to the convergence of some iterative methods for singular M-matrices and Markov chains</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Borovac, Stefan</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2006-07-19</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/mathematik/diss2006/borovac</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=833</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20060359</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-939/dc0609.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">This thesis concerns the interaction of two widely known topics in the field&#13;
of applied mathematics. These are Markov chains (or likewise singular&#13;
M-matrices) and Schwarz methods.&lt;p&gt;&#13;
&#13;
Markov chains as well as singular M-matrices are extensively used, their&#13;
range of application stretching from stochastic processes over network modeling&#13;
to the discretisation of partial differential equations.&lt;p&gt;&#13;
&#13;
Schwarz methods are widely used as preconditioners for the numerical solution&#13;
of partial differential equations and can be classified as domain&#13;
decomposition methods.&lt;p&gt;&#13;
&#13;
Both topics are brought together for the solution of consistent square&#13;
linear systems or likewise the Frobenius vector problem, i.e. a fixed&#13;
point problem for nonnegative matrices of unit spectral radius.&lt;p&gt;&#13;
&#13;
It is a known technique to solve such problems using block Jacobi&#13;
or block Gauss-Seidel iterations. Schwarz methods can be seen as a&#13;
generalisation of these techniques. They naturally occur in two setups,&#13;
the additive Schwarz iterations and the multiplicative Schwarz iterations&#13;
which extend the block Gauss-Seidel iteration. Both iterations have their own&#13;
advantages. Additive Schwarz methods are easy to parallelise. Multiplicative&#13;
Schwarz usually converges more rapidly but cannot be parallelised in such an&#13;
easy way. However, it can be partly parallelised using block asynchronous&#13;
iterations.&lt;p&gt;&#13;
&#13;
In this work, solutions of linear systems having a positive fixed point using&#13;
additive and (standard and asynchronous) multiplicative Schwarz iterations are&#13;
considered. This is done for several different block updates including the&#13;
standard (one-level) update, the two-stage update, and an update derived from&#13;
the power iteration. Additionally, relaxed versions of the three block updates&#13;
are considered. &lt;p&gt;&#13;
&#13;
One main goal of this thesis lies in the detailed analysis of the structure of&#13;
a nonnegative matrix having a positive fixed point. It turns out that such&#13;
matrices possess some basic pattern which can be exploited to construct&#13;
convergent Schwarz iterations. This pattern consists of either a spanning tree&#13;
or a spanning forest within the transposed graph.&lt;p&gt;&#13;
&#13;
Based on these patterns, operators for Schwarz iterations can be constructed&#13;
which are consistent and (semi)convergent for several block updates. We put&#13;
some special emphasise on the differences between non-relaxed and relaxed&#13;
block updates. Additionally, we obtain some results for block asynchronous&#13;
iterations.&lt;p&gt;&#13;
&#13;
Altogether, several new results for additive and multiplicative Schwarz&#13;
iterations as well as asynchronous iterations are achieved. In contrast to the&#13;
known theory on this topics the theory presented here is completely uniform&#13;
and based only on the structure of the given matrix which is either a spanning&#13;
tree or a spanning forest within the transposed graph.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>Linear systems</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>M-matrices</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Markov chains</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>singular matrices</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>iterative methods</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>block methods</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>additive Schwarz</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>multiplicative Schwarz</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>domain decomposition methods</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>overlap</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>asynchronous iterations</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>parallel iterations</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>two-stage</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>non-stationary</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>matrix graph theory</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 510 Mathematik » 510 Mathematik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Mathematik und Informatik » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>