<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>oai:elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de:789</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:54:540</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="de">Entwicklung, Optimierung und Validierung eines rezeptorproteingestützten  Mikrotiterplatten-Tests zur Rückstandsanalytik von ß-Lactam-Antibiotika</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Lamar, Janine</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2007-02-20</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/chemie/diss2007/lamar</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=789</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20070084</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-886/dc0702.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">The recombinantly obtained &lt;i&gt;Streptococcus pneumoniae&lt;/i&gt; penicillin-binding protein PBP 2x* has&#13;
been utilised to develop a novel microtiter plate assay for the detection and determination of&#13;
penicillins and cephalosporins in milk, honey, porcine, bovine, turkey and deer muscle tissue and&#13;
egg. The major advantage in using PBP 2x* is that only intact beta lactams are detected and both,&#13;
penicillins and cephalosporins, can be screened within one assay.&#13;
&#13;
&lt;p&gt;In the assay, the receptor protein was immobilised to a microplate in the first step. To each&#13;
sample a bifunctional reagent synthesised for this assay was added, with ampicillin and digoxigenin&#13;
as functional groups (DIG-AMPI). The amount of bifunctional reagent, which was bound via its&#13;
ampicillin part to the receptor protein, decreased with increasing beta-lactam concentration in the&#13;
sample. The detection step used anti-digoxigenin F&lt;sub&gt;ab&lt;/sub&gt; fragments marked with horseradish peroxidase.&#13;
The more bifunctional reagent was bound to the receptor protein, the more antibody fragments were&#13;
bound via the digoxigenin part of the reagent. A maximum colour development with hydrogen peroxide&#13;
as substrate for the peroxidase and tetramethylbenzidine as chromogen was achieved, when no&#13;
beta-lactam residues were present. Consequently, the colour development was reversely related to&#13;
the beta-lactam concentration in the sample.&#13;
&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The expression of PBP 2x* as recombinant protein in &lt;i&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/i&gt; and the following&#13;
purification by affinity chromatography were optimised to achieve high protein amounts.&#13;
&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Chemometric experimental design was used to optimise the assay procedure. A fractional factorial&#13;
design was created to detect effects and interactions of the assay parameters. For final&#13;
optimisation of the significant parameters a Box-Behnken design was used. As a result of the&#13;
optimisation, operation parameters could be selected, which allowed a low consumption of PBP 2x* as&#13;
the most valuable reagent, while keeping sensitivity at the necessary high level.&#13;
&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The assay has been developed for various food matrices to screen for residues of beta-lactam&#13;
antibiotics. Except cefalonium, all EU relevant beta-lactam antibiotics could be detected at&#13;
concentrations around their respective MRL. Cefalonium had a too low binding affinity to PBP 2x*,&#13;
so that the detection at its MRL was not possible. Matrix interferences could be eliminated by&#13;
tenfold dilution of raw milk, porcine and turkey muscle meat, honey and egg. The matrix effect&#13;
observed with raw milk could also be eliminated by a centrifugation step only. Matrix interferences&#13;
caused by bovine muscle tissue and albumen could only be partially reduced by a tenfold dilution.&#13;
For the analysis of deer muscle tissue a membrane filtration step was necessary prior to the&#13;
dilution step. Samples of albumen, bovine and deer muscle tissue needed matrix blank samples using&#13;
the same microplate for reliable beta-lactam identification.&#13;
&#13;
&lt;p&gt;A validation using the principles of EU decision 2002/657 was performed for benzylpenicillin,&#13;
ampicillin, cefquinome and cefoperazone in milk. The developed microplate assay satisfied the&#13;
criteria for specificity, reproducibility, precision and accuracy. CCα&#13;
and CCβ values were calculated. A set of 8 blind-fortified samples for&#13;
each of the four beta-lactams was analysed. All blanks were correctly identified and a very high&#13;
accuracy for quantitative results was observed.&#13;
&#13;
&lt;p&gt;At the Federal Research Centre for Nutrition and Food (Institute for Hygiene and Food Safety)&#13;
at the location in Kiel the excretion of antibiotics (e.g. benzylpenicillin, ampicillin, cefquinome&#13;
and cefoperazone) in milk was studied. There, the residues were determined by high performance&#13;
liquid chromatography (HPLC) with UV detection and different screening methods. From these&#13;
experiments 289 milk samples (with the four β-lactam antibiotics&#13;
mentioned above) preserved by lyophilization were available. With these samples and by comparison of&#13;
the microtiter plate assay results and the HPLC results obtained in Kiel the opportunity to use the&#13;
microtiter plate assay as quantitative assay (when the identity of the residual beta-lactam is&#13;
known), the quantitative accuracy and the validity of the developed microplate receptor assay were&#13;
checked. No false positive reactions could be detected, giving a diagnostic specificity of 100 %.&#13;
No false negative samples could be observed as well.&#13;
&#13;
&lt;p&gt;In conclusion the results indicate that the assay has the potential to emerge into a screening&#13;
assay for routine use.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 540 Chemie » 540 Chemie und zugeordnete Wissenschaften</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Chemie » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>