<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>oai:elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de:319</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:53:530</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="de">Datengetriebene Modelle stochastischer dynamischer Systeme - am Beispiel hydrodynamischer Turbulenz</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Ragwitz, Mario</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2002-01-22</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fb08/diss2001/ragwitz</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=319</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20020053</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-413/d080109.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">This thesis deals with the development of data driven models&#13;
for stochastic dynamical systems based on measured time sequences. Reconstruction&#13;
of deterministic dynamical systems from time series is a well established technique,&#13;
whereas only very few methods exist in the case of a nonlinear stochastic setting.&#13;
The need for such algorithms arises in a variety of fields, such as physics, biology,&#13;
economics, or meteorology. First we derive a method to construct Fokker-Planck- and&#13;
Langevin-equations from time series, if all relevant dynamical variables are measured.&#13;
The latter assumption, however, is unrealistic in many applications.&#13;
Therefore we discuss, whether it is possible to embed a scalar time series in a stochastic&#13;
setting and, if so, how to choose the correct parameters.&#13;
This leads us to novel time series predictors for Markovian-processes.&#13;
The performance of these algorithms is demonstrated by numerical examples.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
In the second part of this work we apply the techniques developed in the first&#13;
section to hydrodynamic turbulence and the&#13;
problem of predicting the fluctuations in wind energy production. For a hydrodynamic&#13;
flow with pronounced coherent structures, nonlinear phase space methods prove&#13;
to have significantly higher predictive power within such structures than ordinary linear&#13;
schemes.&#13;
This knowledge is then applied to time series of atmospheric surface&#13;
wind velocities and of the power output of a wind turbine. In these cases as well, strong&#13;
turbulent fluctuations are clearly better predicted by nonlinear methods than by&#13;
linear ones. This fact has relevant applications for the control of rotor blades of wind turbines&#13;
as well as for the regulation of conventional power supplies.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 530 Physik » 530 Physik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Physik » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>