<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>oai:elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de:335</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:53:530</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="de">Bestimmung der Newtonschen Gravitationskonstanten G</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Kleinevoß, Ulf</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2002-03-12</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fb08/diss2002/kleinevoss</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=335</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20020143</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-429/d080201.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">The value of the Newtonian Gravitational constant &lt;i&gt;G &lt;/i&gt;has interested physicists for more than&#13;
200 years and except for the speed of light, it has the longest history of measurements. But&#13;
although &lt;i&gt;G&lt;/i&gt; is the aim of experimentalists for such a long time, it is the least well known&#13;
fundamental constant. At the end of 1998 the CODATA even decided to increase the uncertainty&#13;
of the accepted value for the gravitational constant from 128 ppm to 1500 ppm. This remarkable&#13;
step of increasing the uncertainty instead of decreasing was made to reflect the discrepancies&#13;
between recent experiments, which span a wide range of more than 0.7 %. Motivated by this&#13;
fact and the uniqueness of the Wuppertaler experiment concerning distance range and method,&#13;
strong efforts were performed in order to minimize the uncertainties and to determine a realistic&#13;
estimate for the Newtonian constant and the remaining errors.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
The heart of the experiment is an open Fabry-Pérot resonator, which is formed by two reflectors.&#13;
On each outer side of the reflectors a 576 kg brass mass is placed, coinciding with the axis&#13;
of the resonator. The two masses are moved symmetrically and simultaneously from a reference&#13;
to a measuring position near the reflectors. This causes the distance between the reflectors of&#13;
the cavity to change due to the change in gravitational force acting on them. The measured&#13;
quantity is the change in the resonant frequency of the resonator arising from the change in&#13;
its length of approximately 13 nm. Because the resulting shift in the resonance frequency is&#13;
measured as a function of the field masses position, Newton’s inverse-square law can be tested&#13;
between the ranges of 0.7 m and 2.1 m.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
This thesis describes the results of a search for further systematical errors and the reduction&#13;
of known uncertainties. A correction function for the tilt of the experiment due to deformation&#13;
of the ground by the brass masses was determined, which enabled us to reanalyse the results&#13;
of older measurements. Also, the dependence on the alignment between the resonantor and&#13;
the waveguides was reduced and an active temperature stabilization was installed. Therefore,&#13;
systematic uncertainty could be reduced by more than an order of magnitude compared to the&#13;
previous measurements. As a result, the Newtonian Gravitational constant has been determined&#13;
with a relative accuracy of 147 ppm to be&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&#13;
&lt;div align="right"&gt;&lt; &lt;i&gt;G&lt;/i&gt;&#13;
      &gt;  = ( 6:67422 ± 0:00049 ± 0:00085 ) &lt;sup&gt;.&lt;/sup&gt; 10&lt;sup&gt;-11&lt;/sup&gt; [m&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; kg&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; s&lt;sup&gt;-2&lt;/sup&gt;].             (1)&lt;/div&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&#13;
In addition it puts new constraints on the excluded regions for non-Newtonian gravity in the&#13;
range between 0.1 m to 1 m. The value itself is in good agreement with the latest measurements&#13;
of other groups.&#13;
&lt;/P&gt;</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 530 Physik » 530 Physik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Physik » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>