<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>oai:elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de:3831</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:54:540</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="de">Analyse fettchemischer Produkte mittels comprehensiver zweidimensionaler Flüssigchromatographie gekoppelt mit der Massenspektrometrie (LCxLC-MS)</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Elsner, Victoria</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2018-01-22</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/chemie/diss2013/elsner</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=3831</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20140113-115443-6</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-3940/dc1319.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;p&gt;Fatty alcohol derivatives are used as surfactants and applied in commercial&#13;
formulations like laundry detergents, cleaning agents or cosmetic products as&#13;
complex mixtures. Different classes of surfactants are combined in formulations to&#13;
improve the properties of the product such as cleaning capacity or foam formation.&#13;
Furthermore, the individual surfactant classes already consist of a complex mixture&#13;
of homologues because of the raw materials used and the production process. Due to&#13;
the complexity of this kind of samples, an analytical method is necessary which can&#13;
detect all individual substances as well as qualify and quantify them.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#13;
In this work, it has been shown that complex mixtures consisting of anionic, nonionic&#13;
and amphoteric surfactants can be separated with HILIC by substance class.&#13;
Furthermore, a separation by EO homologues was achieved for the ethoxylated&#13;
substances while a separation by alkyl chain length distribution was only obtained&#13;
for the betaines. In addition, the application of a reversed phase material showed a&#13;
very good separation by alkyl chain length distribution whereas the substance&#13;
classes could not be separated from each other. The use of different organic mobile&#13;
phases can also lead to a separation by EO homologues, if needed. But exemplified&#13;
by a special phase material for the analysis of surfactants, it was shown that the onedimensional&#13;
separation by substance class, alkyl chain length distribution and EO&#13;
homologues of a complex surfactant mixture leads to coelutions and a very&#13;
complicated data evaluation.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#13;
Since the one-dimensional separation did not lead to the desired result,&#13;
comprehensive two-dimensional liquid chromatography (LCxLC) was implemented.&#13;
Firstly, the Neue test was carried out for a closer characterization of the reversed&#13;
phase materials used. While the separation in the first dimension was performed by&#13;
polar interactions of a HILIC phase, a C&lt;sub&gt;8&lt;/sub&gt; diol phase showed the highest orthogonality&#13;
when used as second dimension. With this column combination, a separation by&#13;
substance class and EO homologues was achieved in the first dimension, while the&#13;
separation in the second dimension led to a further separation by alkyl chain length&#13;
distribution. Finally, the developed method allowed the separation of about 110&#13;
individual substances.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#13;
The LCxLC method was successfully applied to the analysis of several real samples&#13;
from the home care sector. Furthermore, analyses for the determination of the&#13;
reproducibility of peak area and retention time showed that the reproducibility of the&#13;
retention time in the first dimension is dependent on the retention time. Apart from a&#13;
small sector in the chromatogram where broad signals were obtained, the&#13;
reproducibility of the retention time in the first dimension resulted in values below&#13;
10%. The retention time in the second dimension showed a very good reproducibility&#13;
with a relative standard deviation below 7% for all substances. Concerning the&#13;
reproducibility of the peak area, a relative standard deviation below 7% was&#13;
achieved for fatty alcohol ethoxylates (FAEO), fatty alcohol ether sulfates (FAES) and&#13;
betaines. For the fatty alcohol sulfates (FAS) and alkyl polyglucoside (AG), higher&#13;
values were achieved, which is due to an insufficient and non-reproducible&#13;
ionisation. Regarding the betaines and fatty alcohol ethoxylates, it was shown that a&#13;
quantification of the surfactants in complex mixtures is possible with an external&#13;
calibration or the standard addition method.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 540 Chemie » 540 Chemie und zugeordnete Wissenschaften</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Chemie » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>