<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>oai:elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de:294</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:53:530</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="de">Untersuchung präparativer Einflüsse auf die Mikrostruktur und die Transporteigenschaften von YBa&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;Cu&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;7&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sub&gt;-&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&amp;#948;&lt;/sub&gt; -Stufenkantenkontakten</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Hill, Frank</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2001-02-05</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fb08/diss2000/hill</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=294</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20010098</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-388/d080003.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">Josephson junctions are the key elements of unique superconducting electronic devices&#13;
like extremely sensitive magnetometers, tunable microwave and three-terminal devices and&#13;
very fast (f ~ 100 GHz) digital circuits. The large energy gap of high-temperature&#13;
superconductors (HTS) promises improved performance of Josephson devices compared to&#13;
the established Nb/Al&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt;O&lt;SUB&gt;3&lt;/SUB&gt;/Nb technology. Unfortunately, HTS Josephson&#13;
junctions still suffer from poor reproducibility, which impedes large-scale integration.&#13;
Optimised preparation processes are therefore strongly required.&lt;P&gt;&#13;
&#13;
&lt;P&gt;The research described in this thesis focused on&#13;
YBa&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt;Cu&lt;SUB&gt;3&lt;/SUB&gt;O&lt;SUB&gt;7-δ&lt;/SUB&gt;&#13;
(YBCO) step-edge junctions, which are based on the natural formation of junctions at grain boundaries,&#13;
involve comparatively simple preparation processes and have the potential for large-scale integration.&#13;
More than 1000 junctions of 2-60 µm width were prepared on 10x10 mm&lt;SUP&gt;2&lt;/SUP&gt; LaAlO&lt;SUB&gt;3&lt;/SUB&gt;&#13;
substrates. UV lithography combined with an additional photoresist postbake and a new two-step Ar&lt;SUP&gt;+&lt;/SUP&gt;&#13;
ion etching process yielded steep and very smooth substrate steps of up to 560 nm height. The 200 nm thick&#13;
YBCO films were deposited by DC-sputtering at a set of pressure and temperature values at Wuppertal, or by&#13;
off-axis laserablation at the 'Forschungszentrum Jülich'. Simultaneous patterning of the YBCO microbridges&#13;
and the gold contact pads improved the junction reproducibility.&lt;/P&gt;&#13;
&#13;
&lt;P&gt;An AFM analysis of the sputtered YBCO films at the 'Free University of Amsterdam' revealed a low, but highly&#13;
temperature dependent, surface diffusion constant&#13;
D&lt;SUB&gt;s&lt;/SUB&gt; ~ 10&lt;SUP&gt;-14&lt;/SUP&gt; - 10&lt;SUP&gt;-13&lt;/SUP&gt; cm&lt;SUP&gt;2&lt;/SUP&gt;/s&#13;
during film growth. This result is one to two orders of magnitude lower than the value derived for off-axis&#13;
laserablation. It could be shown by TEM analysis at Jülich that the poor surface diffusion led to a high&#13;
density of crystal defects and to a deep trench in the film near the lower edge of the substrate step, where&#13;
one of the two grain boundaries is formed.&lt;/P&gt;&#13;
&#13;
&lt;P&gt;The current-voltage characteristics (IVC) of the low-temperature sputtered&#13;
junctions were flux-flow-like, with a low T&lt;SUB&gt;c&lt;/SUB&gt; ≤&#13;
 30 K and a yield ≤&#13;
 30%, independent of the film-thickness-to-step-height ratio and other preparation parameters.&#13;
 In contrast, the IVCs of the laserablated junctions could be described well by the resistively-shunted&#13;
 junction model, with typical parameters T&lt;SUB&gt;c&lt;/SUB&gt; of 88 K, characteristic voltage&#13;
 I&lt;SUB&gt;c&lt;/SUB&gt;R&lt;SUB&gt;n&lt;/SUB&gt; of 2.1 mV at 4.2 K and 0.24 mV at 77 K, a yield ≥&#13;
 90%, and a statistical spread at 4.2 K of as low as σ&#13;
(J&lt;SUB&gt;c&lt;/SUB&gt;)=16.8%, σ&#13;
(R&lt;SUB&gt;n&lt;/SUB&gt;A)=18.8% and σ&#13;
(I&lt;SUB&gt;c&lt;/SUB&gt;R&lt;SUB&gt;n&lt;/SUB&gt;)=7.4%. The shape of the IVCs, the critical temperature,&#13;
yield, reproducibility, microwave sensitivity and magnetic field modulation of the&#13;
critical current were found to depend sensitively on the YBCO deposition process.&#13;
It could be concluded from a comparison between laserablated and low- and high-temperature&#13;
sputtered junctions that both their transport properties and microstructure improved with&#13;
increasing surface diffusion.&lt;/P&gt;&#13;
&#13;
&lt;P&gt;The observed scaling law I&lt;SUB&gt;c&lt;/SUB&gt;R&lt;SUB&gt;n&lt;/SUB&gt; ∞ J&lt;SUB&gt;c&lt;/SUB&gt;&lt;SUP&gt;p&lt;/SUP&gt; with p ≈&#13;
 0.5 and slightly non-linear IVCs at high voltages indicated that resonant&#13;
 tunneling through one localised state was the dominant quasiparticle transport mechanism&#13;
 in all investigated junctions. Metallic point contacts, which give rise to a subharmonic&#13;
 energy gap structure in the dI/dV characteristics, were observed in O&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt;-deficient&#13;
 step-edge junctions. The measurements were analysed in the framework of an extended&#13;
 Octavio-Tinkham-Blonder-Klapwijk model, yielding a high energy gap Δ  = 30-33 meV and Δ /kT&lt;SUB&gt;c&lt;/SUB&gt; = 3.8 - 4.2 in the&#13;
 superconducting electrodes adjacent to the barrier. The typical low&#13;
 I&lt;SUB&gt;c&lt;/SUB&gt;R&lt;SUB&gt;n&lt;/SUB&gt; &lt;&lt; Δ  of HTS junctions is therefore, at least in this case, not due to a suppressed energy gap,&#13;
 but attributed to the barrier itself.&lt;/P&gt;&#13;
&#13;
&lt;P&gt;Since sputtered bicrystal junctions appeared to be much more sensitive to defects at the&#13;
substrate grain boundary than laserablated bicrystal junctions, D&lt;SUB&gt;s&lt;/SUB&gt; has to be&#13;
considered a key parameter to optimise any HTS grain boundary junction engineering.&lt;/P&gt;</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 530 Physik » 530 Physik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Physik » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>