<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>oai:elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de:880</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:53:530</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">Measurement of the W boson helicity in tt decays</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Schmitt, Christian</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2005-12-07</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/physik/diss2005/schmitt</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=880</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20050717</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-986/dc0514.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="de">&lt;p&gt;Ziel dieser Dissertation ist die Messung des Anteils an W Bosonen mit&#13;
positiver Helizitaet aus Top-Antitop Zerfällen. Die Daten für diese Analyse&#13;
wurden mit dem D0 Detektor am Fermilab Tevatron in den Jahren 2002-2004 aufgezeichnet.&#13;
Sie entsprechen einer integrierten Luminositaet von ca. 230 inversen pb.&#13;
Die Messung benutzt den Zerfallswinkel theta zwischen dem geladenen Lepton und der&#13;
(negativen) Flugrichtung des b-Quarks im Ruhesystem des W Bosons. Um den Winkel&#13;
theta zu rekonstruieren, wird das Top-Antitop System mit Hilfe eines kinematischen&#13;
Fits rekonstruiert, wobei die Masse des W Bosons und des Top Quarks als Nebenbedingungen&#13;
ausgenutzt werden.&#13;
&#13;
Der Vergleich zwischen der erwarteten Verteilung in cos(theta) aus Monte Carlo Simulationen fuer verschiedene Anteile&#13;
an rechtshaendigen W Bosonen, f+, mit der Verteilung in den Daten ergab&#13;
das folgende Resultat fuer f+: f+ = -0.10 +- 0.17(stat) +- 0.07 (syst).&#13;
&#13;
Dieses Ergebnis schliesst theoretische Modelle die einen sehr grossen V+A Anteil&#13;
im elektroschwachen geladenen Strom des Top Zerfalls vorhersagen aus.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;p&gt;The subject of this thesis is the measurement of the fraction of W&#13;
bosons with positive helicity in top-antitop events recorded by the D0&#13;
detector at the Fermilab Tevatron collider during the years 2002-2004.  The data&#13;
corresponds to an integrated luminosity of about 230 inverse pb.&#13;
The measurement makes use of the decay angle theta&#13;
between the charged lepton and the (negative) b quark direction in the&#13;
rest frame of the W boson. To obtain the angle theta, the top-antitop&#13;
system and its decay products are reconstructed using a&#13;
kinematic fit with constraints on the mass of the W boson and of the&#13;
top quark.&#13;
&#13;
By comparing the expectation for cos(theta) from Monte Carlo samples with&#13;
different fractions of right-handed W bosons, f+, with the&#13;
distribution obtained in data, the following result for f+ has&#13;
been obtained:  f+ = -0.10 +- 0.17(stat) +- 0.07 (syst).&#13;
&#13;
This effectively rules out theoretical models which predict a pure or&#13;
very high V+A contribution in the weak charged current interaction&#13;
of the top quark. Together with a similar analysis using only events&#13;
where no b-jets could be identified, this result has been&#13;
published in Physical Review D.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 530 Physik » 530 Physik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Physik » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>