<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>oai:elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de:10950</id><datestamp>2020-09-21</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:53:530</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">Reconstruction of Three-Dimensional Nerve Fiber Orientations from Histological Brain Sections in Three-Dimensional Polarized Light Imaging</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Schmitz, Daniel</dc:creator>
          <dc:contributor>Lippert, Thomas</dc:contributor>
          <dc:contributor>Axer, Markus</dc:contributor>
          <dc:date>2020-09-21</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/physik/diss2020/schmitz</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=10950</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20200921-090438-8</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.25926/15kc-t577</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-10243/dc2012.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;p&gt;Three-Dimensional Polarized Light Imaging enables to reconstruct nerve fiber orientations&#13;
from polarimetric measurements of histological brain sections based on the birefringence&#13;
of myelinated nerve fibers. Measurements of the brain sample from oblique views&#13;
facilitate the retrieval of the three-dimensional orientation of the nerve fibers as well&#13;
as the birefringence strength. The enhancement of this noise sensitive reconstruction&#13;
represents the major motivation for this thesis. First, a novel and fast reconstruction&#13;
algorithm based on a least squares approach is introduced. At the mesoscale an unprecedented&#13;
comprehensive view of the human brain’s nerve fiber tracts is obtained based on&#13;
the new reconstruction algorithm. Next, the reconstruction is further improved for very&#13;
low signals utilizing a Bayesian estimator. Furthermore, as the parameter estimation&#13;
is sensitive to noise, the uncertainty of the obtained parameter maps is studied. This&#13;
results in the first nerve fiber orientation confidence estimates for Three-Dimensional&#13;
Polarized Light Imaging. Finally, the developed analysis is applied at the microscale. A&#13;
validation against higher-resolved volumetric measurements shows that individual fiber&#13;
bundles can be reconstructed with high accuracy using the developed algorithms.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="de">&lt;p&gt;Das bildgebende Verfahren Three-Dimensional Polarized Light Imaging (3D-PLI) ermöglicht&#13;
die Rekonstruktion von Nervenfaserorientierungen mithilfe polarimetrischer&#13;
Messungen histologischer Gehirnschnitte basierend auf der Doppelbrechung myelinisierter&#13;
Nervenfasern. Aufnahmen des Hirnschnitts von schrägen Perspektiven erlauben die Abschätzung&#13;
der dreidimensionalen Faserorientierung sowie der Doppelbrechungsstärke.&#13;
Die Verbesserung dieser rauschsensitiven Abschätzung ist das Ziel der vorliegenden Arbeit.&#13;
Zuerst wird ein neuartiger Rekonstruktionsalgorithmus basierend auf dem Verfahren&#13;
der kleinsten Quadrate entwickelt. Dieser möglicht auf der Mesoskala einen umfassende&#13;
Darstellung der menschlichen Nervenfaserarchitektur. Zur Verbesserung der&#13;
Rekonstruktion für sehr kleine Signale wird ein bayesscher Schätzer entwickelt. Weiterhin&#13;
wird die Unsicherheit der rekonstruierten Gewebeeigenschaften untersucht. Dies&#13;
ermöglicht zum ersten Mal die Abschätzung der Verlässlichkeit der in 3D-PLI ermittelten&#13;
Nervenfaserorientierung. Schließlich werden die entwickelten Analysemethoden auf&#13;
mikroskopische 3D-PLI Messungen mit schrägem Lichteinfall angewandt. Ein Vergleich&#13;
mit höher aufgelösten volumetrischen Messungen zeigt, dass die Orientierung einzelner&#13;
Nervenfaserbündel mit den entwickelten Algorithmen mit hoher Genauigkeit rekonstruiert&#13;
werden können.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 530 Physik » 530 Physik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Physik » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>