<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>oai:elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de:8700</id><datestamp>2018-09-11</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:53:530</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">Laterally Separated Muons from Cosmic Ray Air Showers Measured with the ICECUBE Neutrino Observatory</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Soldin, Dennis</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2018-09-11</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/physik/diss2017/soldin</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=8700</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20180910-115302-5</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-8091/dc1740.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;p&gt;Cosmic rays enter the Earth’s atmosphere with energies up to 10&lt;sup&gt;20&lt;/sup&gt; eV, producing extended air showers, which contain up to billions of secondary particles that&#13;
can be detected on the ground. Inside these showers, hadrons with large transverse&#13;
momentum may be produced, which subsequently decay into muons, also&#13;
carrying large transverse momentum. These muons separate from the shower&#13;
core while traveling to the ground, producing lateral separations from the core&#13;
up to several hundred meters. Together with the dense muon core bundle, they&#13;
produce distinctive double-track signatures in the IceCube Neutrino Observatory.&#13;
The corresponding lateral separation distributions are a measure of the&#13;
underlying transverse momentum of hadrons, and therefore yield important&#13;
information on hadron production during the air shower development.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
In this work, the lateral separation of atmospheric muons, between 135m&#13;
and approximately 450 m, is measured using three years of IceCube data, taken&#13;
between May 2012 and May 2015. A dedicated Monte Carlo for the simulation&#13;
of laterally separated muons from air showers is presented. This is used to&#13;
develop selection criteria in order to isolate the events of interest from IceCube&#13;
data. In addition, a specific double-track reconstruction is introduced, which&#13;
enables a precise measurement of the lateral separation and arrival direction&#13;
of muons. Using existing energy estimation methods, which are optimized for&#13;
the reconstruction of this class of events, the first primary energy dependent&#13;
analysis of the lateral separation distribution of muons far from the shower core&#13;
is performed.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
After applying all selection criteria, 80951 events are left with an effective&#13;
lifetime of 960 days. The resulting lateral separation distributions are studied&#13;
with emphasis on the angular arrival directions and the transverse momentum&#13;
of muons, which is estimated based on Monte Carlo simulations. In addition,&#13;
the sensitivity of laterally separated muons on the mass composition of cosmic&#13;
ray nuclei and the seasonal variations of the resulting muon fluxes over three&#13;
years are studied.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
Finally, the prospects for a search of double-track signatures, produced by&#13;
exotic particles in cosmic ray air showers, which are predicted by theories&#13;
beyond the standard model, are discussed. It is shown that, considering recent&#13;
constraints on existing theoretical models, such as supersymmetry, the expected&#13;
fluxes are below 10&lt;sup&gt;-3&lt;/sup&gt; events per year. Hence, it is concluded that the observation of exotic double-tracks from air showers, using existing neutrino telescopes, is&#13;
not feasible.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 530 Physik » 530 Physik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Physik » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>