<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>oai:elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de:913</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:53:530</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">On large-scale wave coupling across the stratopause</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Oberheide, Jens</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2007-08-03</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/physik/habi2006/oberheide</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=913</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20070724</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-1019/hc0601.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">The present understanding of Earth's mesosphere and lower thermosphere&#13;
(MLT) region, and its coupling with the atmospheric layers below and above is far from being complete.&#13;
For many years, its inaccessibility caused the lack of a comprehensive database and important open&#13;
science questions remain.&lt;p&gt;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;What are the spatio-temporal variations of temperature, winds, and chemical constituents and what causes them?&#13;
&#13;
&lt;li&gt;What are the sources and magnitudes of atmospheric waves and how do they interact with each other?&#13;
&#13;
&lt;li&gt;What is the relative importance of radiation, chemistry, and dynamics for the momentum and energy budget?&#13;
&#13;
&lt;li&gt;How large is the anthropogenic effect?&#13;
&#13;
&lt;li&gt;Can we quantify the MLT effect on climate?&lt;/ul&gt;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&lt;p&gt;A key role in this context plays the large-scale vertical wave coupling across the stratopause by&#13;
planetary waves and tides. Its better understanding is the leading objective of this work using data&#13;
from several satellite instruments and models of differing character. Some emphasis is given to&#13;
nonmigrating (non-Sun-synchronous) tides that are among the least  understood and explored phenomena&#13;
in the MLT.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 530 Physik » 530 Physik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Physik » Habilitationsschriften</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Habilitation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>