<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>oai:elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de:8880</id><datestamp>2018-10-29</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:51</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">The Tree-Grid Method</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Kossaczký, Igor</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2018-10-29</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/mathematik/diss2018/kossaczky</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=8880</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20181029-153921-8</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-8282/dc1815.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;p&gt;In this thesis we are concerned with the development of numerical schemes for solving the&#13;
stochastic control problems and the related Hamilton-Jacobi-Bellman (HJB) equations. In&#13;
the first part, we present the convergence theory and the standard finite difference methods&#13;
(FDMs) used for solving HJB equations. We present then our result on non-existence of&#13;
higher order monotone numerical methods. This result represents also the motivation for&#13;
the numerical methods presented in this thesis. Rather than aiming for an high-order&#13;
method, we focus on reducing the computational time.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The piecewise predicted policy timestepping method presented in this work represents a&#13;
modification of the well-established piecewise constant policy timestepping method. The&#13;
main idea of the method is reducing the control space based on the prediction computed&#13;
on a coarse grid in order to reduce the computational time. We show the efficiency of the&#13;
method on examples from finance.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The Tree-Grid methods represent the central topic of this thesis. The main essence of&#13;
these methods is the combination of the tree structure, similar to that from trinomial&#13;
tree methods, with the rectangular grid used in FDMs. We prove that these methods are&#13;
unconditionally stable and convergent on an arbitrary grid. On the other hand, as the&#13;
methods are explicit, they are faster and can be easily parallelized. We developed the&#13;
methods for the cases of a one-dimensional and two-dimensional state variable, and have&#13;
shown that for higher dimensions a monotone generalization is not feasible for a general&#13;
problem. An additional advantage of the Tree-Grid method in the two-dimensional case&#13;
is, that although the method uses a wide-stencil scheme, no interpolation is needed. For&#13;
the case of a one-dimensional state variable, we developed a useful modification leading to&#13;
a more efficient search for the optimal control. We tested all methods on examples from&#13;
finance.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&#13;
&lt;p&gt;In the conclusion we also propose possible further research directions emerging from this&#13;
thesis.&lt;/p&gt;</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 510 Mathematik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Mathematik und Informatik » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>