<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>oai:elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de:6900</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:53</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="de">Search for Exotic Double Tracks with the IceCube Neutrino Telescope</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Kopper, Sandro</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2018-01-22</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/physik/diss2017/kopper</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=6900</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20170511-093419-2</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-6711/dc1707.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;p&lt;&gt;Physics theories beyond the Standard Model, like supersymmetry&#13;
and models with extra dimensions, often invoke Z&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;-symmetries in&#13;
order to avoid new couplings that lead to unobserved new physics,&#13;
like unnaturally fast proton decay. This gives rise to the possibility&#13;
of heavy new particles being produced in pairs with the lightest of&#13;
them being (meta-)stable. Thus, under favorable conditions, neutrinos&#13;
in the PeV range can produce pairs of exotic, charged particles&#13;
that can be seen in a km&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;-sized detector as two parallel, muon-like&#13;
tracks with a track separation of a few hundred meters.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
This thesis discusses methods for simulating and reconstructing&#13;
these exotic double tracks for the case of the IceCube neutrino observatory&#13;
located at the geographic South Pole. It deals with techniques&#13;
to separate them from other air shower or neutrino-induced muon&#13;
events in a model independent way.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
The search for such events with data taken by the IceCube detector&#13;
in its 79-string configuration between May 2010 and May 2011 resulted&#13;
in no candidate events. This result can be used to derive limits&#13;
that can be applied to explicit exotic models.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
As this is the first analysis of its kind, the prospects and requirements&#13;
of future double track searches are also addressed.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>Supersymmetry</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>UED</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Extra Dimensions</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>IceCube</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 530 Physik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Mathematik und Informatik » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>