<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>oai:elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de:894</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:53:530</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">Atlas Pixel Opto-Board Production and Analysis and Optolink Simulation Studies</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Nderitu, Simon Kirichu</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2008-04-02</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/physik/diss2007/nderitu</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=894</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20080137</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-1000/dc0721.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="de">At CERN, a Large collider will collide protons at high energies. There are four experiments&#13;
being built to study the particle properties from the collision. The ATLAS experiment&#13;
is the largest. It has many sub detectors among which is the Pixel detector which is the&#13;
innermost part. The Pixel detector has eighty million channels that have to be read out.&#13;
An optical link is utilized for the read out. It has optical to electronic interfaces both on&#13;
the detector and off the detector at the counting room. The component on the detector&#13;
in called the opto-board.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;This work discusses the production testing of the opto-boards to be installed on the detector.&#13;
A total of 300 opto-boards including spares have been produced. The production was&#13;
done in three laboratories among which is the laboratory at the University of Wuppertal&#13;
which had the responsibility of Post production testing of all the one third of the total&#13;
opto-boards. The results are discussed in this work. The analysis of the results from the&#13;
total production process has been done in the scope of this work as well.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;In addition to the production, a study by simulation of the communication links optical&#13;
signal has been done. This has enabled an assessment of the sufficiency of the optical signal&#13;
against the transmission attenuation and irradiation degradation. A System Test set up&#13;
has been put up at Wuppertal to enhance general studies for better understanding of the&#13;
Pixel read out system. Among other studies is the study of the timing parameters behavior&#13;
of the System which has been done in this work and enhanced by a simulation. These&#13;
parameters are namely the mark to space ratio and the fine delay and their relatedness&#13;
during the optolink tuning. A bit error rate test based on the System has also been done&#13;
which enabled assessment of the transmission quality utilizing the tools inbuilt in the&#13;
System Test. These results have been presented in this work.</dc:description>
          <dc:source xml:lang="de">Datei "sc0721.pdf" = Corrigendum "Aknowledgements"</dc:source>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 530 Physik » 530 Physik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Physik » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>