<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>oai:elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de:295</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:53:530</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="de">Bruchkontaktspektroskopie an Hochtemperatur-Supraleiter-Einkristallen zur Bestimmung der Energielücke und der Symmetrie des Ordnungsparameters</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Lorenz, Michael</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2001-05-18</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fb08/diss2000/lorenz</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=295</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20010290</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-389/d080009.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;P&gt;&#13;
In contrast to the classical superconductors there is actually no consensus on the theory of&#13;
high-temperature superconductivity. Especially the symmetry of the order parameter and the&#13;
coupling mechanism which leads to the superconducting state below a critical temperature T&lt;SUB&gt;c&lt;/SUB&gt; are&#13;
still open questions. In addition, the energy gap Δ as a function of temperature T and a possible&#13;
existence of the so-called pseudogap above T&lt;sub&gt;c&lt;/sub&gt; are unsolved problems. Tunneling experiments play&#13;
an important role to solve this challenge, because they can measure the density of states directly&#13;
and therefore examine the energy gap and the symmetry of the order parameter.&#13;
The tunneling experiments described in this thesis used the break junction technique. The&#13;
main advantages of this technique are a very high quality of the junction and an in situ adjustable&#13;
contact area. The investigated materials were mainly Bi&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt;Sr&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt;Ca&lt;SUB&gt;n-1&lt;/SUB&gt;Cu&lt;SUB&gt;n&lt;/SUB&gt;O&lt;SUB&gt;2n+4+δ&lt;/SUB&gt;(n = 1 - 3). The small single crystals&#13;
      with typical sizes of 2 x 1 x 0.01 mm³ were cracked in liquid helium while&#13;
      the current voltage characteristic could be measured simultaneously. With&#13;
      a lock-in technique the computer controlled setup could also measure the&#13;
      first and the second derivative. The tunneling current was always parallel&#13;
      to the c-direction.&lt;/P&gt;&#13;
&lt;P&gt;The energy gap Δ was determined from tunnel- and point-contact characteristics. The former&#13;
ones were compared with numeric calculations based on the extended Dynes model for various&#13;
symmetries of the order parameter. Most of the characteristics have been described much better&#13;
by a s-wave than a d-wave symmetry. The energy gap of optimally doped samples at 4.2 K was&#13;
Δ = 12.7 ± 0.5 meV (n = 1), Δ = 26 ± 1 meV (n = 2) and Δ = 36 ± 1.5 meV (n = 3). This&#13;
linear dependence of the gap upon the number n of CuO&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt; planes has been observed not only&lt;/P&gt;&#13;
for Bi-compounds, but also for Tl- and Hg-based superconductors. The steeper slope dΔ =dn for&#13;
superconductors containing Ba instead of Sr and first measurements on a new superconductor&#13;
HgSr&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt;Ca&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt;Cu&lt;SUB&gt;3&lt;/SUB&gt;O&lt;SUB&gt;8&lt;/SUB&gt; have given an evidence that the value of the gap is controlled by the nature of&#13;
the blocks including the CuO&lt;SUB&gt;2&lt;/SUB&gt;- and BaO- or SrO-planes.&#13;
      &lt;P&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&#13;
&lt;P&gt;For Bi-2201 and Bi-2212 the gap Δ as a function of the hole concentration p scaled in the&#13;
same way as T&lt;SUB&gt;c&lt;/SUB&gt;(p) and led to a constant value 2Δ/k&lt;SUB&gt;B&lt;/SUB&gt;T&lt;SUB&gt;c&lt;/SUB&gt; = 12.5 ± 2 (6.9 ± 0.5) for the single&#13;
(double) layer. In the whole doping range there was no hint for a pseudogap above T&lt;SUB&gt;c&lt;/SUB&gt;.&#13;
Due to the adjustable contact area it was possible to measure high-resistance intrinsic&#13;
junctions (stacks) with a small number of contacts (n =&lt; 28) and often negligible small Josephson&#13;
current. These criteria were important to avoid heating effects. However, stacks always have&#13;
much higher quality compared with single contacts. The very sharp gap feature in the SIS-like&#13;
characteristics (Bi-2212) ruled out any anisotropic contribution to the symmetry of the&#13;
order parameter. The characteristics of SNS-stacks (n = 4) could be interpreted as a new effect&#13;
called &lt;I&gt;Intrinsic Multiple Andreev Reflection Effect (IMARE)&lt;/I&gt;, which has not been theoretically&#13;
understood yet.&lt;/P&gt;&#13;
&lt;P&gt;A reproducible fine structure at subgap voltages in the differential conductivity of BSCCO&#13;
Josephson junctions prooved the strong coupling between the AC-Josephson current and the optical&#13;
Raman-active phonons. The characteristic voltages &lt;I&gt;U&lt;SUB&gt;res&lt;/I&gt;&lt;/SUB&gt; have been found to be independent&#13;
of T, T&lt;SUB&gt;c&lt;/SUB&gt; and Δ. Applying an external magnetic field, &lt;I&gt;U&lt;SUB&gt;res&lt;/I&gt;&lt;/SUB&gt; remained constant but the amplitudes of&#13;
      the resonances showed the same Fraunhofer-like patterning as the critical&#13;
      Josephson current. The temperature dependence of the amplitudes have shown&#13;
      the typical Riedel singularity. The overall form of the fine structure was&#13;
      in good agreement with Raman scattering spectra of the optical phonon&#13;
      modes in this material. These results were verified by a new theoretical&#13;
      model by E.G. Maksimov et al.. Moreover, A.A. Abrikosov used this&#13;
      experimental results as a part to formulate a new theory of&#13;
      high-temperature superconducting cuprates. &lt;/P&gt;</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 530 Physik » 530 Physik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Physik » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>