<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>oai:elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de:3362</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:53:530</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">CRISTA-NF observations in the vicinity of the polar vortex</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Kalicinsky, Christoph</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2018-01-22</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/physik/diss2013/kalicinsky</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=3362</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20130213-125215-6</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-3480/dc1301.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;p&gt;CRISTA-NF (Cryogenic Infrared Spectrometers and Telescope for the Atmosphere - New&#13;
Frontiers) is an infrared limb sounder operated aboard the Russian high-altitude research&#13;
aircraft M55-Geophysica. The instrument measures thermal emissions of the atmosphere&#13;
in the spectral range from 4 – 15 µm between flight altitude ( ≈ 20 km) and around 5 km.&#13;
CRISTA-NF successfully participated in a large polar aircraft campaign within the EU FP7-&#13;
project RECONCILE (Reconciliation of essential process parameters for an enhanced predictability&#13;
of Arctic stratospheric ozone loss and its climate interactions) in Kiruna (Sweden)&#13;
from mid-January to mid-March in 2010. The preparation of the instrument for the campaign&#13;
including calibration measurements as well as performing the measurements during&#13;
the campaign were part of this work.&#13;
The limb emission spectra measured by CRISTA-NF are used to detect polar stratospheric&#13;
clouds (PSCs) and analyse their composition (NAT, STS, ice). PSCs were observed during&#13;
the first five flights of the campaign (2010-01-17 – 2010-01-25). A polar stratospheric ice&#13;
cloud, located above flight altitude during the first flight, is identified by means of the measurements&#13;
and meteorological data. The observation of polar stratospheric clouds composed&#13;
of (or clearly dominated by) a large amount of small NAT particles (mean radii &lt; 3 µm) can&#13;
be excluded by means of the analysis.&#13;
The CRISTA-NF measurements enable the derivation of several trace gas volume mixing&#13;
ratios (e.g. CFC-11, O&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;, HNO&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;) with an unprecedented vertical resolution of around 500 –&#13;
600m (or even less for CFC-11) for several kilometres below flight altitude and a horizontal&#13;
sampling along flight direction of ≈ 15 km. Comparisons with in-situ and remote sensing&#13;
measurements illustrate the quality of the retrieved volume mixing ratios.&#13;
Flight 11 of the aircraft campaign, which took place on March 2 in the vicinity of the polar&#13;
vortex, is analysed in detail. The observations of the polar vortex (including the bottom edge&#13;
of the vortex) and two filaments of different origin are presented. By means of O&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;-CFC-11-&#13;
relations these filaments are clearly identified as one vortex and one non-vortex filament.&#13;
The obtained results are compared with simulations by CLaMS (Chemical Lagrangian&#13;
Model of the Stratosphere) to assess the model performance in terms of transport and chemical&#13;
processes. CLaMS is capable of simulating even small scale transport structures. But the&#13;
comparisons indicate an underestimation of the ozone depletion inside the vortex. Additionally,&#13;
a model concept using artificial tracers, which enables the differentiation of air masses&#13;
with respect to their origin, is validated. The date of the artificial tracer initialisation is very&#13;
important to obtain simulation results, which are comparable to the observations. These&#13;
tracers can be used to obtain additional information about the air mass origin. Furthermore,&#13;
the artificial tracers are used to determine the impact of a vortex split event in December&#13;
2009 on the composition of air masses inside the vortex.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="de">&lt;p&gt;CRISTA-NF (Cryogenic Infrared Spectrometers and Telescope for the Atmosphere - New&#13;
Frontiers) ist ein Infrarot-Horizontsondierer, der an Bord des russischen Höhenforschungsflugzeuges&#13;
M55-Geophysica eingesetzt wird. Das Instrument misst thermische Emissionen&#13;
der Atmosphäre im Spektralbereich von 4 - 15 µm zwischen Flughöhe ( ≈ 20 km) und ungefähr&#13;
5 km. CRISTA-NF hat erfolgreich an einer großen polaren Flugzeugmesskampagne innerhalb&#13;
des EU FP7-Projekts RECONCILE (Reconciliation of essential process parameters for&#13;
an enhanced predictability of Arctic stratospheric ozone loss and its climate interactions)&#13;
in Kiruna (Schweden) von Mitte Januar bis Mitte März 2010 teilgenommen. Die Vorbereitung&#13;
des Instruments auf die Kampagne einschließlich der Kalibrationsmessungen, sowie&#13;
die Durchführung der Messungen während der Kampagne waren Bestandteil dieser Arbeit.&#13;
Die von CRISTA-NF gemessenen Emissionsspektren werden verwendet, um polare Stratosphärenwolken&#13;
(PSCs) zu erkennen und ihre Zusammensetzung (NAT, STS, Eis) zu untersuchen.&#13;
PSCs wurden während der ersten fünf Flüge der Kampagne (17.01. – 25.01.2010)&#13;
beobachtet. Mit Hilfe der Messungen und meteorologischen Daten kann eine stratosphärische&#13;
Eiswolke, die sich während des ersten Fluges oberhalb der Flughöhe befand, identifiziert&#13;
werden. Die Beobachtung von polaren Stratosphärenwolken, die aus einer großen Anzahl&#13;
von kleinen NAT-Teilchen (mittlerer Radius &lt; 3 µm) bestehen (oder klar dominiert sind),&#13;
kann mit Hilfe der Analyse ausgeschlossen werden.&#13;
Die Messungen ermöglichen die Bestimmung der Mischungsverhältnisse mehrerer Spurengase&#13;
(z.B. CFC-11, O&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;, HNO&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;) mit einer bis jetzt unerreichten vertikalen Auflösung von&#13;
ungefähr 500 – 600m (oder weniger für CFC-11) über mehrere Kilometer unterhalb der&#13;
Flughöhe und einem horizontalen Sampling von ≈ 15km entlang des Flugpfades. Vergleiche&#13;
mit insitu- und Fernerkundungsmessungen bestätigen die Qualität der bestimmten Mischungsverhältnisse.&#13;
Flug 11 der Kampagne, der am 2. März im Bereich des Polarwirbels stattfand, wird im Detail&#13;
untersucht. Während des Fluges wurden der Polarwirbel (einschließlich der Unterkante)&#13;
und zwei Filamente unterschiedlicher Herkunft beobachtet. Diese Filamente werden mit&#13;
Hilfe von O&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;-CFC-11-Relationen eindeutig als ein Vortexfilament und ein Filament anderer&#13;
Herkunft indentifiziert.&#13;
Die erzielten Ergebnisse werden mit CLaMS (Chemical Lagrangian Model of the Stratosphere)&#13;
Simulationen verglichen, um die Leistungsfähigkeit des Modells hinsichtlich Transport&#13;
und chemischen Prozessen zu beurteilen. CLaMS ermöglicht die Simulation sehr kleinskaliger&#13;
Transportprozesse. Die Vergleiche zeigen aber eine Unterschätzung des Ozonverlusts im Polarwirbel. Zusätzlich wird ein Modellkonzept, das künstliche Tracer verwendet&#13;
und die Unterscheidung von Luftmassen bezüglich ihrer Herkunft ermöglicht, überprüft.&#13;
Der Initialisierungszeitpunkt dieser Tracer ist dabei von großer Bedeutung, um Simulationsergebnisse&#13;
zu erhalten, die vergleichbar zu den Beobachtungen sind und zusätzliche Informationen&#13;
über die Luftmassenherkunft liefern. Zudem werden die künstlichen Tracer&#13;
verwendet, um die Auswirkung eines Wirbelsplits im Dezember 2009 auf die Luftmassenzusammensetzung&#13;
innerhalb des Wirbels zu bestimmen.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 530 Physik » 530 Physik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Physik » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>