<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>oai:elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de:338</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:53:530</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">Properties of systems with time delayed feedback</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Manffra, Elisangela Ferretti</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2002-06-17</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fb08/diss2002/manffra</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=338</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20020239</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-432/d080202.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;P ALIGN="justify"&gt;Nonlinear dynamics is a vast field complementary to classical&#13;
mechanics and statistical physics. Inside this field we have chosen to study dynamical&#13;
systems with time delayed feedback. Such systems appear as models in the sciences like&#13;
physics, biology, economy and have at the same time interesting theoretical properties&#13;
being good candidates to present high dimensional attractors. In this work delayed&#13;
systems are studied mainly in the limit of large delay were the scaling properties&#13;
of the attractors are observed. In chapter 2 we describe general properties of&#13;
periodic orbits of dynamical systems with feedback delay. In chapter 3 it is&#13;
shown that the marginal invariant density of chaotic attractors of scalar&#13;
systems with time delayed feedback has an asymptotic form in the limit of&#13;
large delay. We present general considerations, detailed analytical results&#13;
in low order perturbation theory for a particular model, and numerics for the&#13;
understanding of the asymptotic behaviour of the projections of the invariant&#13;
density. Our approach clarifies how the analytical properties of the model determine&#13;
the behaviour of the marginal invariant densities for large delay times. In chapter 4&#13;
properties of the topological and metric entropies are discussed and arguments for the&#13;
boundedness of both are given on the basis of periodic orbits and of the asymptotic&#13;
behavior of the invariant density. In chapter 5 we analyse the representation of maps&#13;
with time delayed feedback as coupled map lattices. We show that when the delayed map&#13;
has an anomalous exponent, this representation gives rise to infinitely large comoving&#13;
Lyapunov exponents of the spatially extended system. Additionally, we present a short&#13;
discussion regarding the anomalous error propagation in the case of continuous time,&#13;
i.e. delayed differential equations.&lt;/P&gt;</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 530 Physik » 530 Physik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Physik » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>