<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>oai:elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de:794</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:54:540</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">Emissions of Non-Methane Volatile Organic Compounds (NMVOC) from Vehicular Traffic in Europe</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Petrea, Dana Monica Violeta</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2007-07-13</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/chemie/diss2007/petrea</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=794</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20070698</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-891/dc0708.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">Vehicles with combustion engines are significant emitters of air pollutants and therefore have&#13;
a major influence on the environment. Road and tunnel studies are important tools in&#13;
evaluating the traffic emission models and in assessing the achievements of new technologies&#13;
for emission reduction.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;During three tunnel measurement campaigns namely: the Lundby Tunnel in Sweden (March,&#13;
2001), the Plabutsch Tunnel in Austria (November, 2001), the Kingsway Tunnel in England&#13;
(March, 2003) and an additional field experiment conducted along a section of the A656&#13;
motorway in Germany (May 2001), emissions from a large variety of vehicles were&#13;
investigated. The measurements covered the standard pollutants CO&lt;sub&gt;&lt;font size="2"&gt;2&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;, NO&lt;sub&gt;x&lt;/sub&gt; and non methane&#13;
volatile organic compounds (NMVOC).&#13;
&lt;br&gt;The data obtained from the measurements carried out in these European locations were&#13;
analysed with respect to the composition of the NMVOC mixture and the ratio of individual&#13;
compounds to benzene, CO&lt;sub&gt;&lt;font size="2"&gt;2&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; and NO&lt;sub&gt;x&lt;/sub&gt;. The NMVOC profiles observed in the tunnel as well as&#13;
in motorway measurements are in good agreement with the NMVOC profiles observed in&#13;
other campaigns. Among the aromatic hydrocarbons, toluene showed the highest mixing ratio,&#13;
whereas iso-pentane and propene had the highest mixing ratios among the alkanes and&#13;
alkenes, respectively. During the motorway experiment, vertical gradients were observed for&#13;
several NMVOC downwind of the motorway, in contrast to the upwind measurement site,&#13;
where NMVOC were constantly distributed. This indicates that the studied NMVOCs are&#13;
directly emitted by the traffic. The ratio toluene/benzene, which is an indicator of traffic&#13;
activity, was found in the performed studies to be: 3.09 in the Lundby Tunnel, 2.44 in the&#13;
Plabutsch Tunnel and 2.87 in the Kingsway Tunnel. During the A656 motorway experiment,&#13;
the ratio was constantly 2.5 except for stop and go periods when this could increase up to 3.6.&#13;
These values are higher than the previously measured ratios at traffic sites. This finding can be&#13;
explained by an over proportional decrease in the benzene emissions compared with the&#13;
aromatic compounds since the year 2000, when the new European Directive 98/70/EC&#13;
limiting the benzene content in gasoline to 1% started to be applied.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;Within the framework of extensive emission data validation experiments, the emission factors&#13;
for the Lundby Tunnel, the Plabutsch Tunnel and the A656 motorway have been determined&#13;
using the local traffic measurements in combination with new emission models. The models&#13;
provide emission factors with a temporal resolution of 20 min for the tunnel studies and 3 h&#13;
for the motorway study. The models took as input parameters the emission factors for CO&lt;sub&gt;&lt;font size="2"&gt;2&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; -&#13;
model 1; total hydrocarbons (THC) - model 2; and benzene, toluene, xylene (BTX) - model 3&#13;
from the Handbook Emission Factors for Road Transport (HBEFA) version 2.1. The input&#13;
parameters were modified by taking into account the slope gradients for the corresponding&#13;
measurement sites as well as the fleet composition and the driving pattern. By comparing the&#13;
direct calculated values of emission factors with the model 1 values, a good correlation of data&#13;
was obtained for the time intervals characterised by fluent and high traffic density. This&#13;
proves that the emission factors for CO&lt;sub&gt;&lt;font size="2"&gt;2&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; in the HBFEA 2.1 are a good estimation for the real&#13;
traffic situation. In the case of the Lundby and the Kingsway Tunnels, for all analysed&#13;
compounds except benzene, the emission factors calculated through model 1 were higher than&#13;
those obtained from model 2 and 3. For the Plabutsch Tunnel, the models 2 values were&#13;
higher. The data analysis of THC emission factors for the given traffic fleets was used in order&#13;
to clarify the discrepancy between measured and model calculated emission data.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;Two hypotheses were verified:&#13;
&lt;ul type="square"&gt;&#13;
&lt;li&gt;the THC emission factor of heavy duty vehicles is not correct; and/or&lt;/li&gt;&#13;
  &lt;li&gt;the percentage of catalyst vehicles determined from the fleet data analysis does&#13;
not reflect the reality, i.e. cars that are registered with catalyst in fact have a&#13;
malfunctioning catalyst and should be counted as non-catalyst vehicles with the&#13;
corresponding emission factor.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&#13;
The influence on the emission factors of the about 12% malfunctioning catalysts was&#13;
demonstrated.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;From the overall emission factors determined for weekday traffic, in the Plabutsch Tunnel, the&#13;
emission factors for light duty vehicles (LDV) and heavy duty vehicles (HDV) were&#13;
calculated by means of a regression analysis. The comparison of the LDV emission factors for&#13;
benzene and toluene obtained in the Plabutsch Tunnel, to data from a previous study&#13;
performed in the same tunnel shows a clear decrease of the emission factors in this tunnel.&#13;
The A656 motorway experiment, showed for benzene, toluene, ethylbenzene and 1,2,4&#13;
trimethylbenzene/decane that within the statistical errors the measured values are in good&#13;
agreement with the modeled ones.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;The results of the present study show that the NMVOC split is influenced by the fleet&#13;
composition and that the most important contribution to the NMVOC emissions results from&#13;
poorly maintained vehicles and those with malfunctioning catalysts. The results of the present&#13;
study reflect the current situation and the improvements of the European car fleet with respect&#13;
to hydrocarbons emissions after the introduction of the new European legislation in 2000.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 540 Chemie » 540 Chemie und zugeordnete Wissenschaften</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Chemie » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>