<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>oai:elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de:777</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:54:540</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">The Impact of NMVOC Emissions from Traffic and Solvent Use on Urban Air in Wuppertal - An Experimental Study</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Niedojadlo, Anita</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2005-09-15</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/chemie/diss2005/niedojadlo</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=777</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20050364</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-874/dc0510.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">In order to clarify the contribution of solvent use and road traffic to the total NMVOC emissions in&#13;
Germany, the NMVOC composition of the city air of Wuppertal was investigated. During three campaigns&#13;
NMVOC concentrations were measured at different locations in the city of Wuppertal. The measurements&#13;
covered volatile hydrocarbons in the range of C&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;-C&lt;sub&gt;10 &lt;/sub&gt;and oxygenated compounds such as alcohols,&#13;
ketones and esters.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
An assessment of the contribution from different emission sources to the observed NMVOC&#13;
concentrations was attempted with the Chemical Mass Balance (CMB) modelling technique. Two emission&#13;
source categories were investigated, namely road traffic and solvent use. Emission profiles for&#13;
traffic were obtained from measurements performed in a traffic tunnel, at a down-town street&#13;
intersection and during drives through the city and on free-ways. Solvent emission profiles were&#13;
investigated in the vicinity of different solvent factories and workshops in Wuppertal.&#13;
Apportionment analysis was performed for several receptor points located down-wind from the city&#13;
centre, in residential areas, in dense traffic areas and in industrial areas.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
The outcomes of the CMB analysis with the application of source profiles and receptor concentrations&#13;
obtained from the city measurements showed that traffic emission rather than solvent use determines&#13;
the ambient NMVOC composition. The maximal contribution of solvent use to the NMVOC emission&#13;
estimated on the basis of experimentally obtained results amounts to about 23% in the whole city&#13;
area of Wuppertal. Accordingly, it can be concluded that the contribution of solvent use to the&#13;
NMVOC concentrations in German cities falls in the range of a few to about 20%, provided that&#13;
Wuppertal can be considered as a typical German urban area with certain proportions of domestic&#13;
activities, traffic and various industries.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
The present work clearly shows that the experimentally observed proportions between traffic and&#13;
solvent use emissions are in strong disagreement with the German Emission Inventory which states,&#13;
that at present (reference year 2000) about 62% of the total NMVOC emissions originate from solvent&#13;
use and only 18% from road traffic.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 540 Chemie » 540 Chemie und zugeordnete Wissenschaften</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Chemie » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>