<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>oai:elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de:1505</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:6:62:620</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="de">Zur Identifikation selbsterregter aeroelastischer Kräfte im Zeitbereich</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Neuhaus, Christian</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2018-01-22</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbd/bauingenieurwesen/diss2010/neuhaus</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=1505</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20100820-102122-7</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-1655/dd1002.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;p&gt;The flow around a section of a line like slender structure, e.g. a mast or a wide spanned&#13;
bridge, interacts with the section’s motion. Forces as a reaction of the flow induce deformations&#13;
to the elastic structure. These deformations change the flow conditions&#13;
around the section and therewith the resulting forces. The forces on the section due to&#13;
the motion of the section itself are called aeroelastic or self excited forces. The interaction&#13;
leads to a coupled aeroelastic system including the mechanical properties of the&#13;
structure and the flow around it. Several phenomena may occur, related to the instability&#13;
of the coupled system. Aeroelastic phenomena, depending on the respective&#13;
mechanism, are called flutter, galloping and divergence. They play an important role&#13;
in aeronautics from the beginning of the 20th century. The relevance of these phenomena&#13;
for structures of civil engineering was disclosed by the disaster of the TACOMA&#13;
NARROWS Bridge 1940. Henceforward a great amount of scientific work in civil engineering&#13;
has been done and the aeroelastic stability is nowadays established for all vulnerable&#13;
structures.&#13;
The aeroelastic forces on an oscillating section can be described in the frequency and&#13;
in the time domain. This is often realised using linearization around a mean angle of&#13;
attack of the oncoming flow. The most common linear mathematical model is a time&#13;
domain model using frequency dependent parameters, called Scanlan derivatives. The&#13;
first part of this work presents the basic analytical models for the description of the&#13;
self excited forces and a comparison of experimental methods for their determination.&#13;
The consequences of the linearization on the applicability of the mathematical models&#13;
approximating the aeroelastic forces are educed.&#13;
In the second part a new experimental rig for the determination of SCANLAN derivatives&#13;
using the forced vibration method is presented and analysed. It has been mounted&#13;
in the boundary layer wind tunnel at Ruhr-Universität Bochum. This rig allows experiments&#13;
in a wide frequency range and in three degrees of freedom. Sets of 18&#13;
SCANLAN derivatives for three section models are shown and analysed regarding the&#13;
adaptability of instationary and quasi-steady theory. The interaction of self excited&#13;
forces and forces as a result of vortex shedding is observed analogous to former studies.&#13;
An identification of aeroelastic forces in the time domain, defined as indicial or step&#13;
response functions, is presented in the third part of this work. Two main strategies are&#13;
implemented and compared. An approximation of the frequency response functions,&#13;
given by the measured SCANLAN derivatives, by rational functions using terminology&#13;
of system theory and an identification in the time domain based on nonstationary motions&#13;
of the section are presented. Difficulties and constraints due to the determination&#13;
of time domain functions are worked out. The existence of indicial functions, derived&#13;
in the frequency domain using rational function approximation, for a two degree of&#13;
freedom model is verified in the time domain.&lt;/p&gt;</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>600 Technik, Medizin, angewandte Wissenschaften » 620 Ingenieurwissenschaften » 620 Ingenieurwissenschaften und zugeordnete Tätigkeiten</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Architektur und Bauingenieurwesen » Bauingenieurwesen » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>