<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>oai:elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de:718</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:54:540</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="de">Enzymatische Transformationen von Mono- und Disacchariden in Gegenwart von Lipasen und ß-Glycosidasen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Machmüller, Guido</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2005-10-14</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/chemie/diss2004/machmueller</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=718</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20050460</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-814/dc0420.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">Due to their overfunctionality the direct a) regioselective esterification or b) stereoselective&#13;
glycosidation of native, i.e. underivatised sugars (Fig. 1.1. Enzymic derivatisations of&#13;
D-glucose) poses a particularly challenging problem to synthetic organic chemists. In&#13;
most cases the use of suitable protected groups and/or multistep synthetic sequences -&#13;
all methods of low atom efficiency - provided in the past reasonably practical solutions.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;  &lt;img SRC="/images/machmueller/fig1_1.jpg" height=200 width="95%" ALT="Fig. 1-1. Enzymic derivatisations of D-glucose"&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#13;
Hydrolytic enzymes such as esterhydrolases (lipases) or glycosidases are known for&#13;
their capability of such derivatisations with high regio- and stereoselectivity, respectively.&#13;
However, successful applications of these transformations were largely limited by the&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;                    a) low solubility of native sugars in non-polar solvents,&#13;
&lt;br&gt;                         where lipasesdisplay their highest esterification activity&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;                    b) low activity (or inactivity) of glycosidases in organic solvents.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;In the past the problem was solved partially by using modified sugars like alkyl&#13;
glycosides and protected sugars, solvents like DMF or pyridine or solubilising agents like&#13;
phenyl boronic acid.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;In this work we provide satisfactory solutions for both problems using native sugars&#13;
throughout in non-toxic solvents. Inspired by the discovery of Prasad and Sørensen [1]&#13;
that 2-deoxy-D-ribose and D-ribose can be acylated by Novozym SP 435™ in THF, we&#13;
were able to demonstrate that also hexoses – which are practically insoluble in such&#13;
organic solvents – can be esterified with high regioselectivity and excellent yields.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Similarly, direct glycosylations via reverse hydrolysis of native, unprotected D-glucose&#13;
were achieved by compromising the low solubility of these materials in organic solvents&#13;
with the need of glucosidases for a microaqueous environment for activity. This way we&#13;
were able to produce b-glycosides in stoichiometric reactions with up to 50 % yield.&#13;
Yields of this magnitude were previously only achieved with excess of one reaction&#13;
partner and the use of activated glycosides.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 540 Chemie » 540 Chemie und zugeordnete Wissenschaften</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Chemie » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>