<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>oai:elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de:356</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:53:530</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">Ground state properties of antiferromagnetic spin-1/2 Heisenberg systems in external fields</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Fledderjohann, Andreas</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2001-05-23</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fb08/habi2001/fledderjohann</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=356</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20010694</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-450/h080101.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">The present work investigates the influence of external perturbations on the ground&#13;
states of spin-1/2 antiferromagnetic Heisenberg chains and two-dimensional spin&#13;
lattices. The lifting of the well-known zero-energy excitations (soft modes) of&#13;
the unperturbed Heisenberg chain due to suitably chosen periodicities of applied&#13;
perturbations is presented. The evolution of excitation energies and transition&#13;
matrix elements is described by a complete set of differential equations and scaling&#13;
solutions for small perturbations are discussed. A variety of topic&#13;
quasi-one-dimensional spin systems (spin-Peierls chain, spin ladders in different&#13;
geometries) are then embedded in the descriptive scheme of periodically perturbed&#13;
Heisenberg chains. In particular, the energy gaps and, most noticeable, the formation&#13;
of magnetization plateaus occurring in these systems are discussed in a single&#13;
prediction scheme related to the soft mode positions of the previously unperturbed&#13;
chain. Plateaus due to various kinds of perturbations are furthermore shown to be&#13;
observable in static correlation functions of the perturbed chain. Particular emphasis&#13;
is laid on the consideration of processes of spontaneous breaking of symmetry.&#13;
The latter aspect is discussed for translationally invariant perturbations that&#13;
do not provide an explicit change of the periodicity of the spin system. The&#13;
presented investigations finally turn to two-dimensional spin systems first addressing&#13;
the formation of a non-zero staggered magnetization (long range order) for increased&#13;
two-dimensionality in terms of a translationally invariant perturbed (helical) spin&#13;
system. Finally, first stages of a present study on the formation of magnetization&#13;
plateaus in square spin lattices with frustrating diagonal couplings are given.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 530 Physik » 530 Physik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Physik » Habilitationsschriften</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Habilitation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>