<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>oai:elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de:6130</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:53</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">Temperature Dependence of Carbon Kinetic Isotope Effect for the Oxidation Reaction of Ethane by Hydroxyl Radicals Under Atmospherically Relevant Conditions: Experimental and Theoretical Studies</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Piansawan, Tammarat</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2018-01-22</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/physik/diss2015/piansawan</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=6130</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20160831-114559-0</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-5915/dc1539.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;p&gt;       Ethane is the second most abundant hydrocarbon in the atmosphere, after methane, impacting on air quality, human health and climate. A quantification of its effects requires accurate knowledge of sources, processes along transport, and sinks. Carbon stable isotopic ratio investigations, complementarily to concentration measurements, were demonstrated to give more insight in source apportionment and atmospheric processing of organic compounds. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#13;
&#13;
       Yet, apportionment of atmospheric ethane sources, processing and sinks by using the &lt;sup&gt;13&lt;/sup&gt;C isotopic composition (&lt;i&gt;δ&lt;/i&gt;&lt;sup&gt;13&lt;/sup&gt;C) requires accurate knowledge of the stable carbon kinetic isotope effect (KIE) of its atmospheric degradation through oxidation by hydroxyl (OH) radicals. Moreover, the interpretation of tropospheric ambient data should account for the temperature dependence of KIE, since the tropospheric temperatures can vary extremely, over the range of 180-320 K. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#13;
&#13;
       In this work, the KIE temperature dependence for the oxidation of ethane by OH radicals in the tropospherically relevant temperature range was comprehensively investigated by experimental measurements and theoretical calculations. A framework to apply the observed KIE for interpreting ambient observations is presented. Experiments to determine the KIE temperature dependence of ethane oxidation by OH radicals were carried out with natural isotope abundances in the reactant, at ambient pressure, and in a temperature range of 243 to 303 K. Propane was used as a reference compound to verify the ethane chemistry. Chemical reactions were carried out in a ~12 L FEP reaction chamber, suspended in a newer developed temperature controlled oven. Using Thermal Desorption – Gas Chromatography – Combustion – Isotopic Ratio Mass Spectrometry (TD-GC-C-IRMS), the KIE of ethane with OH radical was derived from the temporal evolution of the ethane &lt;i&gt;δ&lt;/i&gt;&lt;sup&gt;13&lt;/sup&gt;C and concentration. At 303 ± 0.1 and 288.0 ± 0.3 K, the KIE values for the ethane oxidation by OH were found to be 7.45 ± 0.48 and 7.16 ± 0.54 ‰, respectively, showing a remarkable improvement of the measurement precision compared to the only available KIE value of 8.57 ± 1.95 ‰ at 296 ± 4 K reported by Anderson et al. (2004). Over the investigated temperature range, a slight increasing tendency of KIE toward lower temperatures was found, being approximately 0.4 ± 0.1 ‰ per 10 K.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#13;
 &#13;
       Quantum mechanical calculations together with semi-Classical Transition State Theory (SCTST) were employed to theoretically determine the temperature dependence of KIE for reaction of ethane with OH in the temperature range of 150 – 400 K. The goal of this study was to better understand the reaction kinetics, as well as to investigate KIE at temperatures where experimental work has strong limitations. The quantum mechanical calculations were performed employing the M06-2X density functional theory method with an aug-cc-pVTZ basis set. Energy refinements were carried out at high-level theory CCSD(T) using aug-cc-pVxZ (x = D,T,Q) basis set, with extrapolation to the complete basis set limit (CBS). &#13;
To this end, the 3-parameter expression aug-Schwartz6(DTQ) was employed in CBS. Tunneling effects and internal rotation treatments were also included in the KIE computation. For the first time, the anharmonicity of molecular vibration, and internal rotation was considered for the ethane + OH system. The theoretically computed KIE values are overestimated by approximately a factor of six, compared to the experimental results. However, a slightly negative temperature dependence of the theoretical KIE supports the experimental findings. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#13;
&#13;
       Implications of using the refined KIE values in investigating the isotopic fractioning of ethane during its chemical degradation in the atmosphere are discussed.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="de">&lt;p&gt;       Ethan ist der zweithäufigste Kohlenwasserstoff in der Atmosphäre nach Methan. Es beeinflusst die Luftqualität, die menschliche Gesundheit und das Klima. Eine Quantifizierung möglicher Auswirkungen erfordert genaue Kenntnisse über seine Quellen und Senken, sowie über die Prozesse, die während des atmosphärischen Transportes stattfinden. Mithilfe von Untersuchungen zu stabilen Kohlenstoffisotopenverhältnissen kann man, komplementär zu Konzentrationsmessungen, einen fundierten Einblick in die Quellenzuordnung und in die atmosphärischen Abbauprozesse von organischen Verbindungen gewinnen.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#13;
&#13;
       Die genaue Beschreibung von troposphärischen Ethanquellen, Prozessen und Senken anhand der &lt;sup&gt;13&lt;/sup&gt;C-Isotopenzusammensetzung (&lt;i&gt;δ&lt;/i&gt;&lt;sup&gt;13&lt;/sup&gt;C) erfordert präzise Kenntnis des kinetischen Isotopeneffekts (KIE) des atmosphärischen Abbaus von Ethan durch Oxidation mit Hydroxylradikalen (OH). Darüber hinaus sollte die Temperaturabhängigkeit des KIEs aufgeklärt werden, um Feldmessungen zu interpretieren, da die Temperaturen in der Troposphäre von 180 bis zu 320 K variieren können.&#13;
In dieser Arbeit wurde die KIE-Temperaturabhängigkeit für die Oxidation von Ethan durch OH-Radikale durch umfassende experimentelle Messungen und theoretischen Berechnungen untersucht. Die Implikationen einer Anwendung des beobachteten KIEs für die Interpretation von Feldmessungen werden diskutiert. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#13;
&#13;
       Experimente zur Bestimmung der Temperaturabhängigkeit des KIEs für die Ethanoxidation durch OH-Radikale wurden mit einem Reaktanten, der eine natürliche Isotopenhäufigkeit aufwies, bei Umgebungsdruck und im Temperaturbereich von 243 bis 303 K durchgeführt. Propan wurde als Referenzverbindung verwendet, um die Ethanchemie zu verifizieren. Chemische Reaktionen wurden in einer ~12 L FEP-Reaktionskammer durchgeführt. Diese befand sich in einem neu entwickelten, temperaturgesteuerten Ofen. Eine Thermodesorption – Gaschromatographie – Verbrennung – Isotopenverhältnis–Massenspektrometrie (TD-GC-C-IRMS) Methode wurde entwickelt und getestet. KIE für die Reaktion des Ethans mit OH wurde aus dem zeitlichen Verlauf der &lt;i&gt;δ&lt;/i&gt;&lt;sup&gt;13&lt;/sup&gt;C und der Konzentration von Ethan abgeleitet. Die gemessenen Werte von 7,45 ± 0,48 ‰ bei 303 ± 0,1 K und  7,16 ± 0,54 ‰ bei 288,0 ± 0,3 K, zeigen eine bemerkenswerte Verbesserung der Messgenauigkeit im Vergleich zu dem KIE-Wert von 8,57 ± 1,95 ‰, bestimmt von Anderson et al. (2004) bei 296 ± 4 K. Über den untersuchten Temperaturbereich wurde eine leichte steigende Tendenz des KIEs (0,4 ± 0,1 ‰ pro 10 K) zu niedrigeren Temperaturen hin gefunden.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#13;
&#13;
       Quantenmechanischen Rechnungen wurden zusammen mit der semi-klassischen Eyring-Theorie (SCTST) angewendet, um die Temperaturabhängigkeit des KIEs für die Reaktion von Ethan mit OH in einem Temperaturbereich von 150 bis 400 K theoretisch zu bestimmen. Das Ziel dieses Teils der Arbeit war es, die Reaktionskinetik besser zu verstehen, sowie Aussagen über den KIE bei Temperaturen zu treffen, bei denen die experimentelle Bestimmung nicht möglich ist. Die quantenmechanischen Rechnungen wurden unter Benutzung der Dichtefunktionalmethode M06-2X zusammen mit einem aug-cc-pVTZ Niveau des Basissatzes durchgeführt. Bei dem verwendeten hohen Niveau der Theorie CCSD(T) wurden Verfeinerungen der Energie  mithilfe eines aug-cc-pVxZ (x = D, T, Q) Basissatzes und Extrapolation auf die gesamte Basissatzlimit (CBS) eingesetzt. Dafür wurde der Drei-Parameter-Ausdruck aug-Schwartz6(DTQ) in CBS verwendet. Der Tunneleffekt und die Behandlung der Innenrotation wurden ebenfalls in den KIE Berechnungen berücksichtigt. Zum ersten Mal wurde für das System Ethan + OH die Anharmonizität der Molekülschwingung betrachtet. Im Vergleich zu den experimentellen Ergebnissen sind die theoretisch berechneten KIE Werte ungefähr um  einen Faktor von sechs überschätzt. Eine leicht negative Temperaturabhängigkeit der theoretischen KIE unterstützt jedoch den experimentellen Befund.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#13;
&#13;
       Implikationen der Verwendung von verbesserten KIE-Werten in den Untersuchungen zur isotopischen Fraktionierung von Ethan während seiner chemischen Abbau in der Atmosphäre werden diskutiert.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 530 Physik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Physik » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>