<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>oai:elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de:10351</id><datestamp>2020-03-09</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:53:530</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">A lattice QCD study of nucleon structure with physical quark masses</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Hasan, Nesreen</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2020-03-09</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/physik/diss2019/hasan</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=10351</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20200305-121945-5</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.25926/19rj-ej28</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-9678/dc1949.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;p&gt;In this work, we compute various nucleon structure observables using the lattice regularization&#13;
of quantum chromodynamics, lattice QCD. Our calculations are performed&#13;
using 2 + 1-flavor ensembles with clover-improved Wilson fermions and cover three&#13;
sets of observables:&lt;br&gt;&#13;
The first set includes the computation of nucleon isovector axial, scalar, and tensor&#13;
charges. In particular, we focus on controlling the unwanted contributions from&#13;
excited states. Those charges quantify the coupling of nucleons to quark-level interactions&#13;
and play an important role in the analysis of the Standard Model and Beyond&#13;
the Standard Model (BSM) physics.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
The second set of observables includes the nucleon charge and axial radii measured&#13;
using a new and model-independent approach. We developed this approach to enable&#13;
the computation of the nucleon radii directly at zero momentum transfer and avoid the&#13;
systematic uncertainty originating from the large extrapolation commonly included&#13;
in the conventional methods used for measuring quantities like the nucleon charge&#13;
radius. Systematic errors of this kind have been proposed as a possible explanation&#13;
of the radius puzzle which refers to the &gt; 5σ discrepancy between the experimental&#13;
electronic and muonic determinations of the charge radius of the proton.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
We perform the calculations of the nucleon charges and radii on two gauge ensembles&#13;
at the physical pion mass and with different lattice spacings.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
The last set of our calculation is devoted to measuring the nucleon axial form factors.&#13;
This calculation includes both quark-connected and -disconnected diagrams, which&#13;
allows us to determine the up, down, and strange form factors. This calculation is&#13;
done using a single ensemble with pion mass 317 MeV.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 530 Physik » 530 Physik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Physik » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>