<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>oai:elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de:10912</id><datestamp>2020-09-07</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:53:530</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">Lagrangian Simulation of StratosphericWater Vapour: Impact of Large-Scale Circulation and Small-Scale Transport Processes</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Poshyvailo, Liubov</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2020-09-07</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/physik/diss2020/poshyvailo</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=10912</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20200907-104252-6</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.25926/9mcs-tm42</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-10203/dc2010.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;p&gt;The atmospheric global circulation, also referred to as the Brewer-Dobson circulation, controls&#13;
the composition of the upper troposphere and lower stratosphere (UTLS). The UTLS trace gas&#13;
composition, in turn, crucially affects climate. In particular, UTLS water vapour (H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O) plays&#13;
a significant role in the global radiation budget. Therefore, a realistic representation of H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&#13;
and Brewer-Dobson circulation, is critical for accurate model predictions of future climate and&#13;
circulation changes.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
This thesis is structured in two main parts: focussing on the (i) effect of model uncertainties&#13;
(due to tropical tropopause temperature, horizontal transport and small-scale mixing) on stratospheric&#13;
H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O, and on the (ii) uncertainties in estimating Brewer-Dobson circulation trends from&#13;
the observed H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O trends.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
The results presented here are based largely on stratospheric H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O studies with the Chemical&#13;
Lagrangian Model of the Stratosphere (CLaMS). Firstly, to investigate the robustness of simulated&#13;
H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O with respect to different meteorological datasets, we examine CLaMS driven by the&#13;
ERA-Interim reanalysis from the European Centre of Medium-RangeWeather Forecasts, and the&#13;
Japanese 55-year Reanalysis (JRA-55). Secondly, to assess the effects of horizontal transport,&#13;
we carry out CLaMS simulations, with transport barriers, along latitude circles: at the equator,&#13;
at 15° N/S and at 35° N/S. To investigate the sensitivity of simulated H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O regarding small-scale&#13;
atmospheric mixing, we vary the strength of parametrized small-scale mixing in CLaMS. Finally,&#13;
to assess the reliability of estimated long-term Brewer-Dobson circulation changes from&#13;
stratospheric H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O, we apply different methods of calculating mean age of air trends involving&#13;
two approximations: instantaneous entry mixing ratio propagation, and a constant correlation&#13;
between mean age of air and the fractional release factor of methane. The latter assumption&#13;
essentially means assuming a constant correlation between the mean age of air and the mixing&#13;
ratio of long-lived trace gases.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
The results of this thesis show significant differences in simulated stratospheric H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O (about&#13;
0.5 ppmv) due to uncertainties in the tropical tropopause temperatures between the two reanalysis&#13;
datasets, JRA-55 and ERA-Interim. The JRA-55 based simulation is significantly moister,&#13;
when compared to ERA-Interim, due to a warmer tropical tropopause of approximately 2 K.&#13;
Moreover, through introducing artificial transport barriers in CLaMS, we suppress certain horizontal&#13;
transport pathways. These transport experiments demonstrate that the Northern Hemisphere&#13;
subtropics have a strong moistening effect on global stratospheric H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O. Interhemispheric&#13;
exchange shows only a very weak effect on stratospheric H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O. Small-scale mixing mainly increases&#13;
troposphere-stratosphere exchange, causing an enhancement of stratospheric H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O, particularly,&#13;
along the subtropical jets in the summer hemisphere and in the Northern hemispheric&#13;
monsoon regions. In particular, the Asian and American monsoon systems, during boreal summer,&#13;
turn out as regions especially sensitive to changes in small-scale mixing.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
The estimated mean age of air trends from stratospheric H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O changes, in general, are&#13;
strongly determined by the assumed approximations. Depending on the investigated region of&#13;
the stratosphere, and the considered period, the error of estimated mean age of air trends can be&#13;
large. Interestingly, depending on the period, the effects from both approximations can also be&#13;
opposite, and may even cancel out.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
The results of this thesis provide new insights into the leading processes that control stratospheric&#13;
H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O and its trends, and are therefore relevant for improving climate model predictions.&#13;
Furthermore, the results of this work can be used for evaluating the uncertainties of estimated&#13;
stratospheric circulation changes from global satellite measurements.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 530 Physik » 530 Physik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Physik » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>