<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>oai:elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de:6100</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:51</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">Equivariant Vector Bundles and Rigid Cohomology on Drinfeld's Upper Half Space over a Finite Field</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Kuschkowitz, Mark</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2018-01-22</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/mathematik/diss2016/kuschkowitz</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=6100</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20160822-115624-2</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-5885/dc1618.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;p&gt;Fix a finite field k and let X be Drinfeld's Upper Half Space over k of dimension n. Let S be the polynomial ring over k in n+1 variables, let G be the algebraic k-group scheme associated with the general linear group of degree n+1 and let Y=Proj S. Fix an algebraic action of G on Y. &#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;     &#13;
	In the first part of this thesis, the global sections F(X) on X of a G-equivariant vector bundle F on Y are considered as a G(k)-representation. Due to a theorem of Orlik (2008), the computation of F(X) essentially reduces to the computation of the local cohomologies of F on Y with support in a k-rational closed subvariety Z. This local cohomology is considered as a representation of a certain parabolic subgroup P of G which stabilizes Z resp. of its Levi subgroup L. Three types of descriptions of these local cohomology modules are given:&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#13;
In the case where F arises from a representation of the stabilizer of a chosen base point of Y, a very general result on the structure of the local cohomology of F on Y with support in Z as an L-module is translated from Orlik's results.&#13;
For general F, an even coarser strucutre result is proved by using an affine projection of Y onto Y-Z. In particular, when F equals the structure sheaf or a sheaf of differential forms on Y (resp. a Serre twist of either sheaf), this result is made very precise.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
In the case where the graded S-module associated with F is generated in degrees &lt;2, a higher divided power version of the distribution algebra of G is used to for a more conceptual approach to the description of the local cohomologies mentioned in terms of the unipotent radical of P.&#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#13;
In the second part of this thesis, the rigid cohomology of X is computed in two ways. &#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;     	The first method proceeds by computation of the rigid cohomology of the complement &#13;
of X in Y (which is projective itself, thus its rigid cohomology is simply the de Rham cohomology of an associated rigid-analytic tube). Then application of the associated long exact sequence for rigid cohomology with proper supports yields the rigid cohomology of X. &#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;     	The second method proceeds by direct computation of the direct limit of the de Rham cohomologies of a certain cofinal family of strict open neighborhoods of the tube of X in the ambient rigid-analytic projective space. &#13;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;     	The resulting cohomology formula has been known since 2007, when Große-Klönne proved that it is the same as the one obtained from l-adic cohomology using different methods.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 510 Mathematik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Mathematik und Informatik » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>