<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>oai:elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de:9010</id><datestamp>2018-12-04</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:54</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">BODIPY as building blocks for Near InfraRed-Active Organic Compounds</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Squeo, Benedetta Maria</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2018-12-04</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/chemie/diss2018/squeo</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=9010</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20181204-140514-6</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-8385/dc1818.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;p&gt;BODIPY (4,4-difluoro-4-bora-3a,4a-diaza-s-indacene) dyes are promising building blocks for the synthesis of NIR organic materials. Compared to other dye classes, these systems offer unique attractions such as excellent thermal/photochemical stability, intense absorption/emission profiles, negligible triplet-state formation, and small Stokes shifts. Their optoelectronic and semiconductor properties can be finely tuned via facile synthetic modifications on the dipyrromethene core.&lt;/p&gt; &#13;
&lt;p&gt;In this PhD thesis new organic NIR materials (both π-conjugated polymers and small molecules) based on α,β-unsubstituted meso-positioning thienyl BODIPY have been developed, and their optoelectronic properties and their performances when applied in organic light emitting diodes and organic solar cells have been characterized and evaluated.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;In more details, on the one hand donor-acceptor quarterthiophene-BODIPY polymers have been synthesized and the dependence of their optoelectronic, electrochemical and charge transporting properties of the resulting α,β-unsubstituted meso-positioning thienyl BODIPY quaterthiophene-based polymers from the alkyl side chain position have been studied. Tail-to-tail (TT) positioning of the alkyl side chains at the two central thiophenes of the quaterthiophene segment results in lower E&lt;sub&gt;g&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;opt&lt;/sup&gt;, higher energy levels and increased hole mobility as compared to head-to-head (HH) positioning. However, even though the synthesized polymers exhibit high electron affinity, higher even than that of the fullerene PC&lt;sub&gt;71&lt;/sub&gt;BM, they present only p-type behavior in field effect transistors (FETs) independent of the alkyl side chain positioning. Furthermore, one of the synthesized copolymers containing a vinylene bond in the middle of the quarterthiophene segment exhibits a panchromatic absorption spectrum ranging from 300 nm to 1100 nm and an optical band gap around 1 eV, suitable for near infrared (NIR) organic photovoltaic applications as electron donor. Preliminary power conversion efficiency (PCE) in bulk heterojunction (BHJ) solar cells of 1.1% in polymer:[6,6]-phenyl-C&lt;sub&gt;71&lt;/sub&gt;-butyric acid methyl ester (PC&lt;sub&gt;71&lt;/sub&gt;BM) [1:3 weight ratio] has been achieved, demonstrating very interesting and promising photovoltaic characteristics, such as good fill factor (FF) and open circuit voltage (V&lt;sub&gt;oc&lt;/sub&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, BODIPY unit have been symmetrically conjugate with oligothienyls in a “metal-free” A-D-A (acceptor-donor-acceptor) oligomer emitting in the near-infrared (NIR) thanks to the delocalisation of the BODIPY low-lying lowest unoccupied molecular orbital (LUMO) over the oligothienyl moieties, as confirmed by density functional theory (DFT). A PL efficiency of 20% in the solid state (vs. 30% in dilute solutions) has been retained by incorporating such a dye in a wider gap polyfluorene matrix and demonstrate organic light-emitting diodes (OLEDs) emitting at 720 nm. We achieved external quantum efficiencies (EQEs) up to 1.1%, the highest value recorded so far by a “metal-free” NIR-OLED not intentionally benefitting from triplet-triplet annihilation. These results demonstrate for the first time the promise of A-D-A type dyes for NIR OLEDs applications thereby paving the way for further optimization.&lt;/p&gt;</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 540 Chemie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Mathematik und Informatik » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>