<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>oai:elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de:283</id><datestamp>2018-01-22</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:53:530</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="de">Feldinduzierte Elektronenemission von Diamantschichten und Kohlenstoff-Nanostrukturen</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Göhl, Achim</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2001-01-05</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fb08/diss2000/goehl</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=283</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20010047</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-377/d080002.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;P ALIGN="justify"&gt;For Field Emission Displays (FEDs) and other vacuum microlelectronics applications, arrays of electron sources are required, which deliver electron currents via field-induced electron emission (FEE). Commercially available arrays of Mo- or Si-microtips emit strongly and nearly uniform but are unstable due to the sensible structures. Therefore a coating of the microtips with hard diamond-like materials is under investigation. Another approach is the development of cost-effective, stable, strong, and uniform emitting flat cathode materials, e.g. on the basis of diamond films or carbon nanotubes (CNTs).&lt;/P&gt;&#13;
&lt;P ALIGN="justify"&gt;In this work, the FEE of local, µm-sized spots of dielectric diamond films, nanocrystalline diamond coatings on flat substrates and tip arrays, and CNTs were investigated by means of a field emission scanning microscope (FESM). For these analyses, the FESM was equipped with a new scanning mode, improving the lateral resolution by a factor of 20 to 100 nm.&lt;/P&gt;&#13;
&lt;P ALIGN="justify"&gt;Highly reproducible measurements at different temperatures, for both polarities, and in anode-cathode contact as well as in non-contact were performed on nominally undoped, dielectric and heated (300°C, 30 min) chemical vapour deposited &lt;I&gt;diamond films &lt;/I&gt;of several µm in thickness. FEE occurs over the entire surface of diamond grains on a scale of 100 nm. For vacuum fields between 250 V/µm and 700 V/µm and corresponding local current densities of 0.5 mA/cm&lt;SUP&gt;2&lt;/SUP&gt; to 500 mA/cm&lt;SUP&gt;2&lt;/SUP&gt;, the FEE is limited by the Poole-Frenkel bulk conduction mechanism, i.e. the electron transport occurs by a thermally assisted electron hopping through traps. Neither the injection of electrons at the substrate-diamond interface nor the extraction at the diamond-vacuum interface is limiting the FEE. An energetic gap between the traps and the conduction band minimum W&lt;SUB&gt;Tr-CB&lt;/SUB&gt; of 0.62 eV as well as a trap density of about 5·10&lt;SUP&gt;18&lt;/SUP&gt;/cm&lt;SUP&gt;3&lt;/SUP&gt; were derived. It was calculated, that diamond films with traps and W&lt;SUB&gt;Tr-CB&lt;/SUB&gt;≤0.4 eV would be suitable for applications at low onset field E&lt;SUB&gt;on&lt;/SUB&gt;(5 nA) &lt; 10 V/µm.&lt;/P&gt;&#13;
&lt;P ALIGN="justify"&gt;Electrophoretically deposited &lt;I&gt;nanocrystalline diamond on Si tips&lt;/I&gt; of 100 µm in height, apex radius of 20 nm and a density of 3900/mm&lt;SUP&gt;2&lt;/SUP&gt; showed an onset field strength E&lt;SUB&gt;on&lt;/SUB&gt;(5nA) of 4.5 V/µm and a maximum reproducible current density j&lt;SUB&gt;Max&lt;/SUB&gt; of 1.9 mA/mm&lt;SUP&gt;2&lt;/SUP&gt; over mm&lt;SUP&gt;2&lt;/SUP&gt;-sized areas. Due to their good uniformity with 40 % significantly emitting tips, such arrays are suitable for FED applications. &lt;/P&gt;&#13;
&lt;P ALIGN="justify"&gt;Electrophoretically deposited &lt;I&gt;nanocrystalline diamond on a flat silicon substrate&lt;/I&gt; showed an E&lt;SUB&gt;on&lt;/SUB&gt; of 203 V/µm and local j&lt;SUB&gt;Max&lt;/SUB&gt; of 150 mA/mm&lt;SUP&gt;2&lt;/SUP&gt;. The E&lt;SUB&gt;on&lt;/SUB&gt; of chemical vapor deposited &lt;I&gt;nanocrystalline diamond in a graphitic matrix&lt;/I&gt; was 55 V/µm and j&lt;SUB&gt;Max&lt;/SUB&gt; was 5 mA/mm&lt;SUP&gt;2&lt;/SUP&gt;. Only a small number of spots contributed significantly to the FEE of mm&lt;SUP&gt;2&lt;/SUP&gt;-sized areas of both nanocrystalline coatings, thus providing insufficient uniformity for applications yet.&lt;/P&gt;&#13;
&lt;P ALIGN="justify"&gt;Free-standing &lt;I&gt;carbon nanotubes&lt;/I&gt; of 10-20 µm in height and of about 40 nm in diameter emitted strongly at E&lt;SUB&gt;on &lt;/SUB&gt; &gt; 8.6 V/µm and showed a local j&lt;SUB&gt;Max&lt;/SUB&gt; of 2 mA/mm&lt;SUP&gt;2&lt;/SUP&gt;. Due to their non-uniform length and non-uniform alignment, only a small number of spots emitted significantly over mm&lt;SUP&gt;2&lt;/SUP&gt;-sized areas. More stable emission up to j&lt;SUB&gt;Max&lt;/SUB&gt; = 10 mA/mm&lt;SUP&gt;2&lt;/SUP&gt; was measured from CNTs, which were embedded in a diamond-like matrix. This approach seems to be necessary for FED-applications.&lt;/P&gt;</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 530 Physik » 530 Physik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Physik » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>deu</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>