<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/  http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><id>oai:elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de:10890</id><datestamp>2020-09-03</datestamp><setSpec>DDC:5:53:530</setSpec>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en">Aspects of quark mass dependence in lattice QCD</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Varnhorst, Lukas</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2020-09-03</dc:date>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/edocs/dokumente/fbc/physik/diss2020/varnhorst</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DocumentServlet?id=10890</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>urn:nbn:de:hbz:468-20200903-103412-9</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>https://doi.org/10.25926/vrwh-6t66</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>http://elpub.bib.uni-wuppertal.de/servlets/DerivateServlet/Derivate-10192/dc2011.pdf</dc:identifier>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en">&lt;p&gt;The goals of the thesis where to calculate the quark mass dependencies of several observables.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
In a first part we determined the nucleon sigma terms and quark contents. We calculated the&#13;
up, down, strange, and charm quark contents from first principles using lattice QCD. We used&#13;
a perturbative heavy quark expansion to calculate the bottom and top quark contents. These&#13;
expansion are expected to be valid for these two quark flavors. We checked their validity also&#13;
in the case of the charm quark where the errors of the truncated perturbative expansion are&#13;
expected to be larger then for the top and bottom quarks. We find that our lattice determination is in very good agreement with the perturbative calculation. A key part to our lattice calculation is that we employed several fermion actions in our analysis and leveraged the different advantages&#13;
they offer for different parts of the calculation.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
For the calculation of the sigma terms we employed the Feynman-Hellmann method. Our&#13;
results are consistent with other lattice determinations. Despite this, we find that recent phenomenological calculation (s. [115]) based on pion-nucleon scattering predict a slightly larger&#13;
light sigma terms then most lattice calculations, including our own ab-inito calculation. It would&#13;
be interesting to study the source of this discrepancy.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
Our results allow us to calculate the nucleon-Higgs coupling with an error of about 30 %. We&#13;
believe that our results are of high relevance to direct dark matter detection experiments. It is&#13;
remarkable that, in the &lt;i&gt; N&lt;sub&gt;f&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/i&gt; = 6 theory, a large fraction of the Higgs nucleon coupling originates from the heavy quark flavors; while they contribute only through quantum fluctuations that are suppressed by their mass, their Higgs coupling is also large, because they are heavy. Both effects almost cancel.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
In a second part, we calculated the dependence of the kaon mass splitting on the light quark&#13;
mass splitting and the electromagnetic charges of the light quarks. We where able to quantify&#13;
the amount of violation of Dashen’s theorem. We used our result to infer the ratio of the light&#13;
quark masses. The calculation was carried out in a partially quenched setup. While we estimated&#13;
the error made by using this approximation, it would be interesting to carry out this calculation&#13;
in a fully dynamic QED+QCD setting.</dc:description>
          <dc:subject>500 Naturwissenschaften und Mathematik » 530 Physik » 530 Physik</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject>Fakultät für Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften » Physik » Dissertationen</dc:subject>
          <dc:type>Wissenschaftliche Abschlussarbeiten » Dissertation</dc:type>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
        </oai_dc:dc>